<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180325ee3p0004k" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325253499</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p0004k" fid="an"/><Num value="1375" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Book Review Desk; SECTBR</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm">FICTION</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">East Side Story</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>MRS.</Para><Para>By Caitlin Macy</Para><Para>343 pp. Little, Brown and Company. $27.</Para><Para>We're all familiar with the ego-bruising, chest-thumping uncertainties of social ritual. Consider the wedding and funeral industries, which prey on the anxieties of nervous brides ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By ALEX KUCZYNSKI </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"/><Code value="namz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gbook"/><Code value="ncolu"/><Code value="nrvw"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="gent"/><Code value="ncat"/><Code value="nfact"/><Code value="nfce"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325253499</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p0004k" fid="an"/><Num value="1375" fid="wc"/><Num value="6397" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="070223" fid="upt"/><Time value="070223" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">13</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId276566134"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash75043AC9AE25589D"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC42497"/><Code value="FSPRBC213843"/><Code value="FSPRBC214404"/><Code value="FSPRBC234480"/><Code value="FSPRBC808880"/><Code value="FSPRBC852186"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="234480"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gbook"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Books</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="42497"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="213843"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncolu"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Columns</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="808880"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="852186"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nrvw"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Reviews</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="42497"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="213843"/><CodeA name="rule" value="214404"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gbook"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gent"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Arts/Entertainment</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gbook"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Content Types</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:ncolu"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nfact"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Factiva Filters</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nfce"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">C&amp;E Exclusion Filter</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Book Review Desk Review </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Book Review Desk; SECTBR</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field">FICTION</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">East Side Story</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>MRS.</Para><Para>By Caitlin Macy</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>343 pp. Little, Brown and Company. $27.</Para><Para>We're all familiar with the ego-bruising, chest-thumping uncertainties of social ritual. Consider the wedding and funeral industries, which prey on the anxieties of nervous brides and grieving family members. No less horrifying are the rites surrounding entry into some of New York's most exclusive private schools, a Boschian dreamscape of social posturing in which mothers judge one another by their coiffures, their chauffeured Escalades and their husbands' net worth.</Para><Para>In ''Mrs.,'' Caitlin Macy's bristling, funny and ultimately savage novel, set in the postlapsarian year of 2009, St. Timothy's is the stage for these parents' ambitions and affectations. The rituals of pick-up and drop-off become more than mere transportation; every day, they could double as a couture runway show starring a new diva or a PBS special featuring an anthropological two-step. One morning, a mother asserts her alpha status swathed in fur; the next, a father handles midday pick-up to show he doesn't work for the Man -- because he is the Man.</Para><Para>''Mrs.'' centers on the seemingly tidy lives of three women. Philippa Lye, a lissome brunette former model, is married to Jed Skinker, a white-shoe investment banker at his family's firm. Minnie Curtis is the perfectly coifed, seriously hot Latina wife of a rising star at Invictus Capital. Yale-educated Gwen Hogan was a chemical engineer before she became a mother.</Para><Para>But take a few steps into their world and the secrets and insecurities come into focus. Philippa, although still beautiful, is a drunk and has been for a long time -- maybe because she's keeping a terrible secret about her past. Minnie was raised in poverty and sexually abused by her stepfather; her mother was a sleep-all-day-on-the-sofa alcoholic. Oh, and her husband, John D. Curtis (who added the ''D'' to sound more like a Rockefeller), is a sexual predator dating back to his undergraduate years.</Para><Para>Gwen's husband is a prosecutor in the U.S. Attorney's Office who makes $150,000 a year, many multiples less than the other fathers at St. Tim's. Their daughter attends on a scholarship. (As the letter of admission puts it, they owe a ''reduced commitment.'') And -- the horror! -- they live in a no-doorman building in Yorkville. But Gwen's husband has his own secret: about his investigations into the financial dealings between the other two husbands.</Para><Para>In this world, even the privileged are hyper-tense, constantly measuring themselves against their peers. On play dates, the mothers worry about how to hold their silverware: ''Whether she ought to cross, American-style, or keep her fork facing down, European-style.'' They worry about whether they overthanked the doorman -- the richest moms always maintain an aloof, almost distracted separation from the help -- and whether to dress their household staff in uniforms. They bully themselves into submission. ''We deflected compliments,'' Macy writes, Greek-chorus style. ''We made deprecating comments about how much we had eaten at the last meal and how lazy we were and how badly we sucked at tennis when in fact we were not at all lazy and we were very good tennis players.''</Para><Para>Macy artfully observes the elite custom of seeming never to care about anything. Questions, she notes, are proffered only as segues into bragging: ''Do your children...? Because we. ...'' As a Yale student trying to disguise his middle-class upbringing, John D. Curtis wears the hems of his jeans flamboyantly long so his loafers flatten them as he walks, a hallmark of slouchy, preppie indifference. And as the mothers watch another mother hugging and kissing her daughter after school, ''each one of us remembered, in a depth of bumming-out, the moment, in preadolescence, when we had learned from either our parents or our peers that one had to pretend not to care.'' Even the marriages are chilly: ''A certain type of man needed a wife to help keep things impersonal, as if marriage were a barracks, and inspection from the outside could come at any time.'' Brrrr.</Para><Para>Macy is well versed in the rigors of schadenfreude and social judgment. The descendant of an old-money family that had lost its fortune by her father's generation, she attended an East Coast boarding school, then went to Yale on scholarship. As she revealed in 2009 on the publication of her previous book, ''Spoiled,'' a story collection about class distinctions among the privileged, her husband had lost jobs at a bank and a hedge fund, and her older daughter had been rejected by all the private schools they applied to for kindergarten. (I'm pretty sure things have turned out all right for them.)</Para><Para>Macy has clearly observed the world of aspiration and failure up close, which is why ''Mrs.'' has such a tonic air of authenticity. Within this novel, there's almost an entire treatise on the decorating habits of the wealthy -- and not so wealthy. One mother can't be trusted to weigh in on another's apartment because her own home is ''floor to ceiling Pottery Barn -- giant clocks, lobster traps for coffee tables, apothecary shop for a kitchen.'' Minnie's kitchen is ''vast, suburban-size,'' glistening ''like an operating theater with menacing, hyper-clean appliances.'' One townhouse is so grand that its parlor floor makes the gathered parents look dumpy, ''as if the room had been made for a larger, more significant race, one that didn't have to stuff itself into pantyhose or pay through the nose for monthly highlights in a condescending salon on Madison.'' Even among wealthy people, there are levels of fabulousness.</Para><Para>The novel's attention to such interior detail makes you wonder if Macy is curating the scenery for an inevitable cable rendition, the way Liane Moriarty's novel ''Big Little Lies'' was adapted for HBO. In fact, the stories are similar: Both use the children's school as a stage, with the parents as the stars. ''Mrs.'' is set among the Manhattan 1-percenters who count wine cellars and his-and-hers drivers as necessities, just as the TV version of ''Big Little Lies'' is set among the wealthy of Monterey. And as both stories unfold, the pursuit of luxurious lifestyles becomes incidental to survival, revenge and redemption.</Para><Para>Consider a scene from ''Mrs.'' that might as well have been directed by Jean-Marc Vallée. Two mothers confront John D. Curtis and engage him in combat, eventually wresting from his wife an overdue debt. One takes off with her compensation (from an assignation-turned-assault during her ''Belle du Jour'' days), and as she strides away with her children, crisp hundred-dollar bills sail out of her pockets.</Para><Para>The remaining parents regard one another in stunned silence. Do they chase the money? Of course! Even masters of the capitalist universe and their flawless wives are soon scampering after the floating bills, stooping to the sidewalk, ''one with a stomp of the foot, the other on his knees, shooting out a hand.'' It's the children who look on, aghast.</Para><Para>The boldest thing about ''Mrs.'' -- as with ''Big Little Lies'' -- is that it focuses on the depths of women's experiences as wives and mothers. Their clashes with one another are entertaining, sure, but they're a diversion from the more important conflict with their husbands and with male power. ''Mrs.'' could easily have been a glossy, rushed novel about bitchy, bored housewives nursing social resentment. Plenty of those have been published, passing from memory as quickly as the pages fly under your fingers. But Macy hasn't written that kind of book. Although Philippa, Minnie and Gwen aren't smash-the-patriarchy crusaders for social justice, they recognize the violent, self-flattering, corrupt man in their midst and they deliver him, finally, to justice -- even if it comes at the expense of other lives.</Para><Para>Follow New York Times Books on Facebook and Twitter (@nytimesbooks), sign up for our newsletter or our literary calendar. And listen to us on the Book Review podcast.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By ALEX KUCZYNSKI </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field">Alex Kuczynski is the author of ''Beauty Junkies.'' </Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">DRAWING (DRAWING BY PING ZHU) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

