<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180322ee3m0006i" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180322111996</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180322ee3m0006i" fid="an"/><Num value="1020" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="29"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Foreign Desk; SECTA</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Aide to Pope Steps Down After Letter Is Doctored</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>ROME -- Even by the Vatican's minimal standards of transparency, doctoring the letter of a retired pope to make him seem more supportive of his successor turns out to be a bit much.</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By JASON HOROWITZ; Gaia Pianigiani contributed reporting. </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="vcan"/><Code value="eurz"/><Code value="weurz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="grel"/><Code value="gfake"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="gcom"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180322111996</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180322ee3m0006i" fid="an"/><Num value="1020" fid="wc"/><Num value="4980" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="md"/><Time value="070201" fid="upt"/><Time value="070201" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">9</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId275416061"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashFB265438B09CB13B"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATNS"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSPRBC814798"/><Code value="FSPRBC871293"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="vcan"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Vatican City</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180315142020"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="220"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="eurz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Europe</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:vcan"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="weurz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Western Europe</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:vcan"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="grel"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Religion</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishNS_en_20180316142643"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="186"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="814798"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gfake"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Fake News Phenomenon</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="871293"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:grel"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gfake"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcom"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Society/Community</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:grel"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Foreign Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Foreign Desk; SECTA</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Aide to Pope Steps Down After Letter Is Doctored</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>ROME -- Even by the Vatican's minimal standards of transparency, doctoring the letter of a retired pope to make him seem more supportive of his successor turns out to be a bit much.</Para><Para>Pope Francis on Wednesday accepted the resignation of Msgr. Dario Vigano, the head of the Vatican's communications department, after an episode of airbrushing and selective editing had prompted cries of ''Lettergate'' and accusations that the Vatican had spread the type of fake news the pope had recently denounced.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>The resignation of Monsignor Vigano, a close aide to the pope, marked another setback in what has been a difficult stretch for the 81-year-old pontiff, who just completed his fifth year in office.</Para><Para>Remarks Francis made in Chile that were offensive to victims of sexual abuse focused attention on an explosive issue that has threatened to derail his papacy. The success of anti-immigrant forces in Italian elections in March seemed a sharp rebuke in Francis's own backyard to his message of tolerance for migrants. His financial reforms have stalled, and conservatives appalled by what they consider his break with church doctrine and orthodoxy have ramped up their critiques.</Para><Para>''It is a rather critical moment of Francis's papacy,'' said Sandro Magister, a Vatican expert at the Italian weekly L'Espresso. He said that based on the changes made by Francis ''it's hard to call him a reformist now'' and that his greatest achievement had been ''in terms of church image.''</Para><Para>But it was Monsignor Vigano, who as communications director was the keeper of the pope's image, who created the headache this time.</Para><Para>In an apparent effort to buttress Francis against criticism from conservatives for breaking with his predecessor's doctrinal orthodoxy, Monsignor Vigano held a news conference last week to publicize a new series of books about the pope's theology. At the news conference, Monsignor Vigano said he had asked Francis's predecessor, Benedict, to ''write a page or a page and a half of dense theology in his clear and punctual style'' and that the 90-year-old retired pope responded instead with a ''beautiful, personal letter.''</Para><Para>In the letter, Benedict condemned the ''foolish prejudice'' of critics who depicted Francis as a pragmatic pastor without theology and Benedict as an academic with his head in the clouds. Benedict added that the books helped clarify ''the interior continuity between the two pontificates, with all the differences in style and temperament.''</Para><Para>Monsignor Vigano and the Vatican disseminated a photo of the letter and spun it as Benedict's seal of good papal housekeeping for Francis. The suggestion was that Benedict had read and approved of the books. But there were some key omissions.</Para><Para>It turned out that the Vatican had purposefully blurred the final two lines on the letter's first page in which Benedict acknowledged that he had not actually read the books and that he was physically unable and too busy to contribute his own theological assessment of Pope Francis. Distorted though it was, at least the first page saw the light of day. In the photo, the letter's second page sits buried under the books about Francis. Only Benedict's signature was visible.</Para><Para>Monsignor Vigano, in a sort of Keystone Clergy moment, himself drew attention to the omissions in the photo when he read the missing text at Monday's news conference. Mr. Magister, who was at the news conference, transcribed and published the remarks.</Para><Para>The Associated Press first drew attention to what appeared to be blurred lines in the photo of the letter. Its discovery prompted an outcry, especially among Catholic conservatives who complained that their hero, Pope Benedict, was being exploited to paper over Francis' doctrinal deficiencies. The Twitter hashtag #releasetheletter went viral. The Catholic Herald, a Catholic publication, ran the headline ''Blurred Lines: Vatican Manipulation of Photo Becomes the Story.''</Para><Para>Under pressure to address what it called ''presumed manipulation,'' the Vatican on Saturday released Benedict's full letter, of which almost the entire second page consisted of Benedict expressing his ''surprise'' that the 11-volume ''Theology of Pope Francis'' included a German author who, Benedict said, had targeted his teachings with ''virulent'' and ''anti-papist'' attacks. He said he was too busy to read the books and offer his assessment.</Para><Para>''I'm certain you can understand why I'm declining,'' Benedict signed off.</Para><Para>The Vatican claimed it originally released only the portion of the letter it considered ''opportune and relevant.''</Para><Para>But it did not look good. Especially because Pope Francis, who frequently laments journalists who fail to report the full story, released a major document in January condemning ''fake news.'' In the document, he said deception in the media went back to the snake in the Garden of Eden.</Para><Para>That was not a good ancestry for the Vatican's communications director.</Para><Para>''In recent days many controversies have arisen regarding my work, which beyond my intentions, has destabilized the complex and great work of reform that you entrusted to me,'' Monsignor Vigano, 55, wrote in his resignation letter.</Para><Para>Perhaps in an effort to compensate for the previous redaction, the Vatican on Wednesday released what appeared to be the full text of the letters between Mr. Vigano and the pope, who had hired him as communications director in 2015.</Para><Para>On Wednesday, Francis wrote back to Monsignor Vigano and said, ''I respect your decision and I welcome, not without some struggle, your resignation.''</Para><Para>The Vatican press office added that until Francis names a replacement, the communications office will be run by its second-in-command, Msgr. Lucio Ruiz. The pope asked Monsignor Vigano to stay on to advise the future director, it said.</Para><Para>A scandal in a communications department that had been a source of the pope's strength, Mr. Magister said, was not a good sign for Francis's reform agenda. ''This is only the umpteenth proof of the failure,'' he said.</Para><Para>This is a more complete version of the story than the one that appeared in print.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By JASON HOROWITZ; Gaia Pianigiani contributed reporting. </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

