<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180324ee3o0002t" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180324939471</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180324ee3o0002t" fid="an"/><Num value="1251" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180324" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="28"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Metropolitan Desk; SECTA</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">To Be Counted in Death as in Life</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>The first woman whose death was recorded in The New York Times was Abigail Lounsbury.</Para><Para>It was Oct. 2, 1851, two weeks after the first edition of the newspaper then called The New-York Daily Times, and the notice was fewer than 50 words. It ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By ALBERT SUN; Chris Stanford contributed reporting. </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usny"/><Code value="namz"/><Code value="usa"/><Code value="use"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180324939471</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180324ee3o0002t" fid="an"/><Num value="1251" fid="wc"/><Num value="5696" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180324" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="md"/><Time value="070043" fid="upt"/><Time value="070043" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">2</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId276309683"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashA32294666C8106FB"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC213858"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usny"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">New York State</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="213858"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018577-20180323-194546"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="3"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="use"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Northeast U.S.</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="213858"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018577-20180323-194546"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001000-20180323-161933"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Metropolitan Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Metropolitan Desk; SECTA</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">To Be Counted in Death as in Life</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>The first woman whose death was recorded in The New York Times was Abigail Lounsbury.</Para><Para>It was Oct. 2, 1851, two weeks after the first edition of the newspaper then called The New-York Daily Times, and the notice was fewer than 50 words. It referred to Abigail as the ''wife of Amos L. Lounsbury'' and said she was 63. It invited family and friends to the funeral, which was to depart from her ''late residence, Manhattanville'' Thursday at 2 p.m. It did not list the cause of death.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>The Times has published many thousands of obituaries and death notices since, but not so many about women. In each of the last two years, only about a fifth of the subjects of obituaries have been women, including Jean Sammet, a designer of the COBOL programming language; Mathilde Krim, a scientist who was a leader in the fight against AIDS; and Ursula K. Le Guin, a visionary science-fiction author.</Para><Para>Over the entire 167-year history of The New York Times, between 15 and 20 percent of our obituary subjects have been women -- a frustratingly imprecise number that also fails to fully reflect huge changes over the decades in the obituary form itself.</Para><Para>Last week, The Times introduced a new feature called Overlooked, providing obituaries of sorts for people from underrepresented communities who never received them. We started with 15 women, because it is Women's History Month and because the overwhelming maleness of our obit subjects is the most apparent imbalance. We are expanding to men of color as Overlooked becomes a weekly series.</Para><Para>As we embarked on this project, we wanted to be able to provide, for context, a sense of how the gender breakdown had changed over time. That turned out to be a project unto itself.</Para><Para>The first challenge was that The Times's digital full-text repository only reliably records articles back to 1960. We started there, and even that wasn't simple: We selected every piece labeled Obituary or in the Obituaries section, and then had to exclude paid death notices, duplicate articles, remembrances, briefs and other things that look like obits but really are not.</Para><Para>Jeff Roth and David Dunlap, colleagues who have long served as the newsroom's unofficial historians, shared a hardcover book, The New York Times Obituaries Index 1858-1968, that had 1,136 pages of small text: one name and publication date per line. But there was no digital version available.</Para><Para>So we turned to the New York Genealogical and Biographical Society, which graciously scanned the pages and converted them to machine-readable text for free in exchange for being allowed to make them available on its website. That felt like a win-win, since now the public has access to the index, too.</Para><Para>But we still had to write a computer program to classify each article or line of the index as referring to either a man or a woman.</Para><Para>For the articles from 1960 onward it was easier, since most obituaries going back decades are written in a signature style that contains a line about the age their subjects were when they died, beginning ''He was'' or ''She was.'' That made the computer-program task easier. (The Times has not yet published an obituary of someone who identifies as non-binary.)</Para><Para>For the lines of the index and for articles without that signature line, we had to guess based on the person's name. Here honorifics and titles helped: Mrs., for married women, and ''Lady,'' ''Princess,'' ''Countess,'' ''Queen'' -- luckily, many obit subjects are prominent people.</Para><Para>If there was no distinctive title, the program guessed based on the first name: John was almost certainly a man and Jessica almost certainly a woman. For those still unidentifiable, we were left to estimate the male-female ratio after rereading many of the obituaries one by one, though we still have not done so for every year's obituaries.</Para><Para>The first year of our indexing, 1858, three of the 24 obituaries were of women. The first of these was for Ida Pfeiffer (Nov. 16, 1858, Page 4, Column 5), a Viennese woman famed for her globe-trotting adventures. Her journeys took her all around the world until she contracted a mysterious illness in Madagascar to which she succumbed, despite the best efforts of her doctors back in Vienna.</Para><Para>In a letter to a friend quoted in the Times obituary, Ms. Pfeiffer wrote that people who knew her only through her travels ''fancy that my character, manners, even my figure and movements, are more like those of a man than a woman.''</Para><Para>''But you, who know me, know that those who expect to find me six feet high, with a bold, imposing gait, and a dagger and pistol in my belt, discover in me the very reverse,'' she continued, ''and that in every-day life I am plainer, quieter, and more reserved than thousands of my own sex who have never left the seclusion of their native villages.''</Para><Para>In those early decades, coverage of death was so different than in our modern history that it is tough to quantify the gender breakdown or compare it to today's. The Times has long carried both obituaries, which are news stories based on a subject's importance or interest to readers, and death notices, which are paid advertisements available to anyone who can pay the fare, now starting at about $250 for the shortest ones of 20 words or so.</Para><Para>Obituaries varied widely in length and selection criteria over the course of different eras.</Para><Para>From 1926 through 1936, only longer-form obituaries were included in the index; about 10 percent of the 400 to 500 indexed each year were for women.</Para><Para>In the two decades after 1936, many more obituaries appeared in the index, about 10,000 each year. (The peak year was 1949, with almost 13,000 obits, after which the numbers tapered off and slowly declined.) The percentage of women ranged mainly between 15 and 20 percent, dipping and rising without a clear pattern. But in that era there were many single-paragraph obituaries for prominent society figures -- and perhaps, on occasion, the wife of a prominent advertiser.</Para><Para>Through the 1970s, married women's obituaries were headlined using the honorific ''Mrs.'' and their husband's name, as with Frances Stunkard, a New York University librarian whose obituary ran under the headline ''Mrs. H. W. Stunkard,'' for her husband, Horace.</Para><Para>Even Frida Kahlo was identified in the headline of her 1953 obit as ''Diego Rivera's wife.'' While both Ms. Kahlo and Mr. Rivera, the Mexican muralist, were famous at the time, he was more so. The six-paragraph piece led the description of Ms. Kahlo's work with ''She also was a painter.'' Her renown has since grown to surpass Mr. Rivera's.</Para><Para>Then there is Charlotte Brontë, the author of ''Jane Eyre,'' whose 1855 death did not receive a mention in our pages.</Para><Para>The Times did cover the death, a half-century later, of the Rev. Arthur Bell Nichols. The headline: ''Charlotte Bronte's Husband Dead.''</Para><Para>Keep up with Times Insider stories on Twitter, via the Reader Center: @ReaderCenter.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By ALBERT SUN; Chris Stanford contributed reporting. </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field">Albert Sun is an assistant editor on the news platforms team. </Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">The headline on Frida Kahlo's 1953 Times obituary identified the artist as ''Diego Rivera's wife.'' (PHOTOGRAPH BY VICENTE WOLF PHOTOGRAPHY COLLECTION) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

