<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180321ee3l0003r" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180321068586</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180321ee3l0003r" fid="an"/><Num value="870" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180321" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="26"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Foreign Desk; SECT</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">A Town Quebec Would Rather Forget: The Canada Letter</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Hi! This is Dan Bilefsky, writing to you from the passenger seat of a tan Volvo as I travel from Quebec City to Saguenay, an industrial center in the province, on the last leg of my road trip across Quebec.</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By DAN BILEFSKY </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="cana"/><Code value="caqc"/><Code value="namz"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180321068586</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180321ee3l0003r" fid="an"/><Num value="870" fid="wc"/><Num value="4018" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180321" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180321" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180321" fid="md"/><Time value="070021" fid="upt"/><Time value="070021" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">The New York Times on the Web</PubEdition><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId274903211"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="tnomci"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashEC225F99EBE70F38"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NONS"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC633189"/><Code value="FSPRBC853115"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="cana"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Canada</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180309132020"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="154"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:caqc"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="caqc"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Quebec</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="853115"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018566-20180320-194945"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:cana"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:caqc"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Foreign Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Foreign Desk; SECT</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">A Town Quebec Would Rather Forget: The Canada Letter</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Hi! This is Dan Bilefsky, writing to you from the passenger seat of a tan Volvo as I travel from Quebec City to Saguenay, an industrial center in the province, on the last leg of my road trip across Quebec.</Para><Para>My head is spinning from the last few days in Quebec City, the stunning European-tinged capital of this province, where, among other things, I met with high school students and interviewed survivors of last year's attack on a Quebec mosque.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>I also had a wine-fueled meal at L'Affaire est Ketchup, where young chefs conjure up exquisitely wrought dishes of octopus and rack of lamb on an old-style electric stove as diners gyrate to loud French pop music in between shots of Vermouth.</Para><Para>On my quest to understand Québécois identity, I also traveled to the sleepy farming town of Hérouxville, in the Mauricie region,, population 1,300. It was among my most memorable experiences so far for what it showed me about today's Quebec.</Para><Para>The nondescript town, which seems frozen in a 1950s time warp and has one set of traffic lights, a post office, a church and a dépanneur, or convenience store, ignited a provincewide culture war about a decade ago when a city counselor, André Drouin, introduced a code of conduct warning immigrants not to stone women or light them on fire. It also explained the importance of Christmas trees.</Para><Para>The only thing was: The town didn't have any immigrants.</Para><Para>The code of conduct spurred a backlash with liberals ridiculing the town as racist, closed-minded or worse. But the town's many defenders, including social conservatives, said it was merely trying to protect Quebec's way of life.</Para><Para>The debate was so loud that the province convened a commission on the extent to which Quebec should accommodate minorities. And so it was that I found myself shivering and walking down Hérouxville's Main Street this week in the frigid March cold, curious to see whether attitudes had shifted.</Para><Para>At first, the reception was equally frosty as local residents glared at me suspiciously. People who eventually talked to me did not want to give their full names.</Para><Para>The message, though, was clear: Even after 10 years, the town was still reeling. One man said the code was the first subject strangers brought up when he said he was from Hérouxville. A woman said the town was tired of the attention.</Para><Para>But another woman defended the code, saying immigrants to Quebec had to conform to local custom.</Para><Para>Across Quebec, on radio shows and on social media, commentators tut-tutted me for going to Hérouxville, suggesting that there were more interesting places. Others accused me of being out of touch with Quebec.</Para><Para>But my road trip suggests otherwise.</Para><Para>More than a decade later, Quebec seems consumed by some of the same questions about identity.</Para><Para>Late last year Quebec introduced Bill 62, a law requiring people to show their faces in order to get public services. The law has upset some Muslims, including women who wear face-covering veils known as niqabs, and say that it stigmatizes them.</Para><Para>This week I also met with members of the Quebec City mosque where six people were killed by a Québécois gunman more than a year ago, leading to soul-searching about the state of Islamophobia in the province. During a chat at the mosque, which is still pocked with bullet holes, its director, Mohamed Labidi, told me that he feared that the far right combined with right-wing radio was fomenting hatred against Muslims and fear of the other.</Para><Para>''The situation for us has gotten worse over the past decade,'' he said. ''It has taken blood to flow for us to build bridges again.''</Para><Para>As I travel across Quebec, I am constantly reminded how a province with a French-speaking population surrounded by an Anglophone majority in the rest of the country is understandably sensitive when it comes to preserving Quebec's culture.</Para><Para>Moreover, because Québécois revolted against the strictures of the Roman Catholic Church in the 1960s, secularism is deeply ingrained and outward signs of religion can cause discomfort.</Para><Para>The Volvo is passing snow-covered mountains as we head to Saguenay, a center for the forestry and aluminum industries. There, I want to explore how globalization and factory closings have affected a region that is among the most separatist in the province.</Para><Para>On a different note, I also want to sample the region's vaunted meat pies, known as tourtières!</Para><Para>Please follow me on my journey on Facebook, Instagram and Twitter, as well as on The Times's Reader Center. I will return with the regular Canada Letter this weekend to let you know how the rest of the trip went.</Para><Para>We'd love your feedback on this newsletter. Please email your thoughts and suggestions to nytcanada@nytimes.com. And if you haven't done so, please subscribe to the email newsletter version.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By DAN BILEFSKY </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field">A native of Montreal, Dan Bilefsky recently returned there after 28 years to report about Canada for The New York Times. Follow him on Twitter: @DanBilefsky. </Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

