<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180322ee3m0003v" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180322736643</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180322ee3m0003v" fid="an"/><Num value="1533" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="30"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">The Arts/Cultural Desk; SECTC</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Columbia's Uprising: A 50-Year-Old Legacy</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>The campus of Columbia University is dotted with monuments to illustrious alumni and high-minded ideals. But on a sunny afternoon earlier this week, about two dozen people gathered around the sundial in its central plaza to pay tribute to a...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By JENNIFER SCHUESSLER </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="co"><Code value="colunv"/></CSet><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"/><Code value="namz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="guni"/><Code value="gent"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="gedu"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180322736643</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180322ee3m0003v" fid="an"/><Num value="1533" fid="wc"/><Num value="7458" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="md"/><Time value="070125" fid="upt"/><Time value="070125" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">1</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId275416061"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashFAF2200B473143E1"/><Code value="FSPTHINGFINDER"/><Code value="FSP2YESCO"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORG"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORGOC"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSPRBC213845"/><Code value="FSPRBC213868"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="co"><Code value="colunv"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Columbia University</CodeD><CodeI org="thingfinder" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="ptf--aboutCo-00004106-20180321-231407.dictionary"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180315142020"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="84"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="guni"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">University/College</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishNS_en_20180316142643"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="180"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gent"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Arts/Entertainment</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="213845"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/><CodeA name="rule" value="213868"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:guni"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gent"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gedu"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Education</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:guni"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">The Arts/Cultural Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">The Arts/Cultural Desk; SECTC</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Columbia's Uprising: A 50-Year-Old Legacy</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>The campus of Columbia University is dotted with monuments to illustrious alumni and high-minded ideals. But on a sunny afternoon earlier this week, about two dozen people gathered around the sundial in its central plaza to pay tribute to a momentous event that has gone uncommemorated in stone.</Para><Para>''Horam expecta veniet -- await the hour, it shall come,'' Frank Guridy, an associate professor of history at the university, proclaimed, reading a Latin inscription on the sundial. ''I think it's sort of poetic that things began here.''</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>''Things'' is an understatement for what began at Columbia around noon on April 23, 1968, when students, united by opposition to plans to build a university gym in a nearby public park and by Columbia's involvement in weapons research, converged on that spot. A week later, nearly a thousand activists had occupied five buildings (including the president's office), taken the dean hostage and shut down the campus, before being removed by the police in a violent melee that ended with one of the largest mass arrests in New York City history.</Para><Para>Anniversaries of Columbia 1968 tend to arrive like a classic rock hit, replayed nostalgically by those who were there. But it's a story, Professor Guridy told the group of current students and former strikers who had gathered for a walking tour of sites relating to the protests, that is only now, as the 50th anniversary approaches, being fully understood.</Para><Para>The tour, organized by Professor Guridy and Thai Jones, a curator at the university's special collections library, is part of a semester-long exploration of the legacy of the protests, which also includes a Twitter feed that will replay events in real time, an exhibition dedicated to the global dimensions of 1968 and a three-day conference.</Para><Para>About a half-dozen former protesters were joined by students who have been researching the history of 1968 in Columbia's archives, as part of two classes modeled on an earlier one dedicated to exploring the university's connections with slavery.</Para><Para>The slavery research was spearheaded by the university's president, Lee Bollinger. But the 1968 commemoration is taking on a history that is more recent and perhaps more fraught, even at a school where a tradition of student protest is touted as part of the brand.</Para><Para>Mr. Bollinger, in a telephone interview, said that ''part of the identity of Columbia is reinforced by what happened here in 1968.'' But asked if he saw the legacy of the protests themselves as positive, Mr. Bollinger -- whose own office was briefly occupied in 2016 by students demanding fossil fuel divestment -- walked a careful line.</Para><Para>The administration's decision to call in the police in 1968 was ''a serious breach of the ethos of the university.'' However much he agreed broadly with the protesters' opposition to the Vietnam War and support for civil rights, he said, the occupation of buildings ''was not necessarily the right way to manifest those viewpoints.''</Para><Para>Anniversaries of the strike have tended to reflect the campus politics of the moment. At the 10th anniversary, in 1978, the dominant issue was calls for South Africa divestment, and things turned nearly riotous, as people left a panel discussion and tried to occupy Low Library.</Para><Para>In 2008, during the 40th anniversary, the campus was in the midst of intense debate over a planned $7 billion expansion (now partly open), which some saw as a rerun of the plan for the gym in nearby Morningside Park that sparked the 1968 strike.</Para><Para>That anniversary also drew out tensions among the '68ers themselves. African-American veterans of the protests, some of whom had been members of the Student Afro-American Society, spoke about the racism they experienced at Columbia, and the way their role had been pushed to the margins in accounts of the strike emphasizing the mostly white Students for a Democratic Society.</Para><Para>Some white former strikers expressed complicated feelings about having been asked to leave Hamilton Hall, the first building that was seized in 1968, so that the black students could maintain a separate protest.</Para><Para>''It was cathartic,'' Raymond M. Brown, a leader of the Hamilton occupation who is now a prominent lawyer, said of that conversation. ''I was really surprised at how hurt some people had been by what was a strategic decision.''</Para><Para>Today, the dominant image of Columbia 1968 may still be of mostly white radicals hanging out the windows of the occupied buildings. But historical scholarship has swung toward recognizing the Hamilton occupation as ''the pivotal act'' of the protest, as Mr. Brown puts it in ''A Time to Stir: Columbia '68,'' a collection of essays edited by Paul Cronin and recently published by Columbia University Press.</Para><Para>That refocusing of the story was also echoed by the cast of former strikers on hand for the tour. Mark Rudd, the S.D.S. leader who was propelled to celebrity by the takeover (and later led one faction into violent militance), had been scheduled to appear at the tour's original date two weeks earlier, which had been canceled because of a snowstorm. (Cue the weatherman jokes.)</Para><Para>But those on hand included Carolyn Eisenberg, the only woman originally on the strike's central steering committee; and Karla Spurlock-Evans, a former Hamilton occupier who said she had gone to the building initially not to protest, but to hear the Soul Syndicate, a campus band known for Smokey Robinson covers.</Para><Para>''I'm not going to lie, I came over to hear brothers with bass guitars singing 'Ooo Baby Baby,''' Ms. Spurlock-Evans, who is now senior diversity officer at Trinity College, said. ''But I decided to stay, and over that week grew to feel deeply connected to the struggle we had engaged in.''</Para><Para>At every stop, the '68ers filled in Professor Guridy's narrative with anecdotes, commentaries and corrections, many of which complicated the stereotypical narrative of the strike as a generational rebellion playing out between students and the administration.</Para><Para>Recent scholarship has emphasized the close connections between student activists and tenants-rights and other community groups in Harlem, which (then as now, Professor Guridy noted) were often in conflict with Columbia.</Para><Para>The mood during the walk was warm and comradely. But participants kept returning to the African-American students' decision to maintain a distinct protest.</Para><Para>In the lobby of Hamilton, both Mr. Brown and Ms. Spurlock-Evans emphasized that it was a strategic decision. The black students, they said, had stronger ties to the surrounding Harlem community, a deeper history of organizing, greater discipline and less tolerance for the revolutionary rhetoric adopted by the most radical whites.</Para><Para>Professor Eisenberg, now a historian and a peace activist, was among the white students asked to leave Hamilton (and who then helped occupy Fayerweather Hall). She wondered if the request had helped push the mostly male leaders of S.D.S. to what she called ''extreme macho posturing.''</Para><Para>''It created psychological need to reaffirm that they were brave, strong and revolutionary,'' she said.</Para><Para>As with the strike itself, ''the bust,'' as the police raid is called, unfolded differently at Hamilton. The students, who had indicated they would not resist arrest, were taken away by a black-led police unit without the violence at other buildings.</Para><Para>And while other buildings were vandalized (one occupier in Low Library was famously photographed with his feet on the desk of Columbia's president, Grayson Kirk, smoking his cigars), Ms. Spurlock-Evans noted that the Hamilton occupiers took care to leave the building as clean as they found it.</Para><Para>As the tour concluded, Professor Guridy noted that the protests's two main demands -- canceling the gym and severing ties with a weapons-research institute affiliated with the Defense Department -- were ultimately met. Within a year, Mr. Kirk had resigned, a university senate was created and the process of adding courses in African-American history began.</Para><Para>Many at the time, and since, have argued that the strike profoundly damaged Columbia by violating its status as a neutral, if imperfect, bastion of ''free argument and inquiry,'' as the historian Richard Hofstadter said shortly after the protests in a commencement address, delivered in place of Mr. Kirk.</Para><Para>But Professor Guridy said he hoped the strike would still leave one more mark.</Para><Para>''They should put a plaque on the sundial,'' he said. ''It should say, 'This event happened. It was difficult and violent. But it made our community a better place.'''</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By JENNIFER SCHUESSLER </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Top, students in Hamilton Hall, seized on April 23, 1968. That night, African-American students asked white students to leave and seize other buildings so they could maintain a separate protest. Above, Karla Spurlock-Evans and Raymond Brown on a recent walking tour. (PHOTOGRAPHS BY DON HOGAN CHARLES/THE NEW YORK TIMES; COLE WILSON FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES) (C1); Clockwise from top: a damaged classroom at Hamilton Hall at Columbia in May 1968 during a monthlong occupation; police officers forcing students out of Hamilton; and Raymond Brown of the Student Afro-American Society. (PHOTOGRAPHS BY NEAL BOENZI/THE NEW YORK TIMES; LARRY C. MORRIS/THE NEW YORK TIMES; RICHARD HOWARD) (C6) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

