<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180325ee3p00081" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325012050</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p00081" fid="an"/><Num value="1016" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Magazine Desk; SECTMM</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm">LETTER OF RECOMMENDATION</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Schleich Figurines</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Each day, against the blank expanse of Arabian desert just outside my office window, a procession of wild animals continues its relentlessly static march to nowhere. The heart of it comprises a sprawling array of apes -- four chimps, a band...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By CHARLES SIEBERT </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"/><Code value="namz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="ncolu"/><Code value="ncat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325012050</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p00081" fid="an"/><Num value="1016" fid="wc"/><Num value="4597" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="070358" fid="upt"/><Time value="070358" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">26</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId276566134"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashEC2CA64C7AA30BDB"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC213856"/><Code value="FSPRBC234480"/><Code value="FSPRBC852186"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="234480"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="213856"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncolu"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Columns</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="852186"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Content Types</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:ncolu"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Magazine Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Magazine Desk; SECTMM</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field">LETTER OF RECOMMENDATION</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Schleich Figurines</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Each day, against the blank expanse of Arabian desert just outside my office window, a procession of wild animals continues its relentlessly static march to nowhere. The heart of it comprises a sprawling array of apes -- four chimps, a band of mountain gorillas, one orangutan -- each of them caught midstride, -strike or -thought. Nearby, a herd of elephants treads noiselessly, trunks and ears flailing, like a pod of land-whales adrift above a dry, ancient seabed. Following behind, a pride of jungle cats -- tigers, lions, a cheetah cub, a jaguar, an ocelot -- pads about the slow, mine-sweeping snouts of a passing crash of rhinos. Far up ahead, a hyacinth macaw takes flight above two meerkats, standing their endless vigil.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>It was nearly 20 years ago now that I brought home a lone chimpanzee figurine and placed it at the base of a plant on my Brooklyn windowsill. I was spending a good bit of time back then visiting with, and writing about, our nearest evolutionary relatives. The majority were what you might call civilization's castoffs: surplus research-lab subjects; abandoned pets; washed-up actors and circus performers. For a time, I took up residence in a Florida retirement home for chimp entertainers, doing research for a book about a longtime cellist in an all-chimp orchestra at Ringling Brothers. His name was Roger, and he died a year after I last saw him, of a sudden heart attack at age 32. He'd been in one cage or another his entire life, and yet he still preferred humans to other chimps. I bought that first figurine, I think now, as a totem of what individuals like Roger are never allowed to be: nameless and unblemished by captivity.</Para><Para>It may have been the rain-forest-like play of sunlight and shadow around him. Or his slightly skyward, spindrift gaze. But at not even an inch in height, everything about that intricately tooled bit of plastic, from the ruffled whorls of his fur to the chestnut gleam of his eyes to the eerily animate, asking gesture of his upraised right hand, commanded my attention and began to compel his own company. Over my many years of lighting out to encounter and write about nonhuman intelligences, I began, almost subconsciously, to gradually populate the miniwilderness that my lone chimp betokened. Whenever I was in a museum or zoo gift shop, or passing a toy-store window, I'd find myself drawn to the animal figurines, always seeking out the naturalism of that first Roger effigy.</Para><Para>It wasn't until my collection began to spill over onto the sill below that it occurred to me to turn over the beasts one day for closer inspection. On the underbelly of each I found the same name -- ''Schleich'' -- in minuscule lettering. Just below were the words ''Schwäbisch Gmünd,'' a little town in southern Germany, I soon learned, where the 83-year-old company makes many of these beguilingly lifelike beings: wild creatures from around the world, all rendered with such precision that you can see and feel a sea otter's wet and rippling fur, or the weathered cracks and crevasses of an elephant's skin, or the scalloped feathers of a macaw's upraised underwings. Invariably, they have eyes so glimmeringly alive that they rival those of the finest taxidermy in natural-history museum dioramas, without having to slay any of the actual beings for the effect. In fact, you need never have ventured outside the boundaries of civilization to be instantly transported and held spellbound there by these carefully rendered creatures. Each day in my office, a mere glance at the windowsill becomes a way of traveling in place.</Para><Para>Of course, if verisimilitude were my lone collecting criterion, I knew my Brooklyn apartment would soon be riddled with Schleichs. To keep my menagerie from devolving into randomness and kitsch, I decided I could only take in those animals I had encountered and written about. In this way, I knew they'd be bound to one another -- and the lot of them together to me -- by story: the chimps standing in not just for the retired captives but also for the family I saw retiring in the upper boughs of an East African rain forest; the jaguar for the one a field biologist and I tracked all morning through the jungles of Belize only to have him double back and track us, merely to get what was most likely his first look at human beings; the elephant for the matriarch who, with a fierce eye as white as her tusks, held me and my guide frozen on a remote road in Uganda so that her calf could knock freely about within the safe cribbing of her mother's legs; the beluga for the one captured by the United States Navy in the waters of Hudson Bay in order to train him to surveil the Arctic Sea, where newly designed Russian submarines were known to hide. They're all with me still.</Para><Para>When packing three years ago to take a post teaching creative writing here at N.Y.U. Abu Dhabi, the animals went immediately into my carry-on bag for fear not just of their being lost in transit, but also of my ever losing sight of how endangered their living counterparts truly are. Now colleagues and students alike regularly stop by my office and go wide-eyed with wonder at the sight of my windowsill's stark, sand-limned procession. It is, in the end, a bittersweet sort of awe they inspire: a diorama of days and of ways of being that we humans long ago left behind and are now in danger of forever losing.</Para><Para>Sign up for our newsletter to get the best of The New York Times Magazine delivered to your inbox every week.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By CHARLES SIEBERT </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field">Charles Siebert is a contributing writer for the magazine. </Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Wild creatures rendered with an eye for detail that results in museum-diorama quality, but without having to kill anything. (PHOTOGRAPH BY KATHERINE WOLKOFF) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

