<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180322ee3m00044" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180322996882</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180322ee3m00044" fid="an"/><Num value="1397" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="26"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Metropolitan Desk; SECTA</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">In Connecticut, Nomination Devolves Into Partisan Fight</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>HARTFORD -- Andrew J. McDonald had been overwhelmingly approved by lawmakers five years ago when he joined the Connecticut Supreme Court. Now he has returned to the State Legislature -- this time nominated to be chief justice with the ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By RICK ROJAS </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"/><Code value="usct"/><Code value="usny"/><Code value="namz"/><Code value="use"/><Code value="usnew"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gpol"/><Code value="gvsup"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="gcrim"/><Code value="gpir"/><Code value="gvbod"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180322996882</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180322ee3m00044" fid="an"/><Num value="1397" fid="wc"/><Num value="7007" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="md"/><Time value="070128" fid="upt"/><Time value="070128" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">20</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId275416061"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="djsipif"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash659A731C6933BAFB"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATNS"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSPRBC213858"/><Code value="FSPRBC610205"/><Code value="FSPRBC798110"/><Code value="FSPRBC799599"/><Code value="FSPRBC801071"/><Code value="FSPRBC817538"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180315142020"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="84"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usct"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="usct"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Connecticut</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="610205"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="3"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="4"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="usny"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">New York State</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="213858"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="3"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usct"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="use"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Northeast U.S.</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usct"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="usnew"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">New England</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usct"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="3"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gpol"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Domestic Politics</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishNS_en_20180316142643"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="280"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="799599"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gvsup"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gvsup"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Judicial Branch</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishNS_en_20180316142643"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="200"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="801071"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="4"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="213858"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gpol"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gvsup"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gcrim"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcrim"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Crime/Legal Action</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="798110"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gpir"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Politics/International Relations</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gpol"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gvsup"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gvbod"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Government Bodies</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gvsup"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="3"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Metropolitan Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Metropolitan Desk; SECTA</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">In Connecticut, Nomination Devolves Into Partisan Fight</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>HARTFORD -- Andrew J. McDonald had been overwhelmingly approved by lawmakers five years ago when he joined the Connecticut Supreme Court. Now he has returned to the State Legislature -- this time nominated to be chief justice with the backing of much of the state's legal establishment. He was put up for the job by a Democratic governor in a state where the party has dominated for years.</Para><Para>Still, his confirmation is anything but guaranteed and has devolved into a contentious partisan fight.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Justice McDonald is not the first Supreme Court nominee in Connecticut to face significant resistance in the State Legislature. But his nomination has become marked by an unusual level of acrimony. Stiff opposition from Republicans has imperiled his confirmation, while his supporters have mounted a robust effort that borrows from the tactics of political campaigns, even using robocalls and television advertisements to pressure lawmakers. (One commercial featured an image of President Trump and urged residents to call their legislator, saying, ''You can stop this smear campaign now.'')</Para><Para>The battle, which has drawn widespread attention to what can often be a rather subdued process, has been described by legal experts as further evidence of politics seeping into the selection of judges across the country. The situation also reflects a fractured political climate in Connecticut, as Republicans, and even some Democrats, have become emboldened in challenging an unpopular governor, Dannel P. Malloy, who is in his last year in office.</Para><Para>Justice McDonald's critics have sought to portray him as beholden to the governor and the Democratic Party, and they have argued that he has used the court to advance political interests. Much of the opposition has been driven by his role in a Supreme Court decision over the repeal of the death penalty. Among those who voted against his nomination were Representative William A. Petit Jr., whose wife and daughters were killed in a grisly 2007 home invasion. ''I do not believe he has the experience nor temperament to be the C.E.O. of the judicial branch,'' Dr. Petit, who was elected to the Legislature as a Republican in 2016, said on the House floor.</Para><Para>But his supporters have suggested that at least some of the opposition has been motivated by Justice McDonald's sexual orientation -- he would become the first openly gay chief justice in the country. They also contend that the intensity of the questioning he has faced and the rancor surrounding his confirmation suggests dubious motivations.</Para><Para>''The whole thing is just, I'll tell you, it's so out of character for this building,'' said Senator Beth Bye, a Democrat who supports Justice McDonald. ''That's why you have to say, what else could be up? It doesn't sit with past practice.''</Para><Para>The precarious state of his nomination became clear when he testified last month before the Legislature's Judiciary Committee, where, as a former state senator and chairman of the committee, he faced lawmakers who had once been colleagues. The proceedings stretched over more than 12 hours, with questions about his time on the Supreme Court as well as his experience in the Senate and his friendship with Mr. Malloy, who hired him as general counsel, appointed him to the Supreme Court and even officiated at his wedding.</Para><Para>Asked about judicial activism, Justice McDonald defined it as ''when a judge takes their personal opinion about what the outcome of a case should be and disregards the law in an effort to achieve that outcome.'' He added, ''I don't think that's a proper role for a judge.''</Para><Para>The committee was evenly divided in its vote, which meant that his nomination received an unfavorable recommendation. His nomination was then endorsed by a single vote in the House, where the Democrats have a nine-member majority. The Senate, where Democrats and Republicans have the same number of seats, is expected to vote before the end of the month; one Democrat has already indicated that she will abstain from voting.</Para><Para>''Justice McDonald is a consummate jurist who has earned the respect of legal professionals across the state for his exceptional ability to understand, analyze, research and evaluate legal issues,'' Mr. Malloy said in a statement, adding that he encouraged senators to vote ''based on a substantive and objective assessment of facts and not based upon a political calculation.''</Para><Para>Justice McDonald's nomination is the latest hiccup in Mr. Malloy's difficult relationship with lawmakers. Last year, as the state operated for months without a budget amid a financial crisis, Republicans recruited several Democrats in the House and Senate to pass a spending package of their own, which the governor vetoed. The budget that Mr. Malloy ultimately signed was negotiated without him.</Para><Para>Justice McDonald, 52, was nominated to the Supreme Court by Mr. Malloy in 2013, and enjoyed wide bipartisan support in the State Legislature, where he was approved 30-3 by the Senate and 125-20 by the House.</Para><Para>Since then, several high-profile cases have come before the court, including appeals brought by Michael C. Skakel, whose conviction for the 1975 murder of Martha Moxley was reinstated by the court, and family members of victims of the massacre at Sandy Hook Elementary School, who are arguing that the companies that manufactured and sold the military-style assault rifle used by the gunman bear responsibility for the 2012 attack.</Para><Para>But the case that has most incited his critics, including some Democrats, was the court's ruling in 2015 that the state's law abolishing capital punishment must be applied to inmates who had been sentenced before the law, passed in 2012, went into effect.</Para><Para>The decision spared 11 inmates from execution, including the convicted perpetrators of the home-invasion robbery in Cheshire that ended with the rape and strangulation of Jennifer Hawke-Petit and the killing of her daughters, Michaela, 11, and Hayley, 17. (Dr. Petit, the victims' husband and father, was bludgeoned, but escaped to a neighbor's house.)</Para><Para>Justice McDonald was part of the 4-to-3 majority. His critics believe that Justice McDonald should have recused himself from the case; they argued that he had a record of opposing the death penalty as a legislator and that he was the governor's general counsel involved in crafting the language of the bill, which maintained previous death sentences while repealing capital punishment going forward. (People close to the governor countered that Justice McDonald did not play a role in the legislation.)</Para><Para>Minutes before his Judiciary Committee hearing, a group of conservative lawmakers announced their opposition, finding him unqualified because of a lack of experience as a judge. (His critics have also challenged the argument that they opposed Justice McDonald because he was gay, an allegation that one House Republican, Rosa Rebimbas, dismissed as ''just ludicrous.'')</Para><Para>''I think there's certainly a concern that in his role as chief justice, there would be a politicization of the court,'' said Representative Vincent Candelora, a Republican. ''I think that many people believe the fact that we're seeing robocalls and TV ads pressuring lawmakers to support him supports that notion.''</Para><Para>Still, Justice McDonald's nomination has been backed by newspaper editorials across the state, as well as by law school deans, the state bar association and dozens of lawyers, including Democrats and Republicans, who wrote a letter of support. Some have vouched for his intellectual rigor and a sense of fairness he displayed as a jurist. Many also expressed fear of political incursion threatening the judiciary's independence.</Para><Para>In a letter to the Judiciary Committee, James D. Horwitz, president of the Connecticut Trial Lawyers Association, suggested a rubric for weighing court nominees: ''Does he demonstrate patience, calmness and attention? Does he demonstrate courtesy, civility, open-mindedness and compassion? Is he committed to professionalism and improving availability of justice to all? Is he skillful in the administration of justice?''</Para><Para>Mr. Horwitz continued, ''These are the standards by which Justice McDonald and, frankly, all judicial appointments should be measured.''</Para><Para>Follow Rick Rojas on Twitter @rar</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By RICK ROJAS </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Justice Andrew J. McDonald of the Connecticut Supreme Court testified at a hearing last month. (PHOTOGRAPH BY MICHAEL MCANDREWS/HARTFORD COURANT, VIA ASSOCIATED PRESS); Representative William A. Petit Jr. is among those who voted against the nomination. (PHOTOGRAPH BY JESSICA HILL FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

