<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180322ee3m0003d" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180322959308</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180322ee3m0003d" fid="an"/><Num value="1195" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="26"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Style Desk; SECTD</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm">THE SWEET SPOT</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">A Brother-in-Law Who's All Hands</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Dear Sugars,</Para><Para>My husband and I have been together for five years and married for nearly one. We're very happy. I also love his family. His parents and three siblings are kind and fun to be around. The problem is my creepy brother-in-law, who ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By CHERYL STRAYED and STEVE ALMOND </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"/><Code value="namz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"/><Code value="ncolu"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="ncat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180322959308</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180322ee3m0003d" fid="an"/><Num value="1195" fid="wc"/><Num value="5010" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="md"/><Time value="070118" fid="upt"/><Time value="070118" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">2</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId275416061"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashEDB3A338F0FE8840"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC234480"/><Code value="FSPRBC622900"/><Code value="FSPRBC808880"/><Code value="FSPRBC852186"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="234480"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Living/Lifestyle</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="622900"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncolu"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Columns</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="808880"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/><CodeA name="rule" value="852186"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:glife"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Content Types</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:ncolu"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Style Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Style Desk; SECTD</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field">THE SWEET SPOT</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">A Brother-in-Law Who's All Hands</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Dear Sugars,</Para><Para>My husband and I have been together for five years and married for nearly one. We're very happy. I also love his family. His parents and three siblings are kind and fun to be around. The problem is my creepy brother-in-law, who is married to my husband's sister.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>From the beginning, he took an uncomfortable interest in me. He looks me up and down, makes unnecessary comments about my body and clothing, touches me often and for inappropriate amounts of time, and goes out of his way to sit next to me at family gatherings. Each touch, look and comment can be explained away when taken individually, but together, they tell me he's a creep. In my gut, I know: It's not me, it's him. My obvious discomfort only seems to encourage him. I've been consistently rude, and when I must speak to him, I do so curtly. He hasn't retreated.</Para><Para>Recently, he put his hand on my hip/buttocks area. I pulled away and said sharply, ''Do not touch me there.'' Less than an hour later, he reached for my knee. Recently, one of my husband's friends told him how uncomfortable my brother-in-law had made his girlfriend at our wedding last year. My husband was upset and he told me he felt terrible that I'm regularly subjected to this behavior. While it was nice to have validation, I also wonder why my own story isn't enough for him to make it real. His family is unbelievably nonconfrontational. They avoid all topics for fear of offending someone. While my husband and I are not so nonconfrontational in our relationship, he clings to it hard within the context of his family, and he continues to have polite conversations with our brother-in-law. Why isn't he squashing this behavior? Why isn't he on my side?</Para><Para>Alone With a Creep</Para><Para>Cheryl Strayed: You need to tell your brother-in-law that he's no longer allowed to touch you, sit next to you or make comments about your appearance. You've already communicated this to him in ways that are both subtle and quietly direct. That hasn't worked. So now you need to be louder and more explicit. I suggest you tell him about your new rules of being in his presence before your next family gathering, either in person or via email. Very likely, he'll say that you're being silly, that his intentions are innocent, that when he makes comments that make you uncomfortable, he's only joking, but these explanations have no bearing on the matter. You're not having a discussion or negotiation with him. You're telling him how he is permitted to interact with you from now on by setting clear boundaries.</Para><Para>Steve Almond: I second Cheryl's wise counsel. I urge you to talk to your brother-in-law in person, if you can bear it. Not just because tone often gets muddied in emails, but because you need to gently but firmly confront this man with the fact that you no longer consent to his behaviors. I stress this because guys like your brother-in-law are adept at converting our natural tendency to avoid conflict into a license to bully. The fact that your brother-in-law seems encouraged by your ''obvious discomfort'' tells me that he knows you don't want his attention, that he's shamed by your rejection and he deals with this shame by resorting to sadism. Not only does your brother-in-law need to be put on notice, but your husband does, too. He needs to understand that his attempts to keep the peace are, in this case, enabling predatory behavior directed at his wife. You certainly don't need your husband to fight your battles for you, but he should, at the very least, serve as an ally. The fact that you feel ''Alone'' with this creep, even with your husband present, suggests the depth of his negligence. That is something else you need to confront.</Para><Para>CS: I understand why you feel betrayed by your husband, Alone. I suggest you set a boundary with him too: If he won't stop being complicit in your brother-in-law's behavior by acting as if it isn't happening, then you won't accompany him to family gatherings where your brother-in-law will be present. My hunch is it won't come to that, because his loyalty to you will ultimately trump his fear of conflict, but it appears that you're going to have to demand it. Openly addressing your brother-in-law's actions and your husband's passivity in the face of them are not easy things to do, but they must be done if you are to feel safe with your husband and his family. I like Steve's suggestion that you confront your brother-in-law in person, and I urge you to bring your husband along to that meeting. His presence will establish the fact that he is indeed your ally rather than your brother-in-law's enabler. And, perhaps more importantly, witnessing your courage in dealing with this issue might help him gain some as well. It will also put him on notice that you're no longer willing to choose his family's comfort over your own.</Para><Para>SA: Cheryl and I recognize that what we're asking you to do here is difficult. You're not calling out a stranger, but a relative. In the process, you're having to shatter a code of silence that governs this entire family. But you need to remind yourself that demanding common decency is not a radical act. You experience this man's behavior as predatory. You want it to stop. Period. This isn't rocket science, or a complicated legal case. It's not ''He said, she said.'' It's ''Leave me alone, creep.'' In calling out his creepdom, you're not just defending your own rights, but those of other women who might feel harassed by this guy. And you're sending a clear message to your husband and his family: that you don't want to spend time around people who are emotionally abusive to you, or those who defend them. If you find yourself struggling to muster the nerve, it might help to think about the young women in and around your husband's family. What you're modeling for them isn't just courage. It's self-respect.</Para><Para>The ''Dear Sugars'' podcast is an advice program hosted by Steve Almond and Cheryl Strayed. The audio contains more letters; submissions are welcome at dearsugars@nytimes.com. Click the play button above to listen. You can also find ''Dear Sugars'' on the Podcasts app (iPhone and iPad) and Radio Public (Android and tablet).</Para><Para>This is a more complete version of the story than the one that appeared in print.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By CHERYL STRAYED and STEVE ALMOND </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">DRAWING (DRAWING BY HEIDI YOUNGER) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

