<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180325ee3p0008j" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325115738</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p0008j" fid="an"/><Num value="1131" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Metropolitan Desk; SECTMB</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Reader Comments</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Step Right Up and Say What Happened</Para><Para>Readers responded to Andy Newman's article in Metropolitan last Sunday about the city office where people go to fight summonses for all kinds of infractions, from unshoveled sidewalks to underheated hot ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by"></Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usny"/><Code value="usa"/><Code value="nyc"/><Code value="namz"/><Code value="use"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325115738</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p0008j" fid="an"/><Num value="1131" fid="wc"/><Num value="5174" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="070409" fid="upt"/><Time value="070409" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">6</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId276566134"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash86D88A647476100D"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSPRBC213858"/><Code value="FSPRBC474774"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usny"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">New York State</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="132"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="213858"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:nyc"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="3"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="74"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:nyc"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nyc"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">New York City</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="474774"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="4"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:nyc"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="use"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Northeast U.S.</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:nyc"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="213858"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Metropolitan Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Metropolitan Desk; SECTMB</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Reader Comments</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Step Right Up and Say What Happened</Para><Para>Readers responded to Andy Newman's article in Metropolitan last Sunday about the city office where people go to fight summonses for all kinds of infractions, from unshoveled sidewalks to underheated hot dogs. Comments were edited for length and clarity.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>My experience is that millennials and younger are the first to violate the laws that allow us to live, work and socialize together in close proximity to each other.</Para><Para>Like those in the gym (which we all pay for) who are continually on their cellphones talking loudly so as to be heard above the din of treadmills and weight machines, despite clearly posted rules against cellphone use. Or walking down the street with their heads buried in their personal devices and who will walk right into you rather than look up. Or driving at breakneck speeds, weaving in and out of traffic and cutting you off, and who quickly give you the finger when you honk in protest. Self-serving, self-indulgent, and oblivious to the rights of those around them.</Para><Para>Paul, White Plains</Para><Para>My wife made an illegal left turn near Union Square, because the truck in front of her was blocking the sign. I was a passenger and came as a witness, who spoke to the judge separately, after my wife pleaded her side. I said she was trying to make a left turn (pointing to my right -- I have a problem with left-right) as the judge stopped me and asked me again to describe what had happened. Because he realized I was not able to be a good liar, the violation was dropped. Only time that a small ''disability'' helped us, otherwise it has been years of wrong turns, and stepped on toes at square dances, etc.! She still loves me.</Para><Para>SmartenUp, United States</Para><Para>For most people, these interactions are their principal dealings with the justice system. While they may seem trivial to most, they play a huge role in forming people's opinions about our government and our system of justice.</Para><Para>David, California</Para><Para>I had my own run-in with this portion of New York's legal system when I was in college. I was issued a summons for selling T-shirts that I had designed without a license on what turned out to be public property, not school property, where I had permission to sell them. The police officer who wrote the summons told me that there had been a complaint (they were politically themed T-shirts, and undoubtedly the politics rubbed someone the wrong way) and was obviously unhappy writing the summons (and confiscating my shirts). He urged me repeatedly to fight it -- so I did.</Para><Para>When I got to my administrative hearing, the officer was present. The judge began the process by reading the particulars of the case: ''Occurred at 10:15 a.m. at the intersection of Washington Square North and West Fourth Street.'' The officer said, ''Wait, where?'' The judge repeated what the summons said. ''Oh, that's wrong -- those streets are parallel!'' ''Case dismissed!'' I even got my T-shirts back.</Para><Para>Jay Gurewitsch,</Para><Para>Provincetown, Mass.</Para><Para>Is this method of policing really helping New York becomes a better place? It seems that's the people who are trying to make themselves something are being targeted, while the rich can seamlessly do whatever they want. I want empanadas from the lady selling them from her street cart. I wanna hear music in the subway.</Para><Para>Can we please let New Yorkers be New Yorkers? Please and thank you, N.Y.P.D.</Para><Para>Michael, Long Island</Para><Para>I was once called to court for a supposed parking infraction that the judge dismissed. While waiting, I got to hear a lot of excuses. A man of Chinese descent said he had been speeding because he was so excited to meet his sister at the airport, where she would be coming from China. The judge looked at his record and asked, ''These other tickets -- more sisters?'' A young man who had failed to respond to a series of summonses said, ''Judge, I know it's a bad habit, but I don't open my mail.''</Para><Para>GreaterMetropolitanArea</Para><Para>5 Reasons for Copter Ban</Para><Para>Readers also commented on Ginia Bellafante's Big City column on the tourist helicopters flights over New York, following the March 11 crash in the East River that killed five people.</Para><Para>I hope a helicopter ban is enacted. As an apartment dweller near the East River, I'm constantly assaulted by the noisy helicopters going up and down the river. Due to safety, emissions and noise pollution, all helicopter flights should be stopped.</Para><Para>Jeanne, New York</Para><Para>I don't know about banning them, but I would love to see a drastic cut in flights. Sitting at Brooklyn Bridge Park sounds like a war zone with the helicopters.</Para><Para>ggirl, Clinton Hill, Brooklyn</Para><Para>It's the noise pollution and the pollution from the engines that serve no purpose. If Mayor Bill de Blasio were concerned about the quality of life in New York, the copters would have been grounded. But the mayor doesn't like Manhattanites. He thinks were are all in the 1 percent. I have news for him: There are lots of middle-class and working-class folks here too.</Para><Para>m.pipik, New York</Para><Para>And also please let's ban helicopter tours of national parks. Apart from all the other environmental concerns, the noise pollution is incredible; it is the antithesis of what the experience of a wild place should be about.</Para><Para>siobhan, Northern California</Para><Para>Absolutely no, these flights should not be banned. The F.A.A. for decades has been putting the screws to general aviation aircraft and small operators such as this article addresses. Through superfluous regulations (banning would be an extreme example of such regulations) would only continue to squeeze Americans out of the sky in favor of fewer operators and eventually to a government sponsored monopoly. Perhaps change the procedures, but grounding Americans is not an option.</Para><Para>Pilot, Denton, Tex.</Para><Para>Dear Tourists: Please do all New Yorkers a favor and don't take the noisy, fume-spewing helicopters. There are many places where it is possible to get beautiful photographs of the skyline without having to grab shots quickly while working around the heads of other photographing passengers during a short and expensive (and, apparently, risky) ride.</Para><Para>Lynn, New York</Para><Para>They should be banned for the noise pollution alone! Why should profits of helicopter tour companies come before the rights of everybody else to enjoy a quiet peaceful day along the water?</Para><Para>Samuel Russell, Newark</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field"></Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">The Office of Administrative Trials and Hearings handles the violations of 13 New York City agencies. (PHOTOGRAPH BY GREGG VIGLIOTTI FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

