<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180325ee3p00057" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325250180</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p00057" fid="an"/><Num value="1505" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Book Review Desk; SECTBR</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm">NONFICTION</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Beyond Marie Curie</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>A LAB OF ONE'S OWN</Para><Para>Science and Suffrage in the First World War</Para><Para>By Patricia Fara</Para><Para>334 pp. Oxford University Press. $24.95.</Para><Para>BROAD BAND</Para><Para>The Untold Story of the Women Who Made the Internet</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By DAVA SOBEL </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="uk"/><Code value="eecz"/><Code value="eurz"/><Code value="weurz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gbook"/><Code value="ncolu"/><Code value="nrvw"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="gent"/><Code value="ncat"/><Code value="nfact"/><Code value="nfce"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325250180</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p00057" fid="an"/><Num value="1505" fid="wc"/><Num value="7314" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="070235" fid="upt"/><Time value="070235" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">8</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId276566134"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash0F32B4F5FD8A2529"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORGOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC42497"/><Code value="FSPRBC213843"/><Code value="FSPRBC214404"/><Code value="FSPRBC624992"/><Code value="FSPRBC808880"/><Code value="FSPRBC851990"/><Code value="FSPRBC852186"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="uk"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United Kingdom</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="624992"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="eecz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">European Union Countries</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:uk"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="eurz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Europe</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:uk"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="weurz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Western Europe</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:uk"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gbook"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Books</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="851990"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="42497"/><CodeA name="rule" value="213843"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncolu"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Columns</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="808880"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="852186"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nrvw"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Reviews</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="42497"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="213843"/><CodeA name="rule" value="214404"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gbook"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gent"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Arts/Entertainment</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gbook"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Content Types</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:ncolu"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nfact"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Factiva Filters</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nfce"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">C&amp;E Exclusion Filter</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Book Review Desk Review </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Book Review Desk; SECTBR</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field">NONFICTION</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Beyond Marie Curie</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>A LAB OF ONE'S OWN</Para><Para>Science and Suffrage in the First World War</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>By Patricia Fara</Para><Para>334 pp. Oxford University Press. $24.95.</Para><Para>BROAD BAND</Para><Para>The Untold Story of the Women Who Made the Internet</Para><Para>By Claire L. Evans</Para><Para>278 pp. Portfolio/Penguin. $27.</Para><Para>A woman scientist was such a rarity in early 20th-century Britain that other women could not conceal their surprise at encountering one. Even the eminent suffragist Emmeline Pankhurst, when seated next to a female engineer at a formal dinner, was heard to exclaim, ''But surely that's a very unsuitable occupation for a lady, isn't it?''</Para><Para>The nation that employed two million women as domestic servants in 1900 counted 200 female doctors and two female architects. The Great War upset that imbalance. By the time the war ended, almost a million British women were carrying out chemical work in munitions factories, while others were synthesizing medicines, developing antiaircraft systems and code-breaking in naval intelligence. As Patricia Fara recounts in ''A Lab of One's Own,'' however, many wartime advances in women's employment were rolled back soon after the Armistice.</Para><Para>Fara, who studied physics at Oxford, did not venture lightly into writing about suffrage and science. Her first book-length biographies focused on Isaac Newton, Carl Linnaeus and Joseph Banks, but her research must have convinced her that there were many women toiling -- anonymously and sometimes secretly -- alongside such famous men.</Para><Para>''A Lab of One's Own'' is an engrossing, exciting tale of uncelebrated scientists who innovated and experimented against a background of grand historical events. The numerous heroines named in its pages, many of whom come and go with only a brief mention, challenge the reader to keep track. Yet their very multitude underscores Fara's underlying argument that there is nothing unusual about a feminine engagement with science. The love of botany, the passion for chemistry, the fascination with geology or cosmology is just as likely to animate a girl's mind as a boy's. If only her parents, her circumstances and the cultural norms of her country will answer her interest with education and opportunity, any girl may aspire to a lab of her own.</Para><Para>For all Fara's erudition and scholarship, not to mention her description of herself as a ''pernickety academic'' at Clare College, Cambridge, she writes without a trace of stuffiness. She also avoids whining about chances missed or credit denied. With the same refreshing approach to perceived injustice that she displayed in earlier books like ''Pandora's Breeches'' and ''Science: A Four Thousand Year History,'' Fara bends her talents to a sprightly telling of what happened: ''At Imperial College London, during the First World War, Muriel Baker -- wife of the professor of inorganic chemistry -- was isolated at home in a small laboratory where she experimented on using stockings stuffed with cotton wool to absorb poisonous gases.''</Para><Para>Among the women Fara singles out for chapter-length treatment, Dr. Isabel Emslie Hutton led a particularly eventful life. ''Taught by her parents to give away all but one of her Christmas presents on New Year's Day, she committed herself to medicine at the age of 17, renouncing with the dedication of a nun all thoughts of marriage.'' Eventually she did marry Maj. Thomas Hutton, but not before working as a pathologist in a Scottish mental hospital, carrying out research into chemical tests for syphilis, selling experimental guinea pigs to laboratories throughout Scotland and seeing in the outbreak of World War I the opportunity to practice surgery, ''her favorite specialty but one normally reserved for men.''</Para><Para>Upon arrival in Salonika in October 1915, Emslie and her female colleagues ''built incinerators, dug latrines, erected tents, installed X-ray equipment and set up a dispensary in a disused silkworm factory.'' She operated on wounded soldiers in a wooden hut.</Para><Para>Military invasions and outbreaks of malaria kept Emslie moving from one field hospital to another -- even serving as a commanding officer -- all the way until the end of the war. Even then she stayed on in the region for two more years to treat civilian surgical patients in Serbia and children in Sebastopol.</Para><Para>Despite Emslie's distinguished war record, her marriage in 1921 disqualified her from future employment as a surgeon in Britain. Resuming a prior interest, she served three decades as honorary consultant psychiatrist at the British Hospital for Mental and Nervous Disorders in Camden, ''playing a key role in the introduction of psychoanalysis to Britain.'' At the same time she campaigned for equal pay for women doctors and helped women achieve international pilot's licenses by demonstrating that they were not ''incapable of flying during periods and pregnancies.'' When her husband was posted to India she gave up her own career to follow him. ''Trapped there during the Second World War,'' Isabel Emslie Hutton became director of the Indian Red Cross.</Para><Para>''A Lab of One's Own,'' with its title salute to Virginia Woolf, is primarily an English war story. ''Broad Band,'' in contrast, mostly takes place in the United States of the 1940s through the 1990s, and is peopled predominantly with all-American girls wanting, as Time magazine once quipped, ''a ROM of their own.''</Para><Para>The author, Claire L. Evans, has met and managed to interview most of the principals in this recent history of technology. Her familiarity puts the reader on a first-name basis with all of them, as well as with two important predecessors -- Ada (Countess of Lovelace, generally considered the world's first programmer) and Grace (Admiral Hopper, the Navy's much decorated queen of software).</Para><Para>Evans proves a companionable guide for a tour through cyberspace. An insightful, intelligent observer, she speaks fluent tech lingo, has written about science and sci-fi for the likes of Vice and Wired, and also sings in a pop group.</Para><Para>''When we say the words 'internet' and 'web,''' Evans writes, ''we often mean the same thing: the force, larger than nature, that emanates from our screens.'' But the internet predates the web by decades. It harks back to the time when folks ''dialed directly into each other's machines and into host computers to exchange files and post messages'' in text-only format. ''Many of these ad hoc networks interacted with, and eventually coalesced with, the infrastructure of the internet,'' a map of which today ''is a tensile, crazy, fractal thing'' akin to ''a beating heart, a web of synapses, a supernova.'' The World Wide Web sits atop the internet, functioning as ''a network of interconnected visual pages built in a shared language called HTML ... structured pages of text, images and video dotted with clickable links connecting individual points to one another. Those connections don't just influence how we navigate the web ... but how we communicate with one another, and ultimately how we understand the world.''</Para><Para>The women pioneers who penetrated the mostly male domain of early computing did not always fit the geek mold. When Radia Perlman, for example, enrolled in her first programming course as a high school student in the 1960s (and many more courses later as an odd-woman-out at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology), she discovered that her classmates had been dismantling radios and other electronics from a tender age. ''I never took anything apart,'' she told Evans. ''I would have assumed I would break it or get electrocuted.'' Nevertheless, Evans reports, Perlman invented a protocol for moving information that is now fundamental to the way computers are networked. ''Her work might be invisible to the everyday user, but it's invisible in the way that laws are invisible or the rules of traffic in a busy city are invisible: It directs the flow of information at a layer beyond our conscious awareness.''</Para><Para>Such contributions embolden Evans to declare, with emphasis: ''Even when women were invisible, it never means they weren't there.''</Para><Para>It is tempting to think these unsung female presences of the past paved the way for today's women scientists. In fact they did not. They filled particular niches that opened briefly before closing again, leaving scant evidence, let alone a path to follow. Most people struggle to name even one woman scientist (usually Marie Curie).</Para><Para>Both ''A Lab of One's Own'' and ''Broad Band'' -- along with numerous other recent titles like ''Hidden Figures,'' by Margot Lee Shetterly -- provide much needed perspective, along with presumed-absent foremothers and role models. As a genre, these true stories constitute a chorus of voices all saying the same thing: ''Yes, Virginia, there are women who do science.''</Para><Para>Follow New York Times Books on Facebook and Twitter (@nytimesbooks), sign up for our newsletter or our literary calendar. And listen to us on the Book Review podcast.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By DAVA SOBEL </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field">Dava Sobel is the author of ''Longitude,'' ''Galileo's Daughter'' and, most recently, ''The Glass Universe.'' </Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">British women in the 1920s using chemical processes to test batches of milk from cows. (PHOTOGRAPH FROM TOPICAL PRESS AGENCY/GETTY IMAGES) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

