<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180325ee3p0004r" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325420751</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p0004r" fid="an"/><Num value="1266" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Book Review Desk; SECTBR</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm">FICTION</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Compromising Positions</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>BACK TALK</Para><Para>Stories</Para><Para>By Danielle Lazarin</Para><Para>240 pp. Penguin Books. Paper, $16.</Para><Para>In an essay called ''On Pandering,'' which appeared in Tin House magazine in 2015, the novelist Claire Vaye Watkins wrote about the struggle to establish herself as a ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By CARMEN MARIA MACHADO </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"/><Code value="namz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gbook"/><Code value="ncolu"/><Code value="nrvw"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="gent"/><Code value="ncat"/><Code value="nfact"/><Code value="nfce"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325420751</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p0004r" fid="an"/><Num value="1266" fid="wc"/><Num value="5963" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="070226" fid="upt"/><Time value="070226" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">9</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId276566134"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash4E55A8A532269C73"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC42497"/><Code value="FSPRBC213843"/><Code value="FSPRBC214404"/><Code value="FSPRBC234480"/><Code value="FSPRBC808880"/><Code value="FSPRBC852186"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="234480"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gbook"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Books</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="42497"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="213843"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncolu"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Columns</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="808880"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="852186"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nrvw"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Reviews</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="42497"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="213843"/><CodeA name="rule" value="214404"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gbook"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gent"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Arts/Entertainment</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gbook"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Content Types</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:ncolu"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nfact"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Factiva Filters</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nfce"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">C&amp;E Exclusion Filter</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Book Review Desk Review </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Book Review Desk; SECTBR</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field">FICTION</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Compromising Positions</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>BACK TALK</Para><Para>Stories</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>By Danielle Lazarin</Para><Para>240 pp. Penguin Books. Paper, $16.</Para><Para>In an essay called ''On Pandering,'' which appeared in Tin House magazine in 2015, the novelist Claire Vaye Watkins wrote about the struggle to establish herself as a woman artist in the face of the patriarchy. It was, in part, a discussion of the way men, both well-intentioned and not, had consciously and subconsciously asserted their authority, but it was also an acknowledgment of her own complicity, her desire to pander to the male gaze. The essay was challenging, provocative and ultimately chilling in a ''the call is coming from inside the house'' sort of way. It put internalized misogyny on full display. It also became part of a larger conversation about divestment -- from maleness, from whiteness, from straightness and thinness and cisgenderness -- and how we might reconsider our assumptions about whose perspectives are worthy of literary treatment.</Para><Para>At the time, Watkins was accused of, among other things, a distinctly heteronormative frame of reference, of presuming that only straight women writers were capable of being ensnared in the blithely wielded cross hairs of men. But the truth is, all women writers find themselves turning the crystal tumbler of their experience against men's light. (Men, on the other hand, just get to write about the light, and are applauded for it.) And so the question remains, grows ever larger: How do writers divest themselves from the pressures of the dominant culture while also addressing the burdensome weight of that dominant culture?</Para><Para>The majority of the protagonists in ''Back Talk,'' Danielle Lazarin's debut story collection, seemingly heterosexual women and girls, are caught in this very quandary. The stories drift around and over certain characters -- an American woman going to college in Paris, the members of a troubled family -- some connected in a common fictional universe and others simply echoes of one another, like the characters in Lucia Berlin's short fiction. The younger women are learning, however obliquely, to line themselves up with men, to put themselves in the context of a man's world. The older women are trying to extract themselves from that world and discovering how obscenely difficult this can be.</Para><Para>In ''American Men in Paris I Did Not Love,'' the story's very structure is defined by its male characters. The narrator has ''forgotten how to be around'' other women and instead moves through a series of relationships -- some sexual, some not -- in which she is almost comically uninvested. These men are insufferable: They smirk, they lecture, they play jokes they think are funny, they push boundaries. They use her, to paraphrase Virginia Woolf, as a mirror, enjoying the way she distorts their reflection in pleasant ways. She silently judges them, she dodges their moves. But only rarely does a radical impulse rise up: ''And for once I don't care whether the professor likes me, if I'm pleasant or easy to teach, whether my work is any good.'' But the impulse quickly fades. ''I am not beautiful, but I am pretty enough,'' she remarks. ''That year, and for years after, I hold on to the pretty parts, to the appearance of being open. If only I had allowed myself to look mean in those photos.''</Para><Para>The depiction of these recurring themes is stressful in its realism. Some of Lazarin's stories -- not coincidentally, my favorites -- show women pinging furiously off one another instead of their boyfriends, husbands and fathers, gathering incremental surges of strength and autonomy and rage, of unspoken power. In ''The Holographic Soul,'' two young sisters playact a psychic guessing game, then try to actually access their powers, longing for a presence to manifest itself and give them something solid on which to pin their anxieties. The two teenage friends in ''Gone'' keep a list of real-life dead girls, sharing their fear as puberty descends. (''Girls are taught to be discreet,'' Lazarin writes in a later story. ''Boys, who shout their own terror, make a mess of it, take you down with them.'')</Para><Para>It's easy to anticipate criticism of ''Back Talk'' and its quietly realist, ''literary'' writing. It won't help to note that Lazarin's characters are educated and middle- to upper-class, that her stories are often set in New York and Paris. They are, certainly, beautifully crafted. I loathe the word ''polished'' in the context of prose. It's too clinical, implying that the work was dull before the author intentionally spruced it up. So I'd prefer to say that the sentences in these stories are living and seamless, as if Lazarin had run her hand over them until they became smooth and gleaming with the evidence of her touch. Yet they are not without viscera; sublimated rage fills the crevices between them.</Para><Para>Lazarin's style succeeds in part because the stakes for her characters are wide-ranging, because the implications of their actions ripple outward. In ''Back Talk,'' the theme of internalized misogyny is, to be quite blunt, terrifying. It's all the scarier in that it's so quietly and accurately rendered: These women aren't running screaming through the night, fleeing to convents, joining all-female cults or driving off into the desert without looking back.</Para><Para>In ''Spider Legs,'' the teenage narrator goes to Paris to visit her mother, who is writing a book about St. Agnes. Long divorced from the girl's father, she has chosen as her subject this woman of early Christian Rome, honored by the church for spurning the marriage proposals that would have spared her from suffering and martyrdom. ''For that, she was tortured, shamed, killed, of course,'' the narrator's mother tells her with a wry smile. ''No sense of self-preservation, those saints.''</Para><Para>How ironic that the choice is between death and assimilation, loss of identity and survival. Although Lazarin's work has the tone and style of traditional mainstream short fiction, it joins a growing canon of quietly realist stories that establish women's experiences as worthy of literary attention. And not just women's experiences: These stories also explore the exhausting, slow poison of masculine power, the grind of the patriarchy on even the most privileged of women, the subtle ways in which men have trained women to minimize themselves.</Para><Para>The hunger for these types of stories is powerful. How else to explain the ferocious explosion of emotion aroused by Kristen Roupenian's New Yorker story ''Cat Person''? It shared many qualities with Lazarin's work -- quiet, literary, realist -- but it made a particular generation of women feel as if they were about to crawl out of their skin, as if they suddenly remembered how bad things had been, how bad they could be, how bad they could get.</Para><Para>In ''American Men in Paris I Did Not Love,'' Lazarin's narrator finds herself in the presence of an insufferable pedant who is probably married and certainly has designs on her. ''We spend four hours together,'' she notes flatly, ''before I remember that I can just get up and go.'' And so these stories hand their warnings to us: Don't be pleasant or easy to teach. Look mean for the camera. Just get up and go.</Para><Para>Follow New York Times Books on Facebook and Twitter , sign up for our newsletter or our literary calendar . And listen to us on the Book Review podcast .</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By CARMEN MARIA MACHADO </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field">Carmen Maria Machado's story collection, ''Her Body and Other Parties,'' was a finalist for the National Book Award. </Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">DRAWING (DRAWING BY AMBER VITTORIA) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

