<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180325ee3p0009m" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325110434</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p0009m" fid="an"/><Num value="1011" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="25"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Metropolitan Desk; SECTMB</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Ah, Spring, You're Such a Tease</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>People, did you enjoy it while it lasted -- spring?</Para><Para>Even if it surfaced for only one day before winter returned in buckets, wasn't it a thing to behold?</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By JOHN LELAND </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usny"/><Code value="nyc"/><Code value="namz"/><Code value="usa"/><Code value="use"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325110434</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p0009m" fid="an"/><Num value="1011" fid="wc"/><Num value="4460" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="070428" fid="upt"/><Time value="070428" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">8</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId276566134"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashE5C0FBCCD5C8C144"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC213858"/><Code value="FSPRBC474774"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usny"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">New York State</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="200"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="213858"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:nyc"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="3"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nyc"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">New York City</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="474774"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="4"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:nyc"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:nyc"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="use"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Northeast U.S.</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usny"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:nyc"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="213858"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Metropolitan Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Metropolitan Desk; SECTMB</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Ah, Spring, You're Such a Tease</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>People, did you enjoy it while it lasted -- spring?</Para><Para>Even if it surfaced for only one day before winter returned in buckets, wasn't it a thing to behold?</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>The lengthening daylight, the restlessness during afternoon math class, the premonitory whiff of gefilte fish and vinegary egg dye that signifies that Ernie Anastos Day (Mar. 21) is upon us, and beckons the bears of New York to pull their tank tops out of winter hibernation. Spring!</Para><Para>To mark the season's first day, we sent five photographers to document it throughout the five boroughs -- in nature and fashion, in courtship and recreation and shopping. Visions of short shorts and food carts danced in the photographers' heads: Frisbees arcing over Central Park, ospreys returning to Jamaica Bay, couples flirting on the Staten Island Ferry, crocuses waking from their annual slumber.</Para><Para>''For me, spring looks like a lot more sun, more time outdoors, and a lot more kids on the trains,'' said An Rong Xu, who set out to capture spring's arrival in the fashions of Staten Island. ''Things are in flux. The city starts getting more crowded, everything's heating up, and summer hits before you get to enjoy spring.''</Para><Para>Welcome, instead, to the first day of spring 2018.</Para><Para>This year, the seasons resemble less an orderly tilting of the earth's axis than the hotels on the Vegas Strip, where Egypt, the Caribbean, ancient Rome and Treasure Island all tumble together at random. On Feb. 21, the heart of winter, the temperature in the city hit 78 degrees. Now look at this mess. Instead of three-month seasons, we get a jumble of microseasons, with a few episodes of Reese Witherspoon interrupted by a high pressure front of ''Westworld.'' Life does not imitate art so much as the cable upfronts.</Para><Para>Which is to say, if you're heading out this spring, bring your sunscreen and a warm scarf. Or stay home and watch television instead. Somewhere on the great cable spectrum, the sun is shining. Even if it is midnight.</Para><Para>In Manhattan, where Andres Kudacki sought the jubilance of spring retail fever, he found instead people stocking provisions against more winter. ''Very gray and depressed,'' he said. Mr. Kudacki, who grew up in Argentina and recently lived in Spain, was looking forward to his third spring in New York. And he will no doubt get it.</Para><Para>Eventually.</Para><Para>But whatever the weather, some rites of spring are not to be denied. March brings college basketball madness, Lent nears its end, pitchers and catchers head for Florida and snowbirds head back up north. Days are finally as long as nights, and they're still growing. The Persian New Year, Nowruz, brings a fresh start to the calendar year and a warning flag for allergy season. Autumn may be the beginning of the end, but spring is the beginning of the beginning. It's all promise, even when it fails to deliver. You can't keep a good tank top down forever.</Para><Para>''People want to be outside with people,'' said Amy Lombard, whose assignment was to capture spring love in Queens. ''With that first warm day, everyone is a million times nicer. I don't know anyone who's had an easy winter, whether you're talking about the news or the weather. Just life. This is getting ridiculous.''</Para><Para>Alas, love proved hard to find. Or else it stayed indoors, which can be trouble, but also a lot of fun.</Para><Para>On the other hand, maybe the calendar makers had cool weather in mind when they started spring in March. If it is the season of renewal, perhaps it calls for a leap into the cold -- daring, defiant, perhaps a little foolish. Imprudent, as the great basketball announcer Walt Frazier might say. It's a season for the bold. Bring on the snow. Spring is all about hope and belief in warmer days to come. It's the time to plant, not to harvest.</Para><Para>''I was an athlete, so the weather change is about that transfer from indoors to outside,'' said Adrienne Grunwald, who photographed leisure in Brooklyn. ''It's still too chilly, but you're happy to get out of that gym. There's a sense of relief. It feels like we're all starting again, getting a fresh start. But you have to run around to get warmed up.''</Para><Para>And even in the cold, signs of spring burst out. Searching for colorful blooms or plumage in the Bronx, Elias Williams, who considers spring mainly a warm-up act for summer, found man-made substitutes: hanging laundry, street art tags and shopping bags that grew on trees. Ms. Grunwald found sunflowers trying to put on a good face. And Mr. Kudacki found the bumper season's secret: that another day of cold means another day to wear that fur coat. Fret not, short shorts, your day will come. And if recent patterns hold, it will come too soon.</Para><Para>On days like this, it can be hard to imagine the weather ever turning warm again. But nothing lasts forever. Except, of course, the marshmallow Peeps in the drugstore window.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By JOHN LELAND </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Clockwise from left: early spring scenes at an ice rink in Prospect Park; the Botanical Garden in the Bronx; Midtown; and in Sunset Park, Brooklyn. (PHOTOGRAPHS BY ADRIENNE GRUNWALD FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES; ELIAS WILLIAMS FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES; ANDRES KUDACKI FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES); Above left, a discarded egg carton in the Bronx. Left, chickens in Queens. Above, Xavier Green sitting with his girlfriend, Hazel Nolasco, aboard the Staten Island Ferry. (PHOTOGRAPHS BY ELIAS WILLIAMS FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES; AMY LOMBARD FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES; AN RONG XU FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES) (MB8); From the day after the vernal equinox: top, a nor'easter blast in Manhattan; left, emerging into the cold air; above, a stretch of Broadway that doesn't evoke the season. (PHOTOGRAPHS BY RAMSAY de GIVE FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES) (MB9) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

