<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180321ee3l0003w" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180321906492</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180321ee3l0003w" fid="an"/><Num value="1506" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180321" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="30"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Foreign Desk; SECTA</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">The Warm, Soft Truth: Canada's Backyard Rinks Are Melting</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>WATERLOO, Ontario -- Jack Williams and his sister, Cara, sat in their kitchen watching their backyard rink melt.</Para><Para>''Dad calls it a big birdbath,'' said Jack, who is 12.</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By JOHN SCHWARTZ </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="caon"/><Code value="cana"/><Code value="namz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gnatcn"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="genv"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180321906492</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180321ee3l0003w" fid="an"/><Num value="1506" fid="wc"/><Num value="6693" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180321" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180321" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180321" fid="md"/><Time value="070023" fid="upt"/><Time value="070023" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">8</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId274903211"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash7EFE360A5A2AB4F6"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSPRBC624990"/><Code value="FSPRBC800665"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="caon"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Ontario</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180309132020"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="140"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="624990"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018566-20180320-194945"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="cana"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Canada</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180309132020"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="138"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:caon"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:caon"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:cana"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gnatcn"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Environmental Protection</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="800665"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018566-20180320-194945"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gnatcn"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="genv"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Natural Environment</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gnatcn"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000997-20180320-161217"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Foreign Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Foreign Desk; SECTA</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">The Warm, Soft Truth: Canada's Backyard Rinks Are Melting</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>WATERLOO, Ontario -- Jack Williams and his sister, Cara, sat in their kitchen watching their backyard rink melt.</Para><Para>''Dad calls it a big birdbath,'' said Jack, who is 12.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Their father, Ian, lovingly rebuilds the rink every year. He shovels it clear after each snowfall, and occasionally finishes the 24-foot-by-48-foot surface with hot water. He frets over every leaf that lands on the ice: they warm with the sunlight and create mini-craters.</Para><Para>A rink like the Williamses' used to offer good skating in this part of Canada from early December into March. But on this late February afternoon, the temperature outside was 55 degrees and rain had fallen steadily all day. The week before, two feet of snow -- mostly gone now, with leftover mounds seeping foggy wisps into the saturated air -- blanketed the ground.</Para><Para>Mr. Williams makes a rink every year because he had one across the street when he was a child. Long seasons on the ice helped him get good enough to play college hockey.</Para><Para>''You want your kids to experience a little of the goodness you had when you were growing up,'' he said. He has seen Jack and Cara's skills improve, and he enjoys when their friends come over to skate and play hockey or just goof around on the ice.</Para><Para>But Mr. Williams is finding it hard to maintain the ice in a warming world. ''There's a huge difference between when I grew up and was skating outside, and the last five years of skating out here,'' he said. ''Will my kids, my grandkids, be able to play in an outdoor rink? Probably not. It might be a dying tradition.''</Para><Para>That day last month happened to be the warmest Feb. 20 in recorded history for Waterloo. The previous record was set in 2016, noted Robert McLeman, an environmental scientist at Wilfrid Laurier University here. ''You're here on a landmark day,'' he told me. ''And if you come back in a couple of years, you'll probably have another one.''</Para><Para>An hour away in Brantford -- hometown of Wayne Gretzky, who learned to skate on a backyard rink made by his father -- a huge flood forced me to cancel a tour of local rinks and required thousands of residents to evacuate their homes.</Para><Para>Climate change is warming the Northern Hemisphere rapidly, largely because of the greenhouse gases that humans have put into the atmosphere since the beginning of the industrial age.</Para><Para>Mr. McLeman, with Colin Robertson, both associate professors of geography at Wilfrid Laurier, created Rink Watch, a citizen science project that has enlisted more than 1,500 backyard rink owners like Mr. Williams -- about 80 percent of them in Canada -- to report skating conditions on a daily basis.</Para><Para>Climate change does not mean the immediate end of cold weather, as recent nor'easters have shown, but it is putting a squeeze on outdoor skating, a deep part of this country's cultural identity. Irregular freezing weather is not enough for a good outdoor rink; consistency is key.</Para><Para>At least five days of hard freezing, 14 degrees Fahrenheit or lower, is essential to start a rink, Mr. McLeman said. And 23 degrees or lower is required from then on to maintain a good surface.</Para><Para>''Any warmer than that and the rink is no longer skateable,'' he said. ''And that's sort of on the horizon for us in the second half of the 21st century,'' with warmer temperatures and more frequent thaws shrinking the season for outdoor skating. ''Is anyone going to put in the effort for just a few, or just a couple, of weeks?''</Para><Para>Combining projections of climate change with their current data, the Rink Watch researchers have projected the number of skating days to decline by 34 percent in Toronto and 19 percent in Calgary by 2090.</Para><Para>''As average inter-month temperature regimes across large parts of northern North America and Eurasia warm into this window over the course of the coming century, growing numbers of people will experience winters that are cold and icy, but not cold or icy enough to skate,'' they wrote in a report published in The Canadian Geographer.</Para><Para>Mr. McLeman said that life without natural outdoor rinks was not unthinkable. But, he said, it would be sad. ''If you take that away from us, life will go on. We'll do the things we've always done,'' he said. ''But we'll lose a little bit of that cultural heritage.''</Para><Para>The National Hockey League expressed concern about the warming trend as part of its first sustainability report, issued in 2014. The league commissioner, Gary Bettman, wrote that ''Our sport can trace its roots to frozen freshwater ponds, to cold climates.''</Para><Para>Many immigrants to Canada and their families, Mr. McLeman said, find hockey as ''an entry point to access mainstream Canadian culture.'' He pointed to the N.H.L. defenseman P.K. Subban, whose parents came to Toronto from Jamaica and Montserrat. ''It's our version of the melting pot,'' he said. ''Anybody who shows up with skates and a stick can join in.''</Para><Para>Rink Watch has helped Canadians understand the real-life consequences of climate change, Mr. Robertson said: ''The fact that this could be taken away and is tied to climate has been a real eye-opener.''</Para><Para>Mr. McLeman added: ''Your average Canadian will never see a polar bear in the wild, will never see a glacier, will never go to the South Pacific. There's no personal connection. But say your kids or grandkids might not be able to skate on the backyard rink, and they say, 'Oh, I see the connection!'''</Para><Para>Canadian officials are coming to grips with the implications of climate change for their open-air town rinks. Brantford, a city of 100,000 people, maintains as many as 25 outdoor rinks each winter through the work of volunteers. The large number of rinks for such a small city means that most young people can skate within walking distance of home.</Para><Para>But Lori-Dawn Cavin, the manager of community recreation development for Brantford, said she was uncertain how long that could last. Despite many days of bitter cold this winter, she said, ''Two days of Mother Nature not cooperating, and all their work basically drains away.''</Para><Para>While nothing has been formally decided, city officials are talking about concentrating Brantford's efforts on a smaller number of artificially refrigerated rinks that will stand up to moderate thaws. So far, they have not acted on the idea because the volunteers are determined to keep the old-fashioned rinks open, and the city is committed to the volunteers.</Para><Para>Some parents, too, are anticipating a future without their backyard hobby. Marcin Parobek lives down the street from Mr. Williams in Waterloo. As he and his wife, Anna, talked about the joys and frustrations of the rink maintenance they do together, their two boys, Stanley and Lucas, looked out at the watery mess as the afternoon light began to fade.</Para><Para>Mr. Parobek knows that the world is warming. The river he skated on as a boy in Poland no longer freezes over in winter. So, too, will Canada's backyard skating season decline. ''At some point, if it's too short, why do it?'' he asked. ''It's not worth the effort.''</Para><Para>Yet other parents say they will hold on to the tradition as long as they can. Michael Berube, a Rink Watch participant in Miramichi, New Brunswick, who has won a Great Canadian Hoser award for his rink, said, ''It's almost like meditation when I get out there at night.''</Para><Para>Will it ever be too much trouble? ''Never. I love it.'' He will keep building rinks, he said, ''As long as I've still got some kids that are willing to play on it.''</Para><Para>Jean-François Ouimet, a Rink Watch participant who lives in Montreal, said he loved to see his three children, Antoine, who is 14, Ariane, 11, and 4-year-old Delphine, come in from the ice ''with red cheeks.'' He chuckled. ''You know they're going to sleep well.''</Para><Para>Skating, he said, offers an alternative to electronic lures. ''When I was a kid, the challenge was turning off the TV and going outside to play,'' he said. Now, with game consoles and Minecraft and cellphones, ''the challenge is even greater.''</Para><Para>The rink changes the equation. ''When you first pick up your kids at school and the first thing they ask is, 'Can we go skating tonight?,' you know you've fulfilled your mission.''</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By JOHN SCHWARTZ </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Clockwise from top: Jack and Cara Williams on the backyard rink built by their father, Ian, in Waterloo, Ontario; a puck out of its element in the Waterloo yard of Marcin Parobek; Mr. Williams showing photographs of his children skating in colder times; Mr. Parobek son Lucas, 8, looking out at his melting backyard rink. (PHOTOGRAPHS BY AARON VINCENT ELKAIM FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

