<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180325ee3p00044" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325868647</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p00044" fid="an"/><Num value="1357" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="25"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Book Review Desk; SECTBR</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm">EDITORS' CHOICE</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Staff Picks From the Book Review</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>The life of the body as a physical object is all over this week's recommended titles, from Alan Hollinghurst's customarily sexy new novel to Maya Dusenbery's consideration of women's health to Kevin Toolis's study of death rituals around ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by"></Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"/><Code value="namz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gbook"/><Code value="gpol"/><Code value="ncolu"/><Code value="nrvw"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="gent"/><Code value="gpir"/><Code value="ncat"/><Code value="nfact"/><Code value="nfce"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325868647</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p00044" fid="an"/><Num value="1357" fid="wc"/><Num value="6497" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="070214" fid="upt"/><Time value="070214" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">23</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId276566134"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash10FAC6A4BC9FB082"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORGOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSPRBC42497"/><Code value="FSPRBC213843"/><Code value="FSPRBC214404"/><Code value="FSPRBC234480"/><Code value="FSPRBC799599"/><Code value="FSPRBC808880"/><Code value="FSPRBC824601"/><Code value="FSPRBC851992"/><Code value="FSPRBC852186"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="234480"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gbook"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Books</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="824601"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="42497"/><CodeA name="rule" value="851992"/><CodeA name="rule" value="213843"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gpol"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Domestic Politics</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="799599"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncolu"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Columns</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="808880"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="852186"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nrvw"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Reviews</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="42497"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="213843"/><CodeA name="rule" value="214404"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gbook"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gpol"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gent"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Arts/Entertainment</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gbook"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gpir"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Politics/International Relations</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gpol"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Content Types</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:ncolu"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nfact"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Factiva Filters</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nfce"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">C&amp;E Exclusion Filter</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nrvw"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Book Review Desk List </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Book Review Desk; SECTBR</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field">EDITORS' CHOICE</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Staff Picks From the Book Review</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>The life of the body as a physical object is all over this week's recommended titles, from Alan Hollinghurst's customarily sexy new novel to Maya Dusenbery's consideration of women's health to Kevin Toolis's study of death rituals around the world. There's even a history of Victorian approaches to the flesh, which includes a detailed analysis of Charles Darwin's various beard styles and what they tell us about the era's ideals of masculinity. Brooklyn hipsters, take note.</Para><Para>Of course, times being what they are, we also have books about the body politic: In ''The People vs. Democracy,'' Yascha Mounk writes about the rise of populist movements and in ''Impeachment: A Citizen's Guide,'' Cass R. Sunstein writes about the constitutional hurdles to that particular political remedy. We also have new fiction (physical, political and other) from Peter Carey, Donna Leon, Mario Vargas Llosa and Elizabeth Crook.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Gregory Cowles</Para><Para>Senior Editor, Books</Para><Para>THE SPARSHOLT AFFAIR, by Alan Hollinghurst. (Knopf, $28.95.) Hollinghurst's sixth novel plays out across nearly a century of gay life in England, as a hazy sex scandal reverberates through the lives of the characters. ''When Hollinghurst picks up an aspect of human experience, however banal -- riding a bus, sitting for a portrait, being on a sailboat -- he is so exacting that it's as if no one has described these things before,'' our critic Dwight Garner said. ''Hollinghurst is a cerebral sensualist. His characters work themselves into each other's hearts and minds as devotedly as they work themselves into each other's underpants.''</Para><Para>DOING HARM: The Truth About How Bad Medicine and Lazy Science Leave Women Dismissed, Misdiagnosed, and Sick, by Maya Dusenbery. (HarperOne/HarperCollins, $27.99.) Through an orderly blizzard of studies and statistics, Dusenbery examines sexism at every level in medicine from medical school admissions on up. Her book, which our critic Parul Sehgal calls well researched and ''wonderfully truculent,'' argues that women are regarded as unreliable narrators who can't even testify to their own pain. ''This cultural distrust of women -- ancient and ingrained -- is shown to govern quality of care at every stage of treatment,'' Sehgal writes, to sometimes shocking effect, as when a breast-cancer patient opts for a mastectomy only for her doctor to object: ''But you aren't married.''</Para><Para>THE PEOPLE VS. DEMOCRACY: Why Our Freedom Is in Danger &amp; How to Save It, by Yascha Mounk. (Harvard University, $29.95.) The title of this book makes clever use of what looks like a glaring oxymoron: After all, what is democracy if not rule by the people? But Mounk, who lectures on political theory at Harvard, shows how populist insurgencies can undermine democracy in the long run. ''One of the many things to recommend this clarifying book is its international scope,'' our critic Jennifer Szalai writes. ''As much as Donald J. Trump might fancy himself one of a kind, Mounk argues that the American president is part of a global wave.''</Para><Para>IMPEACHMENT: A Citizen's Guide, by Cass R. Sunstein. (Harvard University, paper, $7.95.) Sunstein's topic has obvious contemporary resonance, as Andrew Sullivan notes in his review, and though this short book does not take up the Trump presidency directly it does tease out ''various hypotheticals with some similarities to our current concerns,'' concluding that ''each of these is an impeachable offense.'' Yet Sunstein also cautions that the Constitution was written to ensure that a clear national consensus was necessary if a president was to be judged to be gravely violating his oath of office, or betraying the country. ''This is why in well over two centuries the impeachment power has been invoked against sitting presidents only four times,'' Sullivan writes, ''and never actually pursued to conviction.''</Para><Para>THE TEMPTATION OF FORGIVENESS, by Donna Leon. (Atlantic Monthly, $26.) Commissario Guido Brunetti embarks on another atmospheric Venetian criminal investigation, this time coming to the aid of a woman whose husband has been attacked on one of the city's stone bridges. ''Tagging along after this sleuth is a wonderful way to see Venice like a native,'' Marilyn Stasio writes in the Book Review's crime column, ''especially since Leon takes care to give us precise directions for his routes. But Brunetti's observations aren't always pretty. The air pollution is beyond acceptable limits, and don't even mention the pollution of the canals.''</Para><Para>A LONG WAY FROM HOME, by Peter Carey. (Knopf, $26.95.) This latest novel from the two-time Booker Prize-winning author of ''True History of the Kelly Gang'' and ''Oscar and Lucinda'' follows a married couple and their bachelor neighbor on a bumptious 10,000-mile auto race in 1950s Australia, grappling along the way with the country's historical treatment of its Aboriginal population. ''With all its inventive momentum, all its pleasurable beats, the fast pace of the race, the scenery unfurling, the novel ends up far from where it started, in a place of historical reckoning and colonial guilt,'' Craig Taylor writes in his review. ''Carey's longtime readers will appreciate his arrival here. ... Using a wild road race, he's found a journey into Australia's broken past.''</Para><Para>MY FATHER'S WAKE: How the Irish Teach Us How to Live, Love and Die, by Kevin Toolis. (Da Capo, $26.) The hospital death of Toolis's brother, followed by his father's death in small-town Ireland, led him to examine death rituals around the world. The Irish wake, he concludes, is ''the best guide to life you could ever have.'' In her review, Ann Neumann says that the author's ''fine skill at showing the means and aftermath of death'' most animates the book: ''Toolis's writing is so visceral and profound when he is near dying bodies that the lessons of such experiences become evident.''</Para><Para>THE NEIGHBORHOOD, by Mario Vargas Llosa. Translated by Edith Grossman. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $26.) Written telenova-style, with chapters alternating among various characters, the Nobel laureate Vargas Llosa's new novel is an edgy sendup of life in Peru before the downfall of Alberto Fujimori. Wealthy friends find themselves in a difficult situation when one is blackmailed by a tabloid editor and the other, a lawyer, tries to help. ''In a diseased body politic ... no one is exempt from infection, and the sanity of every citizen is dependent upon that of his neighbor,'' Michael Greenberg writes in his review, speculating that ''the book's 'happy' ending reflects its author's belief, perhaps, in the power of individual morality and will.''</Para><Para>VICTORIANS UNDONE: Tales of the Flesh in the Age of Decorum, by Kathryn Hughes. (Johns Hopkins University, $29.95.) Hughes's detailed account of five notable 19th-century body parts topples great figures from their pedestals. From baby bumps to facial hair, the book asks what we can learn about a culture by studying the human bodies it produces. ''While microhistorians have long zoomed in on individual case studies, Hughes pinpoints her subjects even more narrowly,'' our reviewer, Leah Price, writes. ''Her ultimate question, though, is a broad one: How did the Victorians understand the interplay between mind and body?''</Para><Para>THE WHICH WAY TREE, by Elizabeth Crook. (Little, Brown, $26.) Crook's western-inflected novel follows a pair of siblings on their hunt for the wild panther that upended their lives. The teenage narrator ''unspools his tale of Civil War-era Texas in a first-person voice that is utterly convincing, consistent and believable,'' Paulette Jiles says, in a review that finds echoes of ''Moby-Dick'' in the siblings' quest. (''Think Ahab in the Texas Hill Country.'') The book's voice, Jiles adds, ''swings between the rhythms of the Southern hills and the lofty, elevated tone encountered in Twain and contemporary westerns (which ultimately comes from an acquaintance with the King James Bible).''</Para><Para>Follow New York Times Books on Facebook and Twitter , sign up for our newsletter or our literary calendar . And listen to us on the Book Review podcast .</Para><Para>This is a more complete version of the story than the one that appeared in print.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field"></Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

