<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="NYTF000020180325ee3p0004q" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210950" rl="100">NYT</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325095648</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p0004q" fid="an"/><Num value="1627" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="nytf" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="28"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Style Desk; SECTST</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm">MODERN LOVE</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">First Try the Pastrami, Then the Polyamory</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Over pastrami sandwiches, my new boyfriend said to me: ''One of my ex-lovers is going to be at the conference I'm attending next week. We'll be sharing a room and sleeping together.''</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By DEBBIE WEISS </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"/><Code value="namz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"/><Code value="ncolu"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="ncat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">20180325095648</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="NYTF000020180325ee3p0004q" fid="an"/><Num value="1627" fid="wc"/><Num value="6990" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="070226" fid="upt"/><Time value="070226" fid="mt"/><PubEdition fid="ed">Late Edition - Final</PubEdition><PubPage fid="pg">6</PubPage><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="NYTF"/><Code value="fspFileId276566134"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="NEWSPLUS"/><Code value="NYC"/><Code value="SFNYT"/><Code value="TART"/><Code value="TBCFO"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWD"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="USNY"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash6580AC24865B8666"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC234480"/><Code value="FSPRBC622900"/><Code value="FSPRBC808880"/><Code value="FSPRBC852186"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="NYT_F" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">The New York Times Company</PublisherN><AttribCode value="NYTF" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="NYTF" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The New York Times</SrcName><Logo img="nytfLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="234480"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Living/Lifestyle</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="622900"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncolu"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Columns</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="808880"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="852186"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:glife"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Content Types</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:ncolu"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipd">Style Desk </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Style Desk; SECTST</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field">MODERN LOVE</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">First Try the Pastrami, Then the Polyamory</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Over pastrami sandwiches, my new boyfriend said to me: ''One of my ex-lovers is going to be at the conference I'm attending next week. We'll be sharing a room and sleeping together.''</Para><Para>I blinked away tears. ''I never wanted to know that,'' I said, wishing I had stayed home instead of making the 90-minute train trip to see him.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>''I'm sorry,'' he said. ''I didn't mean to hurt you. I was just being honest.''</Para><Para>My guy was an Ivy League-educated doctor with an M.B.A., but he no longer practiced medicine or worked in business. Instead, he was training to become a tantric sex instructor while working on his songwriting. His name was Howard. He was polyamorous.</Para><Para>I was a widow of four years after being with my high school sweetheart, George, for 32. I had dived into the cesspool of online dating looking for love, but my manic dog paddling hadn't produced that. For now, I was settling for weird.</Para><Para>Howard was sweet, smart and honest to several faults. I liked him, but I also saw him as an experiment. If I couldn't find Mr. Right, what about Mr. Quasi-Right augmented by a few others?</Para><Para>We had been together for only a couple of months, spending Saturday nights together with an occasional weeknight thrown in. I suspected his other nights were reserved for other women, but I didn't want to know. We lived in the San Francisco Bay Area, 13 train stops apart -- I in Danville, a placid East Bay suburb, and he in the bustling Mission district.</Para><Para>Worse, we were far apart in what we wanted. We were both culturally Jewish but our versions were different. Even though my family wasn't religious, my upbringing had been prudish. I couldn't see even cultural Jewishness coexisting with polyamory. The idea of having a beloved, or ''beshert'' (an idealistic word I had stopped using after my husband died), seemed so ingrained to being Jewish.</Para><Para>Howard wanted to move beyond the monogamous model he had been raised with; I wanted to replicate it. Not surprisingly, I didn't want to move to San Francisco and he couldn't see himself living in Danville.</Para><Para>We were both still active online, seeing other people. When Howard told me about his conference, I said, ''I should be honest, too. I'll be going on a couple of first dates while you're gone.'' But the prospect of a tentative first kiss couldn't compete with his announcement that he would be spending multiple nights with someone else.</Para><Para>During the week of the conference, I kept picturing him in bed with some faceless woman, a gold chain sparkling around her slender waist. Their imaginary sex was both tender and incendiary, fueled by shared pasts, synchronized breathing and enviable muscle control.</Para><Para>He had told me he wanted a primary partner, someone to live with and plan a future together. But there were caveats.</Para><Para>''What does it mean for you to be polyamorous and in a relationship?'' I said a couple of weeks later, sitting in his sunken living room with views of the bay, reminding myself I probably shouldn't get too comfortable there.</Para><Para>''Along with having a primary partner,'' he said, ''I need to have a few nights with some former lovers, plus one fling a year.''</Para><Para>''Why must keeping up with old lovers involve sleeping together?'' I said. ''Couldn't you just meet for lunch?''</Para><Para>''I've been poly for seven years,'' he said. ''I can love more than one person at a time. Part of being poly is being able to realize your full potential.''</Para><Para>''But why is your potential tied up with sex?'' I said. ''It's the difference between taking a pottery class because you want to try pottery and needing to sleep with the pottery teacher.''</Para><Para>With all of those lovers and flings, life with Howard looked like being a housekeeper with benefits. We would be maintaining a partnership so that we could give the best of ourselves to other people. An introvert, I wanted to fall in love with one person so I could stop flinging myself around. I wanted to stay home with true love and plenty of time to read. What is seeking a fling when you're in a committed relationship if not the need to feed your ego with fresh meat?</Para><Para>I asked Howard if he minded that I sometimes slept with my ex-boyfriend, a spiky-haired, green-eyed guitarist.</Para><Para>''No, I'm good with it,'' he said. ''It's easier if we both want to spend time with old lovers.''</Para><Para>But my ex-boyfriend couldn't deal with Howard, so I ended my attempt at ex-lover polyamory.</Para><Para>Howard called polyamory ''consensual non-monogamy,'' meaning you could have sex with other people so long as all parties agreed. It involved a lot of mature, evolved discussion about setting parameters.</Para><Para>I'm a former lawyer. This sounded like drafting a settlement agreement. And if we couldn't agree to the terms, would Howard mope around the house moaning that I never let him do anything fun?</Para><Para>I called polyamory ''exposure to disease.'' Even in your primary relationship you always would have to practice safe sex, because your partner was seeing other people. And it always would be emotionally dangerous because he may come to like one of those people more than he liked you. If we both loved other people, wouldn't we want to spend our time with them? It sounded like a recipe for disaster. You could fall in love with your fling.</Para><Para>As early as 2009, Newsweek asked whether polyamory was the next sexual revolution. But back then it wasn't on my radar because I had George. Polyamory has been classified as both a sexual orientation and a lifestyle choice. It seems some people are wired to be in simultaneous relationships and aren't jealous when their partners are too. But many of the questions on sites providing advice about polyamory are from secondary partners who are jealous of their lover's primary relationship.</Para><Para>''When I'm committed to someone,'' I said to Howard, ''I don't want to see other people. And I don't want to hear that you do.''</Para><Para>In my post-George dating years, I had developed a protective shell over my heart. Allowing myself to love again would mean letting that shell crack and fall away, not maintaining it because my partner invited strangers to trample through our relationship. The whole thing seemed so avoidable. At some point, we would have to agree to become exclusive. If either of us were attracted to someone else, we would suffer our lust in silence like decent people.</Para><Para>Then there was my own weakness. If I settled for a man who slept with other people, I would be tempted to do it, too, if for no other reason than to quell my insecurity that I wasn't enough. We could both return home the next morning with smiles on our faces. But I wouldn't be smiling; I'd be in pain.</Para><Para>Howard used the word ''and'' to replace ''but'' in conversation. He said ''but'' indicated an either/or situation, whereas ''and'' suggested coexistence. When I first met him, I tried using ''and'' too, hoping to see more possibilities. ''I want to fall in love and still sleep around.'' ''I want to fall in love but still sleep around.''</Para><Para>Over time I returned to ''but,'' seeing only a linguistic conceit.</Para><Para>When I first met Howard, I had wanted to be open to a different kind of life than when I was married, one that wasn't necessarily monogamous. But that's not me. Maybe I was limiting myself by being so traditional. Or maybe I was finding myself, because years after losing George I was again open to love. I just needed to stop sleeping with my ex-boyfriend and dating men with no long-term potential.</Para><Para>''Stop wasting your love energy on guys you have no future with,'' one of my girlfriends said, quoting her therapist. But she too was still online looking for Mr. Forever while sleeping with Mr. Temporary as a palliative.</Para><Para>''You're my fling,'' I told Howard. ''Eventually I'll meet someone like me and this will end.''</Para><Para>A month later I did meet someone like me, another culturally Jewish lawyer who lived in the suburbs. We even had attended the same synagogue. We agreed that making love meant that we wouldn't see other people. But neither of us wanted to see other people anyway now that we had found each other.</Para><Para>Ending my relationship with Howard wasn't hard. It wasn't even bittersweet. It was more like walking out of a really good movie. I knew it was going to end. I could relate to the characters, but I couldn't be any of them.</Para><Para>Howard's version of polyamory, for all of its openness, was too constrained. He'd had all those years of accumulating experiences, but I'd had George. And I knew that when you find love, you jump in, almost involuntarily. You don't sit on the edge negotiating how to keep your options open.</Para><Para>To hear Modern Love: The Podcast, subscribe on iTunes or Google Play Music. To read past Modern Love columns, click here. Continue following our fashion and lifestyle coverage on Facebook (Styles and Modern Love), Twitter (Styles, Fashion and Weddings) and Instagram.</Para><Para>modernlove@nytimes.com</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By DEBBIE WEISS </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field">Debbie Weiss, a writer in Danville, Calif., is working on a memoir. </Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">DRAWING (DRAWING BY BRIAN REA) </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 The New York Times Company.  All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

