<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STBT000020180322ee3n0000h" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STBT000020180322ee3n0000h</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STBT000020180322ee3n0000h" fid="an"/><Num value="1461" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180323" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stbt" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">Business Times Singapore</SrcName><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Arts</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Arts Fest Shifts Course</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Boasting its share of marquee attractions, the Singapore International Festival of Arts returns next month with a new fest director and new ambitions</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Helmi Yusof , Arts Fest Shifts Course </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gfesti"/><Code value="gart"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="gent"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STBT000020180322ee3n0000h</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STBT000020180322ee3n0000h" fid="an"/><Num value="1461" fid="wc"/><Num value="7144" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180323" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="md"/><Time value="234516" fid="upt"/><Time value="234516" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STBT"/><Code value="fspFileId275748543"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBIZ"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPR"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="STBT"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash02C034AB12027D50"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATNS"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC603183"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC819336"/><Code value="FSPRBC851957"/><Code value="FSPRBC852100"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STBT" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STBT" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">Business Times Singapore</SrcName><Logo img="stbtLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="80"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018572-20180322-075252"/><CodeA name="rule" value="603183"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gfesti"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Festivals</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishNS_en_20180319142640"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="180"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="851957"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018572-20180322-075252"/><CodeA name="rule" value="852100"/><CodeA name="rule" value="819336"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gart"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Art</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishNS_en_20180319142640"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="120"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gfesti"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gart"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gent"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Arts/Entertainment</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gfesti"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gart"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000999-20180322-155044"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Arts</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Arts Fest Shifts Course</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Boasting its share of marquee attractions, the Singapore International Festival of Arts returns next month with a new fest director and new ambitions</Para><Para>THE UPCOMING Singapore International Festival of Arts (SIFA) will be a litmus test of sorts. It will be the first festival to be headed by festival director Gaurav Kripalani, taking over from former director Ong Keng Sen. And its success with audiences and artists will determine whether Mr Kripalani is right to steer the festival away from Mr Ong's more avant garde vision and back to an arguably more broad-based course.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Both appointments have not been without some controversy. Mr Ong's progressive and experimental programming drew much admiration and loyalty among hardcore arts lovers, but alienated novice audiences who struggled with many cutting-edge shows. Mr Kripalani's more conservative tastes have already ensured strong ticket sales for the more recognisable titles and stars (1984 and Jacob Collier, among others), but arts lovers who want to be challenged find his programming "too safe".</Para><Para>For his part, Mr Kripalani is sure that the festival's 41st edition already has a broad spread of works to please different pockets of audiences. He says: "We have such a different audience now compared to what it was 30 years ago. The audience base was small and it was the same people going for everything. Now it's more segmented and, within each art form, there are further sub-segments. A national festival such as SIFA should try to cater to all audiences, and its diverse programming must appeal to the different segments."</Para><Para>Commissioned by the National Arts Council, the festival's opening weekend on Apr 27 to 29 is set to draw large crowds to the Arts House with its free offerings. French circus act Cirque Rouages tells a story of love and loss while walking the tightrope. International music acts Tami Rogeon, Tcheka, Sultan of the Disco and bohemianvoodoo are ready to get audiences up and on their feet. Meanwhile the free closing weekend act, the famous Duke Ellington Orchestra, will draw several hundreds to the Singapore Botanic Gardens.</Para><Para>Free acts aside, Mr Kripalani has programmed two works with familiar titles aimed at attracting big enough crowds to fill the 1,950-seat Esplanade Theatre - a rare challenge for the festival. They are the stage version of George Orwell's dystopian classic 1984 and the celebrated director Thomas Ostermeier's production of Henrik Ibsen's Enemy of the People.</Para><Para>Besides them, other marquee titles include Ballet Preljocaj's Playlist #1, a showcase of excerpts from famous choreographer Angelin Preljocaj's best creations; L-E-V Dance Company's OCD Love, a contemporary dance based on Neil Hilborn's spoken word poem; and The Blues Project, a tap-dancing spectacle by the highly-regarded Dorrance Dance company. Other notable names include American classical composer Nico Muhly, Indian dynamic arts duo Shabana Azmi and Javed Akhtar, and Palestinian artist Amer Hlehel.</Para><Para>Beyond ensuring that these top attractions keep audience numbers up, Mr Kripalani - together with Sarah Martin, CEO of Art House Limited which manages the festival - wants to look at internationalising made-in-Singapore art.</Para><Para>He says: "It's always been a big goal for me to internationalise the Singaporean art scene and have Singapore-made works reach out farther. So one of the mandates of the festival is to facilitate local artists who want to collaborate with international artists. And then sounding out other festivals who might be interested in staging the work too.</Para><Para>"So if there's an artist whose goal is to be on the world stage, we want to help make that dream a reality." While this year's Singapore productions don't bear this out on account of this being Mr Kripalani's first year, upcoming editions of the festival will.</Para><Para>For full programme, visit sifa.sg. Tickets available on Sistic.</Para><Para>SIFA 2018 HIGHLIGHTS</Para><Para>01 PARABLE OF THE SOWER</Para><Para>By Toshi Reagon, Bernice Johnson Reagon and Eric Ting</Para><Para>Octavia E Butler's 1993 science fiction novel is strangely prophetic of our current times. It depicts a world afflicted by climate change, depleting resources, wealth inequality and power-hungry leaders. Now, musicians Toshi Reagon and Bernice Johnson Reagon have adapted the novel into an electrifying genre-defying opera with gorgeous African-American music, directed by Obie award-winning helmer Eric Ting.</Para><Para>May 4 &amp; 5, Victoria Theatre</Para><Para>02 JACOB COLLIER</Para><Para>This 23-year-old jazz prodigy first dazzled the world when his Youtube videos showcasing his one-man music-making abilities went viral. Subsequently, he signed on to Quincy Jones' label and his debut album In My Room earned two Grammies. His upcoming April 27 concert at Victoria Theatre quickly sold out, prompting SIFA to add a second show on the following night.</Para><Para>April 27 and 28, Victoria Theatre</Para><Para>03 1984</Para><Para>By Robert Icke, Duncan McMillan and Headlong Based on George Orwell's novel</Para><Para>George Orwell's classic novel has never seemed more relevant than now, as authoritarian leaders and parties across the world seek to cement their power and suppress sources of information. This adaptation by playwrights Robert Icke and Duncan McMillan is staged by the innovative UK theatre company Headlong, and has drawn mostly raves for its sharp if terrifying depiction of a surveillance state.</Para><Para>April 26 - 29, Esplanade Theatre</Para><Para>04 PLAYLIST #1</Para><Para>By Ballet Preljocaj</Para><Para>Angelin Preljocaj is one of the most prolific contemporary dance choreographers in the world. Playlist #1 is a collection of choice excerpts from 10 of his most memorable works, performed by his company Ballet Preljocaj. Among the highlights are his much-lauded Spectral Evidence danced to music by John Cage and his anything-but-innocent take on Snow White.</Para><Para>May 9 &amp; 10, Sota Drama Theatre</Para><Para>05 THE HIDDEN</Para><Para>By Kamini Ramachandran</Para><Para>One of Singapore's foremost storytellers Kamini Ramachandran finds inspiration in Singapore's oldest church, the Armenian Church, for a session of stories and myths spanning centuries. Ms Kamini says: "The Armenians are a very nomadic people, and that parallels how stories are disseminated over time, evolving and adapting to the local flavour." Taking place in the evening, she tells three stories against the atmospheric backdrop of the church, accompanied by Derrick Tay who plays various musical instruments. The first story is a gypsy tale, followed by an Armenian fairytale and an Indian story of unrequited love.</Para><Para>May 3 - 6, Armenian Church</Para><Para>06 0600</Para><Para>By Ground Z-0</Para><Para>Capital punishment remains a contentious issue around the world. Despite calls to repeal it, Singapore has maintained that the death penalty is an effective crime deterrent. New theatre company Ground Z-0 tackles the issue in a multimedia site-specific production set in National Gallery Singapore, which is formerly the Supreme Court Building. Audiences will move between the waiting cells and the courtroom, and see characters inspired by famous past cases. Director Zelda Tatiana Ng says: "As Singaporeans, many of us have mixed feelings about the death penalty. This is an attempt to seek some personal clarity, if not resolution."</Para><Para>April 27 - May 12, National Gallery Singapore</Para><Para>07 A DREAM UNDER THE SOUTHERN BOUGH - THE BEGINNING</Para><Para>By Toy Factory Productions</Para><Para>A Dream Under the Southern Bough is a classic Chinese tale of a discharged army officer who sleeps under a sophora tree and dreams of entering an ant hole where he meets the King of Ants and marries his daughter. Written in 1600 by Tang Xianzu, whose other classics include The Peony Pavilion, the story has been a staple of Chinese Kun opera for centuries. Now Singapore theatre company Toy Factory Productions is reworking it for the contemporary stage. Director Goh Boon Teck says: "The attraction of A Dream is that the story is so immersive and psychedelic, and yet it makes so much sense to anyone in any period because ultimately it is a human story. The language is very poetic and central to the story's appeal, so despite this being a contemporary retelling, we will not compromise on the language."</Para><Para>April 30 - May 1, SOTA Studio Theatre</Para><Para>08 ENEMY OF THE PEOPLE</Para><Para>By Schaubühne Berlin</Para><Para>This is the third production of Henrik Ibsen's 1882 play to be staged in Singapore in four years. But even if you've watched Nine Years Theatre and W!ld Rice's versions, you should still see this one. Director Thomas Ostermeier is one of the most celebrated helmers in the world. And his version is a gritty, take-no-prisoners, shout-to-the-rooftops celebration of one man's struggle against the system. Performed in German with surtitles.</Para><Para>May 11 &amp; 12, Esplanade Theatre</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Helmi Yusof , Arts Fest Shifts Course </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">French circus act Cirque Rouages tells a story of love and loss while walking the tightrope. </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

