<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180324ee3p002jp" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName><FolderName id="302210924" rl="100">MAS News</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002jp</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002jp" fid="an"/><Num value="1837" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="27"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Invest</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Finding the right financial adviser</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Picking a suitable one that you can trust and have confidence in could be the biggest investment</Para><Para>For many retail investors, finding the right financial advisory representative (FA rep) whom you can trust and have confidence in is essential.</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Lorna Tan </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="co"><Code value="masing"/></CSet><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002jp</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002jp" fid="an"/><Num value="1837" fid="wc"/><Num value="9494" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="md"/><Time value="234515" fid="upt"/><Time value="234515" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId276477861"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashC92EF578E3B4EE28"/><Code value="FSPTHINGFINDER"/><Code value="FSP2YESCO"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORG"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NONS"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="co"><Code value="masing"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Monetary Authority of Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="thingfinder" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="ptf--aboutCo-00004107-20180322-231424.dictionary"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Invest</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Finding the right financial adviser</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Picking a suitable one that you can trust and have confidence in could be the biggest investment</Para><Para>For many retail investors, finding the right financial advisory representative (FA rep) whom you can trust and have confidence in is essential.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>This is why the Government is constantly working to enhance transparency and upgrade the professionalism of the FA industry.</Para><Para>For instance, the Balanced Scorecard Framework, implemented in 2016, requires reps to meet key performance indicators that are not related to sales. These include providing suitable product recommendations and making proper information disclosure to customers.</Para><Para>Recently, the Monetary Authority of Singapore (MAS) proposed measures to address the risks associated with the large-scale movement of reps from one FA firm to another. The measures are meant to safeguard the interests of consumers by promoting more responsible recruitment practices in the FA industry.</Para><Para>Last September, about 300 reps from Great Eastern jumped ship to join rival AIA's financial advisory arm, AIA Financial Advisers. It was one of the biggest migrations in recent years, sparking calls for rules to curb such poaching.</Para><Para>The MAS noted that the mass recruitment of reps by FA firms from competitors was accompanied by sizeable sign-on incentives.</Para><Para>"A large part of these incentives is usually paid upfront and tied to sales targets that these representatives must meet. Such recruitment practices increase the risk of FA representatives engaging in aggressive sales tactics in order to meet the sales targets and retain their sign-on incentives," states the MAS.</Para><Para>It's of utmost importance to do some background checks on the financial adviser and the firms before trusting them with your hard-earned wealth.</Para><Para>One of the proposals recommends that the first-year sales target tied to sign-on incentives should not be higher than the rep's average annual sales in the preceding three years, and that it would be subject to supervisory review by the MAS.</Para><Para>The Sunday Times highlights what to look out for in an FA rep.</Para><Para>Types of FA reps</Para><Para>Your FA rep must inform you about which firm he represents and the products and services that he is authorised to sell.</Para><Para>If he is a rep of a life insurance firm, he can advise you on only that firm's products, which is why he is typically referred to as a tied agent. He may advise you on the products of other FA firms only if the insurer that he represents has agreed to distribute those products.</Para><Para>HSBC's Mr Deepak Khanna suggests checking the rep's track record and his firm's history on ethics and customer centricity.</Para><Para>Similarly, a rep of a bank or other financial institution (typically known as relationship managers) can advise you on only the products of the insurers that his institution has agreed to distribute.</Para><Para>Mr Deepak Khanna, head of wealth development at HSBC Bank (Singapore), says relationship managers can also advise on a range of products offered by the bank, such as investment products, collective investment schemes or insurance policies.</Para><Para>On the other hand, reps from "independent financial adviser" (IFA) firms can provide and advise you on the products of at least four life insurance firms. He should show that he does not have financial or commercial links with these insurers that could influence his recommendations to you.</Para><Para>Ms Wong Sze Keed, chief distribution officer of AIA Singapore, notes that there are online platforms that may be suitable for the financially savvy who are largely confident of their ability to manage their own wealth. But using such platforms means forgoing the personal, professional attention to tailor your portfolio to your unique needs and goals.</Para><Para>Robo-advisers which offer lower investing costs have emerged here, typically providing automated, algorithm-driven financial planning services with little or no human supervision.</Para><Para>Suitability of the FA channels</Para><Para>Mr Brandon Lam, Singapore head of financial planning group at DBS Bank, advises that the suitability of the channels depends on the specific needs of customers, who have different goals and expectations. It is also dependent on both the knowledge level and the types of instruments or products that customers are keen on purchasing.</Para><Para>AIA Singapore's Ms Wong Sze Keed says it is important to feel comfortable with the adviser, his expertise, professionalism and integrity.</Para><Para>"For example, if the customer has the necessary knowledge to invest in equities and other exchange-listed securities, he could use an online trading platform to execute his trades. This channel is also more suitable for customers who already know specifically what is needed or suitable for them to achieve their investment objectives," says Mr Lam.</Para><Para>"For customers who are less experienced or prefer a professional to manage their investments and other financial planning needs, channels that provide advisory services like IFA, insurance agents and bankers would be better suited to the needs of such customers."</Para><Para>This approach ensures that the overall financial planning needs of the customers are adequately addressed and solutions are suited to customers based on their preferences and financial objective.</Para><Para>Notwithstanding the multiple channels that provide financial advice, Mr Lam emphasises that it is important for investors to first build the foundations of their personal financial and investment literacy.</Para><Para>With this, they can critically review and distil advice from across different channels to arrive at an informed investment decision.</Para><Para>"Investors should take a holistic view towards financial advice that covers the bases from budgeting, setting financial and then investment goals, understanding one's risk appetite, developing an understanding of the various product classes and instruments, and determining the suitability of a product before executing a trade," he said.</Para><Para>This approach provides grounding to the plethora of advice one can easily access across multiple mediums these days.</Para><Para>DBS' Mr Brandon Lam says investors must build the foundations of their personal financial literacy before seeking guidance.</Para><Para>Mr Lam says: "Otherwise, investors would only be engaging with financial advice at a transactional level instead of taking a long-term wealth-building perspective. Investors should first seek to be empowered through financial literacy before seeking guidance from trusted wealth partners to make informed investment decisions."</Para><Para>DBS' NAV Hub, which opened last year, is a no-sales financial planning centre for people who are interested in getting financial planning advice with no products being sold.</Para><Para>The one-to-one appointment covers an assessment of their current financial health, finding out about their goals and understanding the gaps to their goals. The session also covers the list of financial planning solutions that are available to them to close the gaps, says DBS.</Para><Para>Selecting a financial adviser</Para><Para>To be a qualified financial adviser in Singapore, stringent criteria have to be met.</Para><Para>"A financial adviser must pass regulatory examinations covering financial advisory ethics, financial market rules and regulations, investment analysis and product knowledge before they are allowed to provide financial advice," says Ms Chung Shaw Bee, UOB's head of deposits and wealth management for Singapore and the region.</Para><Para>"In addition, they have to complete 'continuing professional development' of 30 hours each year to maintain their licence. This keeps the adviser updated on rules and regulations, financial advisory practices and developments in financial market instruments."</Para><Para>Providend's Mr Christopher Tan says a rep should have deep knowledge, empathy and the support of a team of specialists.</Para><Para>Financial experts say a good financial adviser is someone who focuses on understanding the customer's needs first, and then recommends solutions that can fulfil those needs.</Para><Para>Mr Khanna says: "Financial advisers offer advice about investment products such as shares, unit trusts, bonds, insurance among others, taking the investor's goals, risk profile and time horizon into account. In most cases, financial advisers can help monitor the investments and advise you to adjust them when needed."</Para><Para>Here are eight key considerations:</Para><Para>1. HOW MUCH GUIDANCE OR FINANCIAL ADVICE IS NEEDED</Para><Para>Do you make your own decisions regarding financial matters or do you need guidance? Are you willing to pay for professional advice? And do you need just an online platform for trade execution or a full suite of financial planning?</Para><Para>2. RANGE OF SOLUTIONS</Para><Para>It's always good to check the range of services offered by the employer of the rep. Is the rep authorised to advise on products or range of solutions that you are looking at? In addition, check what the support functions working along with the financial adviser are - such as product specialists and service managers - and how frequently the financial adviser reviews the investment portfolio.</Para><Para>3. CREDENTIALS</Para><Para>Find out what credentials - certifications, years of experience or regulatory licences - the rep has.</Para><Para>4. TRUST AND CREDIBILITY</Para><Para>Mr Christopher Tan, chief executive of Providend, suggests looking for a rep who has deep knowledge in financial advisory, has maturity, possesses empathy and is supported by a team of specialists.</Para><Para>UOB's Ms Chung Shaw Bee says reps must pass regulatory exams as well as stay updated on developments in financial market instruments.</Para><Para>"This person should have an ability to communicate simply and he should be someone you feel you can have a long-term relationship with," he adds.</Para><Para>Ms Wong says that on the individual level, the most important factor is whether you feel comfortable with your adviser in terms of his expertise, professionalism and integrity.</Para><Para>"For example, having the Million Dollar Round Table qualification is a strong sign that your adviser is competent, ethical and passionate about helping his clients with their financial needs," she adds.</Para><Para>Mr Khanna suggests looking at the history of the firm and its stability, as well as the level of ethics and customer centricity.</Para><Para>5. HOW IS THE REP REMUNERATED?</Para><Para>It is prudent to consider how the financial adviser's pay structure (commission/fee-based) is determined, how the charges are determined for the services and how much those would be.</Para><Para>6. TRACK RECORD</Para><Para>Though it might not be easy to get a standardised track record because reps' services vary client by client based on invested assets, net worth, income, needs, risk profile, investment horizon and so on, it is advisable to get some information through reference checks from clients who are being served by the same financial adviser. It is of utmost importance to do some background checks on the financial adviser and the firms before trusting them with your hard-earned wealth. After all, your biggest investment could be choosing the right type of adviser, says Mr Khanna.</Para><Para>7. BASIS FOR RECOMMENDATION</Para><Para>FA reps must have a reasonable basis for any recommendation made on any investment product, which includes life insurance policies or accident and health policies.</Para><Para>They must understand and analyse your objectives, financial situation and unique needs before making a recommendation that suits your needs and circumstances.</Para><Para>8. INFORMATION DISCLOSURE</Para><Para>FA reps must disclose to customers material information on a product, especially the potential risks and benefits, and all fees and charges.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Lorna Tan </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Last September, about 300 reps from Great Eastern jumped ship to join rival AIA's financial advisory arm, AIA Financial Advisers. </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

