<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180321ee3m0042n" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210835" rl="100">FNA ASEAN Finance</FolderName><FolderName id="302210865" rl="100">FNA Asian Finance</FolderName><FolderName id="302210894" rl="100">FNA Singapore Finance</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180321ee3m0042n</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180321ee3m0042n" fid="an"/><Num value="1431" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="23"/><S value="55"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Opinion</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Rising insurance claims, healthcare costs - don't blame doctors unfairly</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Doctors face rising costs, and are hemmed in by insurers' practices. Yet they try their best to act in patients' interests</Para><Para>The public discussion on rising insurance claims and healthcare costs is striking for its lack of balance. A follower ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Tan Chi Chiu For The Straits Times </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="co"><Code value="qvhqhg"/></CSet><CSet fid="in"><Code value="i95107"/><Code value="i8200301"/><Code value="i82"/><Code value="i82003"/><Code value="i951"/><Code value="ifinal"/><Code value="iphhp"/></CSet><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180321ee3m0042n</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180321ee3m0042n" fid="an"/><Num value="1431" fid="wc"/><Num value="7356" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180321" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180321" fid="md"/><Time value="234525" fid="upt"/><Time value="234525" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId275278124"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash105546D5EF58D952"/><Code value="FSPTHINGFINDER"/><Code value="FSP2YESCO"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORG"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORGOC"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATIN"/><Code value="FSP2YESIN"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCIN"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NONS"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC648013"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="co"><Code value="qvhqhg"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore Medical Council</CodeD><CodeI org="thingfinder" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="ptf--aboutCo-00004105-20180320-231155.dictionary"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="in"><Code value="i95107"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Hospital Care</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishIN_en_20180316140637"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="162"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="i8200301"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Health/Medical Insurance</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="648013"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018569-20180321-145544"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="3"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="i82"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Insurance</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="in:i8200301"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="i82003"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Non-life Insurance</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="in:i8200301"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="i951"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Health Care/Life Sciences</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="in:i95107"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ifinal"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Financial Services</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="in:i8200301"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="iphhp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Healthcare Provision</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="in:i95107"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018569-20180321-145544"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Opinion</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Rising insurance claims, healthcare costs - don't blame doctors unfairly</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Doctors face rising costs, and are hemmed in by insurers' practices. Yet they try their best to act in patients' interests</Para><Para>The public discussion on rising insurance claims and healthcare costs is striking for its lack of balance. A follower of the issue might be led to believe that doctors are, as a whole, chiefly to blame for everything. It is time to recast the discussion in a fairer light.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Let's dispense with what should be obvious: First, that doctors do play a major role in managing healthcare costs through advising patients on appropriate management as well as charging reasonable fees. Second, that there are miscreants in every sector of society, but a few bad hats should not tarthe vast majority of doctors who act decently.</Para><Para>The Singapore Medical Council's recent advisory to doctors to mind their ethical obligations to help contain healthcare costs states very frankly that "the SMC acknowledges that there are various drivers of healthcare costs, many of which are beyond the control of doctors".</Para><Para>This is salutary as these other drivers have been conveniently ignored in recent public discourse in favour of an easier target - doctors.</Para><Para>First, the cost of running a medical practice has burgeoned over a couple of decades with a generational inequity in that doctors who started 25 years ago can charge lower rates today than young doctors who are competing in the same current market. Are the young doctors "overcharging" when their cost base is so different?</Para><Para>Second, there is a deafening silence on the role of other major drivers such as hospital fees, laboratory and imaging services, pharmaceuticals and medical devices. In most private hospital bills, doctors' fees are the smallest component, yet are somehow deemed the main driver. Many examples bandied about in the mediaquote hospital bill sizes, but often fail to dissect them to see which components predominate.</Para><Para>Third, the milieu of medical practice has changed. There are many advances proven to improve diagnosis and treatment that are demanded by patients. Doctors offer them although they are more expensive, to give patients greater certainty and avoid the liability of wrong diagnoses and unsatisfactory outcomes.</Para><Para>The purported problem of patients being admitted as inpatients for treatment when day ward or outpatient treatment would do is also somewhat self-inflicted by insurers, says the writer, as many insurers continue to demand prolonged day ward or inpatient admission before paying, ironically, a higher price. ST FILE PHOTO</Para><Para>A recent Court of Appeal case also makes it likely that doctors will become more wary of exercising clinical judgments in favour of testing for greater certainty. The case applied a modified Montgomery test - named after a British case - and assessed a doctor's advice primarily from the patients' point of view as to what they would want to know, and not that of the doctors or their peers as to how much information would be deemed sufficient.</Para><Para>Fourth, insurers themselves have scored "own goals" from which they are now trying to extricate themselves. The Straits Times' senior health correspondent Salma Khalik is right that in the insurers' race for greater market share, they scuttled co-payments as a consumption control measure and also offered "as charged" plans that have no upper limits of claims.</Para><Para>Critics have said that holders of such policies made higher claims, as evidence of a "buffet syndrome". There is certainly an element of truth in this. However there are other explanations too, such as that buyers of such riders may be more concerned about their health and are quicker to investigate emergent symptoms or take up appropriate preventative measures. While it is clearly wrong for doctors to service patients with no clinical indications, there is scant evidence that such policyholders consumed services with no justification whatsoever. Medical consumption by patients is a complex issue. While there will be a few doctors who take advantage of such riders to push unnecessary tests, there is no evidence that this is the norm.</Para><Para>INSURERS' PRACTICES</Para><Para>The purported problem of patients being admitted as inpatients for treatment when day ward or outpatient treatment would do is also somewhat self-inflicted by insurers. Many policies are lagging behind the times. Despite more tests and treatments being done as outpatient or day cases, thus saving costs, many insurers continue to demand prolonged day ward or inpatient admission before paying, ironically, a higher price.</Para><Para>It is no surprise that patients demand to be admitted. If doctors accede, are they respecting patient autonomy and acting in patients' best interests (correctly as defined by patients), or are they unethically colluding with patients to defraud insurers?</Para><Para>What about referring inpatients to other doctors when these consultations and treatments could be done later as outpatients? The principal doctor doesn't gain from this. But if patients demand it and there are clinical indications, should doctors respect patient autonomy or refuse in defence of insurers?</Para><Para>There are also liability issues. Take, for example, a patient who is hospitalised for a slipped disc. If he complains of blurred vision and requests an ophthalmologist, should the primary doctor refuse on the grounds that he should wait to make an outpatient appointment? And if it turned out to be glaucoma and a delay led to loss of vision, who would be liable?</Para><Para>Dispensing with the obvious abuses, such as outpatient cosmetic procedures done during otherwise legitimate hospitalisations, there are many other scenarios, many of which are touted in public discussion as abuses without in-depth analysis, that actually lend themselves to reasonable interpretations. Labelling such referrals as "fraudulent" is too convenient and simplistic. Also, why should doctors be asked to police the contracts that patients have with insurers?</Para><Para>Finally, there seems to be an attempt to pressure doctors to modify their code of ethics from acting always in patients' best interests, to "acting in patients' best interests only when insurers' interests are first satisfied".</Para><Para>Traditionally, doctors have professional relationships only with patients and it should remain this way so that professional independence is not violated to the detriment of patients. One of the Health Insurance Task Force's recommendations is that they have avenues to report doctors to the authorities for action should they disagree with the doctors' management or their fees.</Para><Para>This must be seen for what it is: An unacceptable attempt to weaponise a system originally designed to allow patients to seek legitimate redress, to become a tool to cow doctors into acquiescing to insurers' preferences. It would be a grave mistake to allow this channel of aggressive complaints from a novel source, an increasingly muscular third party removed from the professional relationship doctors have with patients, whose interests are mainly financial.</Para><Para>We must be in no doubt: Of the many drivers of medical costs, only the medical profession has a code of ethics that requires doctors to always act in patients' best interests and, by and large, doctors do so, as the SMC's advisory properly admits. Other parties prioritise profits.</Para><Para>Who society should trust more is very obvious, despite publicity designed to try to turn public opinion on its head.</Para><Para>All this said, the decision by the Ministry of Health to re-introduce co-payments into healthcare insurance as well as creating benchmarks for medical pricing are good moves to rectify anomalies caused by reckless insurance policies and an inefficient and unregulated market.</Para><Para>But because the variables that dictate patients' health-seeking behaviour and the pricing of medical services are very complex, due care must be taken to ensure that such moves are not seen as merely protective of the insurance industry but are carefully thought out, rational and fair to all.</Para><Para>The factors that drive healthcare costs in any society are protean. No doubt doctors have an important role to play, but it is unjust to ask them to undertake more than their fair share of responsibility.</Para><Para>Other, much more influential stakeholders must be simultaneously engaged so that in concert, the entire healthcare industry can ensure that healthcare remains affordable.</Para><Para>• Dr Tan Chi Chiu is a gastroenterologist in private practice. He was formally an elected member of 18 years of the Singapore Medical Council and continues to be chairman of its Medical Ethics Committee.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Tan Chi Chiu For The Straits Times </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">The purported problem of patients being admitted as inpatients for treatment when day ward or outpatient treatment would do is also somewhat self-inflicted by insurers, says the writer, as many insurers continue to demand prolonged day ward or inpatient admission before paying, ironically, a higher price. </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

