<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180324ee3p002lm" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002lm</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002lm" fid="an"/><Num value="853" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="30"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Insight</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">#OpinionOfTheDay; Lessons from an empty desk</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>My colleagues are convinced that I am a minimalist.</Para><Para>For the longest time, my desk was as spartan as it could get. All I had was a hand-me-down Ikea lamp from the former occupant, and a pinned-up note from a friend reminding me that "the ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Toh Wen Li </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002lm</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002lm" fid="an"/><Num value="853" fid="wc"/><Num value="3676" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="md"/><Time value="234520" fid="upt"/><Time value="234520" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId276477861"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash638BE53F56067112"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NONS"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Insight</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">#OpinionOfTheDay; Lessons from an empty desk</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>My colleagues are convinced that I am a minimalist.</Para><Para>For the longest time, my desk was as spartan as it could get. All I had was a hand-me-down Ikea lamp from the former occupant, and a pinned-up note from a friend reminding me that "the sincerity of an attachment is commensurate with its cost in pain".</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>People used to leave parcels and letters for me at my table and wonder if they would ever reach me, because it seemed like I'd already moved away. Co-workers joked that it was a sign I didn't plan on staying long in my current role.</Para><Para>Why do I like having an empty desk? Let me count the ways: First, you can be sure that you'll always find what you are looking for. Second, cockroaches are less likely to make your desk their home. Third, according to some self-help gurus, a tidy office means a tidy mind.</Para><Para>What isn't so obvious is the monster of perfectionism that lurks behind the lack of photos and memorabilia. Every object has a kind of totemic significance and proclaims its usefulness in relation to the rest. Introduce something new, and the harmony is broken.</Para><Para>For that same reason, I dislike shopping because it takes me forever to find something that looks just right. The quest for a new outfit often involves a series of swift, fell strokes as I march in and out of retail stores, disappointed that I couldn't find anything that looked good on me.</Para><Para>In my early days co-editing a section of my campus newspaper, I thought the best way to spruce up one writer's lacklustre piece would be to replace everything with something more concise. The end product, as you might expect, sounded very different from the original. I e-mailed the edited version to the writer only to receive the terse reply: Either publish it in my name rather than hers, or don't think about running it at all.</Para><Para>When the time finally came to leave university, like a person on a rocky boat who must throw out the heavy jewellery or risk sinking, I parted with all my books save the ones I cared about most. Mediaeval tomes like The Riverside Chaucer and The Vision Of Piers Plowman were the first to go.</Para><Para>A week before returning to Singapore from Britain, I lugged around bags filled with more books I didn't plan on keeping. One of these was Marie Kondo's The Life-Changing Magic Of Tidying Up, which I sold at a flea market - while giving thanks, of course, for the joy it had sparked.</Para><Para>The thing about "minimalism", or whatever label you want to give it, is that it is peculiarly susceptible to turning into an obsession in itself.</Para><Para>This is a view shared by J.P. Delaney, the author of psychological thriller The Girl Before, which takes place in an austere one-bedroom dwelling.</Para><Para>"One story I heard about several different minimalist architects is that the people who live with them say their houses are often empty simply because they can't make a decision," he told Dezeen magazine last year.</Para><Para>"The architect looks at the sofa and says, 'really we shouldn't have a sofa, we should have two chairs', but can't decide between ones by Piero Lissoni or by Le Corbusier. He is unable to make a decision. So they end up with nothing."</Para><Para>A misplaced striving for perfectionism can easily backfire.</Para><Para>A Singaporean artist told me the other day that she knew a famous potter who had a habit of smashing all the works from the kiln that didn't meet his expectations. He did this for a decade, before realising that he had deprived himself of 10 years' worth of information.</Para><Para>An uncluttered table doesn't necessarily reflect a calm mind. And an all-or-nothing approach to the world is a risky way to live - think of all the happy accidents you might be missing out on.</Para><Para>Kondo says in her book that she knows many people who feel the urge to tidy their rooms before an exam, when they should be revising instead.</Para><Para>Clearly, it's easier to fix a physical mess than a mental one. And even while doing the former, the act of compartmentalising often only gives one the illusion of control. My desk looks neat enough, but its drawers are chock-a-block with old notebooks, folders and dog-eared press releases.</Para><Para>Minimalism, I've come to realise, is not a process of elimination but a state of mind.</Para><Para>Maybe it's time I learnt to take things on their own terms, to accept the messiness and bagginess of reality rather than panning its slipstreams for imaginary nuggets of gold. The 3am first drafts, the "failed" friendships and romances - these are the scaffoldings we build our lives on.</Para><Para>* #opinionoftheday is a column for younger writers in the newsroom to write about issues that matter to them and their peers.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Toh Wen Li </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

