<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180324ee3p002l4" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002l4</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002l4" fid="an"/><Num value="2102" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Cornish charms</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Cornwall was not associated with good food, but that is changing, with award-winning chefs creating unbeatable cuisine with produce from the area</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Lydia Vasko </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="uk"/><Code value="eland"/><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="eecz"/><Code value="eurz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/><Code value="weurz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"/><Code value="gtour"/><Code value="gcat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002l4</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002l4" fid="an"/><Num value="2102" fid="wc"/><Num value="9933" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="md"/><Time value="234519" fid="upt"/><Time value="234519" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId276477861"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashB475C37A23009A73"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC624992"/><Code value="FSPRBC734618"/><Code value="FSPRBC847446"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="uk"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United Kingdom</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="168"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="624992"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:eland"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="eland"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">England</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="156"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="3"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="eecz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">European Union Countries</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:uk"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:eland"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="eurz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Europe</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:uk"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:eland"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="weurz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Western Europe</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:uk"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:eland"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Living/Lifestyle</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="847446"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gtour"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gtour"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Travel</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="734618"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:glife"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gtour"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Cornish charms</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Cornwall was not associated with good food, but that is changing, with award-winning chefs creating unbeatable cuisine with produce from the area</Para><Para>Cornwall's windswept cliffs, charming fishing villages and scenic shores have long been a favourite destination for Britons looking for a holiday close to home.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Hundreds of white and golden sand beaches that unfurl into turquoise waves along the coast, and seaside resort towns such as St Ives have been enticing visitors with fresh air and spectacular vistas since the Victorian times.</Para><Para>Admittedly, the thrill of the hot Mediterranean sun has distracted British holiday-makers for a few decades now, but even the most well-heeled are returning and falling in love with Cornwall again, thanks, rather unexpectedly, to its food.</Para><Para>Less than a decade ago, Cornish cuisine brought to mind little more than clotted cream and pasties.</Para><Para>Delicious classics, sure, but not terribly exciting and certainly not something worth travelling to the farthest reaches of Britain for.</Para><Para>With its rugged coast and mist-shrouded moors, there is something mysterious about this land, even when it is bathed in sunlight, which is fitting, since it is home to the legends of Arthur and the famed castle Tintagel.</Para><Para>A rocky peninsula jutting out into the Atlantic Ocean, almost completely separated from England by the River Tamar, Cornwall feels more closely attuned to the wild surf breaks of north-western Spain than the red sandy cliffs of neighbouring Devon.</Para><Para>*</Para><Para>GETTING THERE</Para><Para>*</Para><Para>British Airways and Singapore Airlines fly direct from Singapore to London daily, while Norwegian Air and Qantas fly direct four times a week. From London, drive or take the train to Cornwall. The trip takes about five hours from London to the heart of Cornwall along the M4 motorway or from London's Paddington station with the Great Western Railway (<ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.gwr.com">www.gwr.com</ELink>).</Para><Para>Perhaps this is why it stayed off the foodie radar for so long.</Para><Para>Or perhaps the notoriously independent Cornish - an ethnic minority with Celtic roots, like the Welsh and the Bretons - were keeping the secret to themselves.</Para><Para>But the world has caught on to Cornwall's potential for culinary excellence.</Para><Para>Talented locals and award-winning chefs are churning out unbeatable produce, from cheese to wine to heirloom vegetables, some of which are not found anywhere else in the country.</Para><Para>Much of Cornwall's bounty is due to its unique geographical location. Surrounded by the ocean on both coasts, it is enveloped by the warmth of the gulf stream.</Para><Para>This creates a mild climate and relatively warm winters, which allow farmers to grow a variety of crops year round.</Para><Para>The gulf stream also keeps the Celtic Sea and English Channel well stocked with dozens of species of fish such as sardines, monkfish and Cornish sole, and a steady supply of rain keeps the meadows lush and green so the resident cattle, sheep and pigs are well fed, ideal for succulent meat and rich, creamy milk.</Para><Para>When I rove around the countryside for a week in autumn, fields which might have been barren or ripe for the harvest elsewhere are still lush with growing fruit and vegetables.</Para><Para>The dynamic landscape of hills, coves and valleys along the peninsula provides unique micro-climates where flora, unable to grow anywhere else in Britain, is thriving.</Para><Para>I visit Tregothnan (tregothnan.co.uk), a 1,000ha living and working private Cornish estate which has been owned by the Boscawen family since 1334.</Para><Para>It has the largest historic botanic garden in Cornwall, thanks to family ancestors who brought rare trees, rhododendrons and manuka trees here 200 years ago.</Para><Para>Many are still thriving though they are thousands of kilometres away from the tropical climes they used to call home.</Para><Para>The gardens are spectacular, rambling stretches of forests, manicured flower beds and wild-looking glens I could happily explore for days. But I am here to see the tea - yes, tea - 60ha of which is grown on the eastern side of the imposing family home.</Para><Para>Because here, where a deep sea creek runs through the estate 12km from the southern coast, are conditions which are similar to the climate of Darjeeling, India, or so I'm told by Jonathan Jones, the estate botanist, who is all too excited to claim the tea as England's own.</Para><Para>But it sort of is. Tregothnan is Britain's first and only tea estate, and has been successfully producing tea since 2005.</Para><Para>Across the peninsula, the family-run Camel Valley Vineyard (<ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.camelvalley.com">www.camelvalley.com</ELink>) produced its first vintage in 1992 and has been winning international awards for its sparkling white and rose wines since 2005.</Para><Para>Grown on cool but sunny slopes in Camel Valley, the vines grow and flower early and the grapes grow slowly, allowing them time to develop luscious flavour.</Para><Para>Fermented and bottled using the same process as champagne, the Camel Valley Sparkling Pinot Noir has won accolades, including the gold medal in the Decanter World Wine Awards in 2009, and is on the wine list of top restaurants such as Hakkasan in London. Queen Elizabeth served the Camel Valley sparkling rose to the King of Spain; and Camilla, Duchess of Cornwall, served it at her 70th birthday party.</Para><Para>But much of this was a blip on the radar when Nathan Outlaw, one of the country's best chefs, decided to set up shop on the far Cornish coast in 2007.</Para><Para>Serving a stylised tasting menu of sustainably caught seafood, the catch delivered straight from the ocean to the kitchen each day, Restaurant Nathan Outlaw (nathan-outlaw.com/restaurant-nathan-outlaw) soon earned two Michelin stars and, this year, it was named the best restaurant in the UK by Good Food Guide 2018.</Para><Para>Not bad for a restaurant in Port Isaac, an unassuming clifftop fishing village on the northern coast.</Para><Para>Outlaw's move to Cornwall, as a Michelin-starred chef, was a watershed moment for the county, says author and Cornish food expert Ruth Huxley, though it was arguably one of Outlaw's mentors, famed television presenter, chef and restaurateur Rick Stein, who started to turn the culinary tide.</Para><Para>Stein opened his first restaurant, The Seafood Restaurant (<ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.rick">www.rick</ELink> stein.com), in 1975 in the fishing port of Padstow, just 25km down the coast from Port Isaac.</Para><Para>He has since built an empire of seafood restaurants in Cornwall and around the world, turned homely Padstow into a bustling tourist town and taught people to value the piscine bounty lapping on its shores.</Para><Para>Traditionally, many Cornish people's exposure to fish was limited to grilled sardines and fish and chips.</Para><Para>Then Stein came along and evangelised the deliciousness of other local catch such as plaice, hake and turbot and taught people how to prepare it through his cookbooks, shows and his cooking school (<ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.rickstein.com/school">www.rickstein.com/school</ELink>) in Padstow, where visitors can sign up for regular workshops.</Para><Para>Still, it was Outlaw's arrival in Cornwall which made the culinary world sit up and take notice.</Para><Para>"Opening a top-end restaurant here was unheard of at the time. Twenty years ago, Cornwall was attracting base-level tourism, people coming to eat fish and chips and pasties, but for the past eight years, Cornwall has become a real upmarket destination," says Huxley, the organiser of the annual Great Cornish Food Festival and owner of the Great Cornish Food Store (<ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.greatcornish">www.greatcornish</ELink> food.co.uk), an independent grocer and cafe in Truro which stocks 2,000 Cornish products.</Para><Para>"Everything, from produce to restaurants to accommodation is moving up in quality. Chefs and tourism are raising the bar together. Now everyone wants Cornish produce. It means quality," she says.</Para><Para>In the past 10 years, other chefs and Michelin stars have followed. Driftwood (<ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.driftwoodhotel.co.uk">www.driftwoodhotel.co.uk</ELink>), at the luxury Driftwood Hotel in picturesque seaside Portscatho, and Paul Ainsworth at No. 6 (<ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.paul-ainsworth.co.uk/number6">www.paul-ainsworth.co.uk/number6</ELink>), serving modern British food in a Georgian townhouse in Padstow, each have a Michelin star.</Para><Para>In the spring of 2016, British chef April Bloomfield, who holds Michelin stars at New York gastropubs The Spotted Pig and The Breslin, joined forces with top London chef Tom Adams of acclaimed barbecue restaurant Pitt Cue to open the 26ha Coombeshead Farm (www. coombesheadfarm.co.uk) in the Cornwall countryside.</Para><Para>The chefs are growing their own produce and heritage game, as well as pickling, curing and baking on the property, where a five-bed guesthouse with simple but beautiful rooms also serves a farm-fresh feast for dinner from Thursday to Sunday each week.</Para><Para>Top restaurants in London are clamouring for Cornish products too. Sales for pilchards have skyrocketed since they were cleverly marketed as Cornish sardines in 2009, and the organic vegetables, fruit and edible flowers grown on Crocadon Farm (crocadon.co.uk) near the River Tamar are sold to some of the best restaurants in Britain, including Alain Ducasse at the Dorchester, The Fat Duck, Gordon Ramsay's Maze Grill Royal Hospital Road and The Ritz Hotel, London.</Para><Para>Musician-turned-farmer Sean O'Neill cultivates 660 products and is continually experimenting with unique varietals such as purple flowering choy sum, three-cornered leek, rocket flower and, his favourite, anise hyssop.</Para><Para>"We are not in the business of growing mediocre things," he says, pulling a beetroot out of the ground and slicing it open as he talks, revealing its stunningly beautiful golden yellow heart.</Para><Para>As we move among rows of fragrant fennel and brightly coloured carrots and kale, he stops every few metres to pull vibrant gems out of the ground and we nibble them like rabbits, each bite crisp and bursting with flavour.</Para><Para>O'Neill describes how every item, whether fruit or flower, is hand-picked at its ripest and grown with the utmost care, and it shows.</Para><Para>I understand why chefs and customers alike would pay top dollar for the produce.</Para><Para>Fortunately, the land O'Neill is farming is owned by the Coryton family, who also owns Pentillie Castle (<ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.pentillie.co.uk">www.pentillie.co.uk</ELink>), a luxury bed and breakfast in the centre of an 800ha estate on the bank of the River Tamar, where I am staying the night.</Para><Para>Many bed and breakfasts will include the additional option of dinner if booked in advance and I am treated to a hearty meal of Cornish lamb served with beetroot, potato and a warm seasonal salad, which are straight from O'Neill's fields, and a cocktail made with Aval Dor, a Cornish potato vodka.</Para><Para>I'm pleased to find that because there is so much excellent produce available, one does not have to book months in advance or go to a Michelin-starred restaurant to eat very, very well.</Para><Para>A few nights later, I have dinner at The Vean, a quiet bed and breakfast in a gorgeously restored Georgian country house overlooking the grounds of Caerhays Castle (<ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.caerhays.co.uk">www.caerhays.co.uk</ELink>).</Para><Para>Deputy manager and chef Nicola Jones whips up a humble but tantalisingly moreish menu of Scotch eggs, quail eggs wrapped in ground pork; a delicate Cornish crab crostini; the most tender fillet steak - from cows reared a few paddocks away on the Caerhays grounds - served with chard, parsnips and carrots; and an apple frangipane tart with pears poached in berry mead.</Para><Para>The meal is simply prepared, ingredients so fresh that they hardly needed any seasoning at all.</Para><Para>Much of the produce comes from the Lost Gardens of Heligan (heligan.com), one of the most beautiful and popular gardens in the UK, visited by more than 300,000 people each year.</Para><Para>It has a productive garden growing more than 300 types of fruit and vegetables, many of them heritage varieties, which are rarely, if ever, found in stores. These include the Blackmoor red apple, edulis berries and turk's turban squash.</Para><Para>But you can tuck into some of them at the garden's cafe, where a menu of seasonal Cornish delights is splayed like a tiered altar of food - fresh salads, soups and savoury pies made from ingredients grown and raised at Heligan.</Para><Para>I grab a Cornish apple cider and savour one of the best beef pies I've ever had, the meat juicy and deliciously pink in the centre.</Para><Para>As I dig in, I realise that finding good food here is as natural as the beauty of the landscape. From Michelin-starred eatery to corner cafe, it is farm to table without the fuss.</Para><Para>• The writer's trip was sponsored by Visit Britain (<ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.visitbritain.com">www.visitbritain.com</ELink>).</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Lydia Vasko </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">The grass-fed cows (above) of Callestick Farm in Cornwall produce milk with a high fat content, perfect for making Callestick's famous clotted cream ice cream. </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

