<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180327ee3r003ju" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180327ee3r003ju</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180327ee3r003ju" fid="an"/><Num value="997" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180327" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="22"/><S value="59"/><M value="79"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">ST</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Pattern of 'denial and inaction' in tech firms' response to misuse on platforms: US professor tells Select Committee on fake news</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>SINGAPORE - While technology companies may say they actively prevent the spread of inappropriate online content on their platforms, there has been a "pattern of denial and inaction" instead, a United States digital forensics expert has ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Seow Bei Yi </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"/><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="namz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gfake"/><Code value="gcat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180327ee3r003ju</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180327ee3r003ju" fid="an"/><Num value="997" fid="wc"/><Num value="5283" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180327" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180327" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180327" fid="md"/><Time value="140014" fid="upt"/><Time value="140014" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId277499580"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash57D74D9BF47564B4"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORGOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC621478"/><Code value="FSPRBC682661"/><Code value="FSPRBC871293"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="80"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621478"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018591-20180327-075522"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="80"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="682661"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018591-20180327-075522"/><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gfake"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Fake News Phenomenon</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="871293"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018591-20180327-075522"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gfake"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001003-20180326-161854"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">ST</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Pattern of 'denial and inaction' in tech firms' response to misuse on platforms: US professor tells Select Committee on fake news</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>SINGAPORE - While technology companies may say they actively prevent the spread of inappropriate online content on their platforms, there has been a "pattern of denial and inaction" instead, a United States digital forensics expert has argued.</Para><Para>"I reject this idea that they are aggressively going after this content... their actions simply don't support it," Professor Hany Farid of Dartmouth College told the Select Committee on deliberate online falsehoods via video conferencing on Tuesday (March 27).</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>The committee had put to him, for instance, that video-sharing site YouTube said 98 per cent of videos removed for violent extremism are now flagged by algorithms.</Para><Para>But what is the denominator, how does YouTube know what it is missing, he asked.</Para><Para>Many inappropriate videos, for instance videos of extremist groups, can be found online for hours, days or even weeks, said Prof Farid, who is involved in efforts to counter the spread of extreme ideologies online.</Para><Para>The US academic was the first speaker on the sixth day of public hearings held by the committee. Civil society representatives, including activists Kirsten Han and Jolovan Wham, are also scheduled to speak, during the later part of the day.</Para><Para>The committee had earlier heard from representatives of global social media companies including Facebook and Twitter, as well as local media companies Singapore Press Holdings and Mediacorp. Various academics from Singapore and overseas had also appeared before the committee to share their views of what can be done to deal with online falsehoods.</Para><Para>On Tuesday, Prof Farid also pointed to how technology companies had "dragged their feet" when it comes to the problem of child pornography shared online.</Para><Para>In his written submission, he noted that between 2003 and 2008, the United States' Attorney-General called on major US-based tech companies to discuss the spread of child pornography online. But the Technology Coalition that was formed "did not develop or deploy and effective solution" in this period, he added.</Para><Para>It was only in 2008 that things got moving with the development and deployment of a software called PhotoDNA, which is now in worldwide use and has been effective in removing tens of millions of images of child exploitation from online platforms, he wrote.</Para><Para>Prof Farid had a hand in developing this solution, after being approached by Microsoft and the National Centre for Missing and Exploited Children.</Para><Para>Likewise, technology companies have been slow in addressing the online recruitment and radicalisation of extremists across the globe, he noted.</Para><Para>Prof Farid called on technology companies to do more to rein in abuses.</Para><Para>"They put in just enough to stave off the regulatory issues", he argued.</Para><Para>The technology to detect and prevent inappropriate content from spreading exists, he said, noting the success of companies in going after unauthorised uploads of copyright content online.</Para><Para>While technology can help to detect and prevent inappropriate content from spreading online, this will likely still have to be paired with manual review by people, said Prof Farid.</Para><Para>This is because, with its current accuracy rate, allowing programmes to run fully autonomously would be "prohibitive" as it could misidentify illegal content, he said.</Para><Para>Currently, a low error rate, such as one in 100 billion, for illegal photos and videos, has to be allowed to detect material that has been modified, such as in size, he added.</Para><Para>Outlining the difficulty of targeting falsehoods with a similar method, he said also that countries will need to come up with reasonable, transparent definitions of such content.</Para><Para>With modern artificial intelligence systems needing a "phenomenal amount of data" to be trained, adversaries will recognise this as well, changing their tactics accordingly - meaning the challenge to combat falsehoods will be an ongoing one.</Para><Para>Public hearings to fight online falsehoods: Read the submissions here and watch more videos. Related Stories: NLB stepping up critical thinking in fight against fake news Related Story NLB stepping up efforts to arm the public with critical thinking skills in fight against fake news cc.jpg Related Story Human Rights Watch responds to criticisms from Select Committee hearing on its report hzjointtask0327.jpg Related Story Form a joint task force with Malaysia to tackle online falsehoods, suggests entrepreneur Independent, multi-stakeholder body needed to fight online falsehoods Related Story Independent, multi-stakeholder body needed to fight falsehoods: RSIS senior fellow Tech firms have "a pattern of denial and inaction" Related Story Pattern of 'denial and inaction' in tech firms' response to misuse on platforms: US professor tells Select Committee on fake news Legislation against online falsehoods should not endanger the work of journalists Related Story Legislation against online falsehoods should not be so broad that it endangers the work of journalists, says SPH Independent fact-checking council can combat deliberate online falsehoods Related Story Independent fact-checking council can combat deliberate online falsehoods: SPH and CNA Facebook admits it should have told users about policy breach earlier Related Story Facebook admits it should have told users earlier about breach of policy hzmortezashahrezaye0327.jpg Related Story No evidence to show that online falsehoods can change people's political opinions: Expert The role of languages in countering falsehoods Related Story NUS academic sounds warning on falsehoods spread in mother tongues and dialects via closed-group platforms Indonesia to have hoax crisis centres to counter online falsehoods Related Story Hoax crisis centres will be launched to counter falsehoods ahead of Indonesian elections, says founder of anti-hoax network hzukexpert0327.jpg Related Story UK expert says legislation is tricky as it is hard to define fake news, but Shanmugam disagrees Human intervention to counter online falsehoods Related Story Fight against online falsehoods must take place offline too, say experts Singapore can be 'a sandbox for subversion' Related Story Singapore can be 'a sandbox for subversion', warns expert at hearing on deliberate online falsehoods unnamed.png Related Story Baring the truth about 'fake news'</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Seow Bei Yi </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

