<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180328ee3s002uv" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180328ee3s002uv</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180328ee3s002uv" fid="an"/><Num value="1315" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180328" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="23"/><S value="59"/><M value="74"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">ST</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">TOC ex-editor calls for Government to better engage citizen journalists to combat fake news</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>SINGAPORE - The former editor of an online news site urged the Government to better engage citizen journalists, and even consider funding programmes to help them hone their skills.</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Nur Asyiqin Mohamad Salleh </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gfake"/><Code value="gpol"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="gpir"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180328ee3s002uv</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180328ee3s002uv" fid="an"/><Num value="1315" fid="wc"/><Num value="6626" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180328" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180328" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180328" fid="md"/><Time value="123023" fid="upt"/><Time value="123023" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId277926737"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash76989FB6AAA6D883"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC682661"/><Code value="FSPRBC799599"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="682661"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018594-20180328-025140"/><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gfake"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Fake News Phenomenon</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishNS_en_20180322142639"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="100"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gpol"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Domestic Politics</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="799599"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018594-20180328-025140"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gfake"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gpol"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gpir"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Politics/International Relations</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gpol"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">ST</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">TOC ex-editor calls for Government to better engage citizen journalists to combat fake news</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>SINGAPORE - The former editor of an online news site urged the Government to better engage citizen journalists, and even consider funding programmes to help them hone their skills.</Para><Para>Mr Andrew Loh, who co -founded The Online Citizen (TOC) in 2006, said in his written submission to the Select Committee on deliberate online falsehoods that he hoped to see the Government "link arms... with (citizen journalists) who can do better if they had the resources to do so" instead of keeping them at arm's length.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>This, he said, could be an additional weapon in the fight against fake news.</Para><Para>At the public hearing on Wednesday (March 28), he told the committee: "I've always wondered why not the Government engage instead of confront... To combat falsehoods, we need everyone on board - and I agree with that, because we're talking about things like national security, our sovereignty, and our national harmony."</Para><Para>He added: "In order to shield ourselves, to build this resilience, you need everyone on board, and that everyone must include the alternative media."</Para><Para>Acting chairman Seah Kian Peng acknowledged the point, assuring Mr Loh that the committee was seeking a range of views, and looking at a multi-prong approach in dealing with online fabrications.</Para><Para>Mr Loh had noted in his written submission that online content producers are mostly short on resources and amateurs when it comes to news reporting. "We are often unaware of the pitfalls of some of these so-called 'out-of-bound markers', and even basic writing skills".</Para><Para>Online users, not infrequently, run into trouble with the authorities. Often, this is not out of "malicious intent" but owing to their limited resources, he said.</Para><Para>He added: "In my opinion, some of these occasions could have been avoided if these online users were better informed in the law, and trained in the skills of journalism, or simply story-writing."</Para><Para>Mr Loh suggested in his submission that the Government step up engagement with citizen journalists - a move he believes will help improve the online space.</Para><Para>It could even consider setting up a fund to help these content producers boost their writing or journalism skills and encourage people with legal and journalistic know-how to conduct lessons or workshops for the online community, he said.</Para><Para>"If nothing else, such a move would signal to the public that the Government's position is not one of simply meting out punishment and penalties and threats, but also one of going upstream, in effect, in its effort to stamp out fake news by helping to equip information disseminators with better skills," he wrote.</Para><Para>"I do believe in the potential of such initiatives, which could also help change the tone of the current 'us-vs-them' situation we have."</Para><Para>The suggestion of a fund was met with interest by select committee member Edwin Tong, who said it was an idea the committee would consider.</Para><Para>Said Mr Tong at the hearing: "The idea is... to inoculate, to make sure that we build a more resilient society. And I don't think anyone on this committee will disagree with that."</Para><Para>The conciliatory note came after he and Mr Loh tussled for more that 30 minutes over such issues as whether legislation like the Administration of Justice Act is used more heavily against alternative media compared to mainstream media, and trust in the police and traditional media.</Para><Para>They also debated intent, with Mr Loh saying a person would need to have "malicious intentions" to be guilty of propagating online fabrications.</Para><Para>Mr Tong c ountered that harm through such fabrications can be caused intentionally or otherwise, but noted that those who did so intentionally would be dealt with differently from those who did not.</Para><Para>"As a broad concept, you would agree?" he asked.</Para><Para>Mr Loh responded: "I see no reason to disagree here."</Para><Para>Mr Loh in his submission said alternative sites are already willing to engage with the authorities, adding that TOC, as far as he was aware, had never denied or rejected publishing - often in full - letters or clarifications received from the authorities.</Para><Para>An annual dialogue between the authorities and citizen journalists, for instance, could help both sides share their perspectives, he added, noting that such meetings were held after the 2011 general election between new ministers - including labour chief Chan Chun Sing and Speaker of Parliament Tan Chuan-Jin - and members of the public and the online community.</Para><Para>Said Mr Loh: "Having been privileged to have attended some of these occasions, it was a pity to me that they were not continued. The Government should consider re-introducing such meetings, and make them a permanent feature in its engagement plans."</Para><Para>At Wednesday's hearing, he agreed there should be a range of remedies, depending on the degree of culpability of the person involved, but urged the Government to be mindful not to overreach, stifling freedom of expression.</Para><Para>"I've been doing this for more than 10 years online, interacting with these people that you might want to be legislating against," he told the select committee. "From my experience, I can tell you that if you engage, you may have a different outcome - and that outcome may be better than legislation.''</Para><Para>As his hour-long session drew to an end, Mr Loh said citizen journalists at times face roadblocks when they seek out facts, and are then accused of propagating falsehoods.</Para><Para>"I hope the Government will understand we are not troublemakers. I don't hide. I'm not anonymous. When I started TOC in 2006, the very first thing I told my team was we're not going to use pseudonyms... because we are Singaporeans," he said.</Para><Para>Public hearings to fight online falsehoods: Read the submissions here and watch more videos. Related Stories: joandrewedit280318.jpg Related StoryTOC ex-editor calls for Government to better engage citizen journalists to combat fake news nvasu0328_2x.jpg Related StoryMeasures against falsehoods should target only those aimed at undermining society: RSIS senior fellow asdan-2803.jpg Related StoryReal threat is not online falsehood but selective news consumption, says European lawyer New laws should protect victims of online falsehoods Related StorySingaporean bore the brunt of xenophobic comments when his photo was misused online Govt should take down falsehoods to send a strong message Related StoryNetizens can sieve out falsehoods most times, but govt action needed in emergencies: NTU lecturers Online content producers dispute what is defined as truth Related StoryNo need for new laws to counter online falsehoods, activists tell Select Committee Legislation can sometimes backfire Related StoryAcademic Cherian George urges caution in drafting new laws to tackle online untruths, calls for repeal of insult law NLB stepping up critical thinking in fight against fake news Related StoryNLB stepping up efforts to arm the public with critical thinking skills in fight against fake news cc.jpg Related StoryHuman Rights Watch responds to criticisms from Select Committee hearing on its report hzjointtask0327.jpg Related StoryForm a joint task force with Malaysia to tackle online falsehoods, suggests entrepreneur Independent, multi-stakeholder body needed to fight online falsehoods Related StoryIndependent, multi-stakeholder body needed to fight falsehoods: RSIS senior fellow Tech firms have "a pattern of denial and inaction" Related StoryPattern of 'denial and inaction' in tech firms' response to misuse on platforms: US professor tells Select Committee on fake news Legislation against online falsehoods should not endanger the work of journalists Related StoryLegislation against online falsehoods should not be so broad that it endangers the work of journalists, says SPH Independent fact-checking council can combat deliberate online falsehoods Related StoryIndependent fact-checking council can combat deliberate online falsehoods: SPH and CNA Facebook admits it should have told users about policy breach earlier Related StoryFacebook admits it should have told users earlier about breach of policy</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Nur Asyiqin Mohamad Salleh </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

