<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180324ee3p002l1" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002l1</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002l1" fid="an"/><Num value="1068" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Early start on the arts</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>At least six groups here offer arts programmes for kids that range from craftwork to storytelling to immersive spaces for free play, making the arts accessible for all</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Bryna Singh </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"/><Code value="gcat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002l1</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002l1" fid="an"/><Num value="1068" fid="wc"/><Num value="5312" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="md"/><Time value="234519" fid="upt"/><Time value="234519" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId276477861"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashF730913E27CC7FEF"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC847446"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Living/Lifestyle</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="847446"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:glife"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Early start on the arts</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>At least six groups here offer arts programmes for kids that range from craftwork to storytelling to immersive spaces for free play, making the arts accessible for all</Para><Para>Housewife Shirin Taylor, 34, makes weekly trips to children's arts centre The Artground with her two young children, aged three and one.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Her kids love the centre's freeaccess play space, she says.</Para><Para>"They can run about and spend hours role-playing with the installations there. It's great for developing their imagination."</Para><Para>Parents such as Mrs Taylor, who wish to expose their children to the arts from a young age, say they are heartened by the array of options they now have here.</Para><Para>At least six organisations offer a slew of arts programmes for children, several of which have been introduced only in the past two years.</Para><Para>While each company's programme differs in terms of focus and forms of engagement, the various providers have a common goal to make the arts accessible to all families, and desire to spark an interest in the arts among children of all backgrounds and abilities.</Para><Para>Exposure to the arts has a positive effect on children, the organisers say, as the little ones learn how to be creative, solve problems, pick up listening skills as well as have empathy, among other things.</Para><Para>Studies have shown that young children have a large capacity to develop their creativity and grow their imagination through various positive artistic stimulation.</Para><Para>MS SAMANTHA SCOTT-BLACKHALL, programming director of Gateway Theatre, which has a weekly arts programme for kids that includes storytelling and free play</Para><Para>Gateway Theatre, which started in July last year, launched its Kids Club Programmethis month. The weekly arts programme at its complex in Bukit Merah offersactivities such as storytelling, arts and craft, and free play.</Para><Para>Its programming director Samantha Scott-Blackhall says: "Studies have shown that young children have a large capacity to develop their creativity and grow their imagination through various positive artistic stimulation."</Para><Para>Her belief is that through the activities, children will develop a variety of skills, including language appreciation through storytelling, visual appreciation and inventiveness from drawing and craft-making, as well as motor skills and problem-solving during free-play games.</Para><Para>Other arts centres and companies that have dedicated arts initiatives and spaces for children include The Artground at Goodman Arts Centre, which opened in July; Superhero Me, which started in 2014 as an inclusive arts movement by the Lien Foundation before becoming a non-profit arts company last year; Keppel Centre of Art Education at National Gallery Singapore, which kicked off in November 2015; and Playeum at Gillman Barracks, which started in September 2015.</Para><Para>A forerunner in the local children's arts scene is the 16-year-old Esplanade - Theatres on the Bay. One of its earliest initiatives is the annual Octoburst! - A Children's Festival, which started in 2003 and encourages play and family fun with free and ticketed performances, activities and workshops.</Para><Para>Like the Esplanade, The Artground and Keppel Centre of Art Education have ticketed programmes, but also offer free-entry activity spaces that allow children to experience the arts through play.</Para><Para>The Artground's play space features an interactive installation that is a collaboration with an artist. It has had two installations so far, with a third coming up next month.</Para><Para>Director Luanne Poh says a free-access play space means that "all can access the arts without any financial barriers".</Para><Para>Over at Keppel Centre of Art Education, there are four creative learning spaces - two immersive ones for free play and exploration called Art Playscape and Project Gallery, and two learning spaces for experimenting with art-making and art materials. All are open to the public for free.</Para><Para>The creation and design of these spaces, which are changed every 18 to 24 months, are done in collaboration with Singapore-based artists. Earlier this month, the centre refreshed these spaces.</Para><Para>The Project Gallery now houses the Who's By The River exhibit, an interactive re-creation of Singapore pioneer artist Liu Kang's masterpiece, Life By The River.</Para><Para>Not every company can afford not to charge for its activity spaces, though. Ms Charlotte Goh, Playeum's executive director, says the centre has a "Play-it-Forward" fund - children from social-sector organisations can play at its premises for free, but it charges for other children.</Para><Para>Despite charging for admission, she says the centre's programmes have been well-received.</Para><Para>The other arts companies also report encouraging responses to their programmes, which they attribute to the variety and high quality of the content offered.</Para><Para>The providers pay close attention to parents' feedback, wants and needs.</Para><Para>Playeum, for instance, will launch a new hands-on exhibition in May, with a theme revolving around Steam (Science, Technology, Engineering, Art and Mathematics). Ms Goh says this is because it has seen "a growing interest" in this interdisciplinary approach to learning.</Para><Para>At Superhero Me, programmes are focused on public advocacy projects. The company's aim is also to bring less-privileged and special-needs children together with the public and have them socialise through the arts.</Para><Para>Co-founder Jean Loo says: "By providing socialising opportunities through the arts, we hope to remove the fear of children who might appear different or behave differently from their peers. Our goal is for every child to feel welcome and for those with special needs to not have to apologise for who they are."</Para><Para>Mrs Chan Lai Yee, 39, has involved her two children aged six and 11 years in Superhero Me's programmes since last year.</Para><Para>The bank manager finds its workshops helpful for her daughter, who is on the autism spectrum.</Para><Para>She says: "My daughter gets to meet different people and has become more willing to engage in conversations with others as a result. I also like it that the facilitators are warm and loving. They are like her big sisters and brothers, guiding her along."</Para><Para>During the recent March school holidays, she enrolled her son in Superhero Me's arts camp.</Para><Para>Through the camp, she says, he has learnt to connect better with his sister and also to care for other children with different and special needs.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Bryna Singh </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Keppel Centre of Art Education at the National Gallery Singapore houses two immersive spaces and two learning spaces, with the exhibits and activities refreshed every 18 to 24 months. </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

