<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180324ee3p002ky" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002ky</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002ky" fid="an"/><Num value="1144" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Life after addiction</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Entertainer Irene Ang endured trauma as a child - her mother was addicted to drugs, and her father to gambling. She and her mother tell The Sunday Times how they picked up the pieces and moved on</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">John Lui </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"/><Code value="gcat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002ky</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002ky" fid="an"/><Num value="1144" fid="wc"/><Num value="4779" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="md"/><Time value="234519" fid="upt"/><Time value="234519" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId276477861"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash928593FCC274FC66"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC592723"/><Code value="FSPRBC847446"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="592723"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Living/Lifestyle</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="847446"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:glife"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Life after addiction</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Entertainer Irene Ang endured trauma as a child - her mother was addicted to drugs, and her father to gambling. She and her mother tell The Sunday Times how they picked up the pieces and moved on</Para><Para>Earlier this month, entertainer Irene Ang opened up about the trauma she and her brother suffered as children.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Her family was racked by addiction: her mother to heroin and tranquillisers, and her father to gambling.</Para><Para>Ang, who is the chief executive of talent agency Fly Entertainment, spoke about how her mother, in a rage and high on drugs, once chased her around with a chopper in hand.</Para><Para>Afterwards, her mother, Madam Tan Ming Choo, had no recollection of doing that.</Para><Para>Ang shared these details at an event organised by the National Addictions Management Service and North East Community Development Council on March 10.</Para><Para>Ang's father and mother now work in her company as a driver and cook respectively.</Para><Para>They divorced in 1984 and her father has two children from another marriage.</Para><Para>I want them to know I used to sit there... I want them to know that if I can make it off the floor, so can they.</Para><Para>MADAM TAN MING CHOO on inspiring drug abusers to start anew</Para><Para>We still have fights. My mother will still forget my birthday or say my brother helped her find and pay for her flat when it was me.</Para><Para>ENTERTAINER IRENE ANG on her mother, Madam Tan Ming Choo</Para><Para>The Sunday Times follows up with Ang, 50, and her mother, Madam Tan, 69.</Para><Para>Madam Tan Ming Choo's story: You can kick the habit</Para><Para>When former inmates and wardens from prison see her, they call out: "Hey, gigolo."</Para><Para>Madam Tan Ming Choo's nickname is a pun on her prison number, 256, pronounced "jee gor luck" in Hokkien. From 1976 to 1983, she was in and out of jail. The longest stretch was three years.</Para><Para>She says she was hooked on "chasing the dragon" - sucking heroin vapour through a straw. She was also taking Upjohn pills, a tranquilliser. She got into drugs - she has said in previous interviews - to ease the pain of getting married at 18 to an unfaithful man, who also cheated her of her savings.</Para><Para>The former nightclub singer was housed in the wing for drug offenders. She hated her loss of freedom as an inmate. "You had fixed times to get up, to eat, to do everything," she says.</Para><Para>But her addiction was a tough habit to overcome and she would break the law again and get sent back. "I made up stories to get money. I told friends the PUB had sent a final notice. They took pity on me and gave me money and I spent it on drugs," she says.</Para><Para>She gave drugs up for good after her daughter, Irene Ang, wrote a letter to her saying that she and her brother would disown her if she relapsed.</Para><Para>Going cold turkey was tough. "I would get chills, fever, nausea and insomnia," she says. But with the help of her children and counsellors, she pulled through the period and has spent the last three decades clean.</Para><Para>One key step: Never go back to situations or friends associated with drugs.</Para><Para>A friend who was looking out for her made sure of that by throwing away her telephone book.</Para><Para>Sometimes, Madam Tan runs into former inmates. They might be the same age as her, but are still in the grip of addiction.</Para><Para>She has been trying to make up for the pain she caused her family and would like to do more. She wants to speak in public about her journey, to show others that it is possible to kick the habit and live a full life.</Para><Para>"I want them to know I used to sit there, on the floor like them, looking up at people on stage talking about how they made something of their lives. I want them to know that if I can make it off the floor, so can they."</Para><Para>Irene Ang's story: Still an ongoing process of healing</Para><Para>Turning 50 is a milestone that people mark with parties and gifts. But Irene Ang wanted to do something more.</Para><Para>"I wanted to let go of the pain," she says.</Para><Para>She wanted to be free of the hurt and resentment caused by her mother, Madam Tan Ming Choo, who was absent because she was in prison for drug offences, and a father who disappeared for days at a stretch, leaving the children in the care of his mother.</Para><Para>The entertainer, who is single, made an anti-drug video with her mother last year with the label #SayNoWithFly.</Para><Para>In it, they talk about the damage done and Madam Tan apologises to her daughter.</Para><Para>She has resolved to forgive, but that is not easy to do when the other party has no memory of doing harm, such as when her mother threatened to kill herself by jumping out of the window, with school-age Ang clinging on to stop her while, at the same time, calling the police.</Para><Para>Forgiveness and apologies might have been offered and accepted, but the process of healing is still going on today, she says.</Para><Para>"We still have fights. My mother will still forget my birthday or say my brother helped her find and pay for her flat when it was me," she says.</Para><Para>Ang gives financial and other help to charities such as HCSA Dayspring, a home and counselling centre for women and girls in need, such as those fleeing abuse.</Para><Para>She thinks about how close she was to entering such a home, if not for her relatives, especially her grandmother, who died in 1996.</Para><Para>"Thank God I didn't have to be in a home. I had my grandmother. She was the most important person in my life.</Para><Para>"Without her, I would not be here," says Ang, who is set to appear in VIC, a Chinese drama on online platform Toggle.</Para><Para>In July, she will appear in the live comedy show Happily Ever Laughter - The Battle, with Kumar, Koh Chieng Mun, Fakkah Fuzz and others.</Para><Para>The comedienne says her grandmother was "the queen of multitasking" - she took care of her and her brother, as well as the children from neighbouring flats, while running a bao (steamed bun) stall close by.</Para><Para>Ang, a Christian, is grateful that her mother stood in line for hours to get her daughter into CHIJ (Kellock), a place where she found solace in the chapel.</Para><Para>She developed a habit of talking aloud to God - one that alarmed her mother when she found her daughter muttering to herself in the shower.</Para><Para>"She thought I was possessed," says Ang with a laugh.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">John Lui </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Madam Tan Ming Choo now works as a cook at her daughter Irene Ang's company, Fly Entertainment. </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

