<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180328ee3s001jm" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180328ee3s001jm</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180328ee3s001jm" fid="an"/><Num value="928" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180328" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="25"/><S value="54"/><M value="72"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">ST</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Real threat is not online falsehood but selective news consumption, says European lawyer</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>SINGAPORE - The real threat to democracy is not deliberate online falsehood, but selective news consumption, an European lawyer and IT expert said on Wednesday (March 28).</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Yasmine Yahya </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180328ee3s001jm</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180328ee3s001jm" fid="an"/><Num value="928" fid="wc"/><Num value="4833" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180328" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180328" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180328" fid="md"/><Time value="080017" fid="upt"/><Time value="080017" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId277805357"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashBE1A796E53DD5FD1"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NONS"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC682661"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="682661"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018593-20180327-195122"/><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">ST</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Real threat is not online falsehood but selective news consumption, says European lawyer</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>SINGAPORE - The real threat to democracy is not deliberate online falsehood, but selective news consumption, an European lawyer and IT expert said on Wednesday (March 28).</Para><Para>"The overreaching problem is that the news I get is not the news you get and so on," Mr Dan Shefet noted in his written submission to the Select Committee on deliberate online falsehoods.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Algorithms used by technology companies such as Google and Facebook track users' online activities and preferences to sort them into groups for targeted advertising, he noted. These algorithms also determine what articles and sources show up on a person's news feed, which in turn creates bubbles and echo chambers.</Para><Para>"That is very dangerous in a democracy. Whether it's fake or not is not the point. We don't have the same information," he warned the committee. "This amounts to psychological manipulation."</Para><Para>Mr Shefet, who is also a consultant to Unesco, said this problem should be addressed in the run-up to major political events such as an election.</Para><Para>"It's a question of suspending the echo chambers for five weeks before an election so every one has the same news," he said.</Para><Para>Mr Shefet noted in his submission that some may say this is like making it compulsory for all news stands "to carry the same newspapers all over the country prior to elections", but did not give more details on how this could be implemented. Govt should take down falsehoods to send a strong message Related StoryNetizens can sieve out falsehoods most times, but govt action needed in emergencies: NTU lecturers nm-fake1-2803.png Related StorySingaporean bore the brunt of xenophobic comments when his photo was misused online Related StoryThe ST Guide To... spotting fake news</Para><Para>He also stressed that it was important for governments to regulate tech companies and the online space, perhaps through appointing an Internet ombudsman which can offer guidance to Internet platform providers and search engine operators on what is unacceptable content.</Para><Para>Tech companies, when asked to better police the content on their platforms, often argue that they are infrastructure providers and not content producers, and are not in the position to judge what should be taken down, Mr Shefet noted.</Para><Para>"So what we need here is an institution that will give guidance to the social media companies and search engines and so on. And that can be done very quickly if the guidance is not a legally binding decision. That judicial oversight could be almost real time."</Para><Para>Mr Shefet also raised another concern - behavioural psychology research which, in the wrong hands, could be used to manipulate people on a large scale.</Para><Para>He cited ongoing research being conducted by Stanford University on the 60 "persuasion points" that each person is vulnerable to.</Para><Para>"If I had the data, I could persuade you to do anything I want you to do. It's dangerous to have this kind of science, this kind of research, if it falls in the wrong hands, as we saw with Cambridge Analytica," he said.</Para><Para>Mr Shefet was referring to how the British data-mining firm was reported to have used Facebook to gather the private information of tens of millions of Americans, to help United States President Donald Trump during the 2016 US presidential election.</Para><Para>Public hearings to fight online falsehoods: Read the submissions here and watch more videos. Related Stories: nm-fake1-2803.png Related StorySingaporean bore the brunt of xenophobic comments when his photo was misused online Govt should take down falsehoods to send a strong message Related StoryNetizens can sieve out falsehoods most times, but govt action needed in emergencies: NTU lecturers Online content producers dispute what is defined as truth Related StoryNo need for new laws to counter online falsehoods, activists tell Select Committee Legislation can sometimes backfire Related StoryAcademic Cherian George urges caution in drafting new laws to tackle online untruths, calls for repeal of insult law NLB stepping up critical thinking in fight against fake news Related StoryNLB stepping up efforts to arm the public with critical thinking skills in fight against fake news cc.jpg Related StoryHuman Rights Watch responds to criticisms from Select Committee hearing on its report hzjointtask0327.jpg Related StoryForm a joint task force with Malaysia to tackle online falsehoods, suggests entrepreneur Independent, multi-stakeholder body needed to fight online falsehoods Related StoryIndependent, multi-stakeholder body needed to fight falsehoods: RSIS senior fellow Tech firms have "a pattern of denial and inaction" Related StoryPattern of 'denial and inaction' in tech firms' response to misuse on platforms: US professor tells Select Committee on fake news Legislation against online falsehoods should not endanger the work of journalists Related StoryLegislation against online falsehoods should not be so broad that it endangers the work of journalists, says SPH Independent fact-checking council can combat deliberate online falsehoods Related StoryIndependent fact-checking council can combat deliberate online falsehoods: SPH and CNA Facebook admits it should have told users about policy breach earlier Related StoryFacebook admits it should have told users earlier about breach of policy hzmortezashahrezaye0327.jpg Related StoryNo evidence to show that online falsehoods can change people's political opinions: Expert The role of languages in countering falsehoods Related StoryNUS academic sounds warning on falsehoods spread in mother tongues and dialects via closed-group platforms Indonesia to have hoax crisis centres to counter online falsehoods Related StoryHoax crisis centres will be launched to counter falsehoods ahead of Indonesian elections, says founder of anti-hoax network</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Yasmine Yahya </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

