<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180325ee3q0030n" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName><FolderName id="302210842" rl="100">FNA Asian Economics</FolderName><FolderName id="302210876" rl="100">FNA Singapore Economics</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180325ee3q0030n</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180325ee3q0030n" fid="an"/><Num value="1679" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180326" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="29"/><S value="58"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">The Life Interview With Miguel McKelvey; The Life Interview with WeWork's Miguel McKelvey: Creative spaces</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Miguel McKelvey's childhood played a part in him founding WeWork, a platform for creators</Para><Para>Communal spaces have long been familiar to Mr Miguel McKelvey, co-founder of WeWork, a company that provides co-working spaces around the world.</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Venessa Lee </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"/><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="namz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"/><Code value="nitv"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="ncat"/><Code value="nfact"/><Code value="nfcpex"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180325ee3q0030n</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180325ee3q0030n" fid="an"/><Num value="1679" fid="wc"/><Num value="7868" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180326" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="234522" fid="upt"/><Time value="234522" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId276728626"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashC1946480B463BF2F"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOCOMOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSPRBC42502"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC695199"/><Code value="FSPRBC847446"/><Code value="FSPRBC874309"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="104"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018584-20180325-144929"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="glife"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Living/Lifestyle</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="847446"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018584-20180325-144929"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nitv"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Interviews</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="42502"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018584-20180325-144929"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:glife"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Content Types</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nitv"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nfact"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Factiva Filters</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nitv"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="nfcpex"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">C&amp;E Executive News Filter</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:nitv"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">The Life Interview With Miguel McKelvey; The Life Interview with WeWork's Miguel McKelvey: Creative spaces</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Miguel McKelvey's childhood played a part in him founding WeWork, a platform for creators</Para><Para>Communal spaces have long been familiar to Mr Miguel McKelvey, co-founder of WeWork, a company that provides co-working spaces around the world.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Mr McKelvey, 43, was raised in a collective in Oregon in the United States, which his mother formed with several close female friends and their children.</Para><Para>An unconventional upbringing was something he had in common with his business partner and fellow billionaire, Mr Adam Neumann, WeWork's other co-founder and its chief executive officer, who lived in a kibbutz - a type of collective settlement that is unique to Israel - for part of his childhood.</Para><Para>"Adam and I love being surrounded by people. (We) moved around a lot as kids and the stability for both of us came from that extended network of people that we relied upon.</Para><Para>"We love to build these communities of people who are connected through shared interests," says Mr McKelvey, who is also WeWork's chief culture officer.</Para><Para>The word "community" comes up often in an exclusive interview with Mr McKelvey, who visited Singapore, WeWork's first South-east Asian location, for the first time earlier this month.</Para><Para>The former basketball player, who is 2.03m-tall, rocks a casual Silicon Valley style in his grey T-shirt and trousers. The Life Interview with Miguel McKelvey</Para><Para>WeWork, a start-up founded by Mr McKelvey and Mr Neumann in 2010, is headquartered in New York. It bills itself not as a provider of shared offices, but as a "platform for creators".</Para><Para>According to Mr McKelvey, this means WeWork members not only work in the same space, but also get the opportunity to share ideas, energy and business interactions with people who are similarly passionate about their work.</Para><Para>Aimed at encouraging interactions between like-minded people, ranging from freelancers to company employees, members can collaborate in person or connect virtually with other members around the world, with events organised to encourage connections.</Para><Para>WeWork has expanded explosively, rolling out 230 locations worldwide in just eight years.</Para><Para>Mr Miguel McKelvey (left) with WeWork co-founder Adam Neumann (second from left) in a 2016 photo. PHOTO: COURTESY OF WEWORK</Para><Para>At its Beach Road location, communal spaces and glass-paned individual offices come with stylish interiors and amenities such as cleaning services and meeting rooms, as well as coffee and three kinds of beer on tap.</Para><Para>WeWork launched in Singapore in December last year in Beach Road and two more locations will open in the Central Business District in the near future, with a fourth slated to open in Funan mallnext year. With a presence in 71 cities globally, WeWork will open its first offices in Thailand, Indonesia, Malaysia and the Philippines by the end of the year.</Para><Para>The company is valued at about US$20 billion (S$26.3 billion), a figure exceeded only by Uber and Airbnb among US start-ups, Forbes reported in October last year.</Para><Para>WeWork's framing of the value of work and community has roots in Mr McKelvey's background.</Para><Para>bp_coshare_141217_10.jpg</Para><Para>Related Story</Para><Para>Co-working space start-up WeWork calls Funan home</Para><Para>The contrasting influences of being the only child of a single parent with hippie sensibilities, and the brands of corporate America that he admired as a child, informed his entrepreneurial approach.</Para><Para>Breaking from traditional family structures, his mother shared responsibilities with other women in the collective.</Para><Para>She also took up activist causes such as women's rights, anti-war and environmental awareness, and co-founded a newspaper.</Para><Para>Mr McKelvey recalls a childhood that was starkly different from that of his peers in the town of Eugene, Oregon. He did not have cable television and ate tofu and organic food, outlier practices at the time in the US which have since entered the mainstream conversation.</Para><Para>"I was always trying to reconcile my relationship between this alternative world and the more commercial world," he says.</Para><Para>A desire to bring people together</Para><Para>He was fascinated with Nike and would hang out at his hometown's Nike store after school to look at innovative products such as Air Jordan sneakers.</Para><Para>"I was intrigued by the business and marketing side and how influential brands can be and (ideas such as) how does a business actually transform culture?" he says.</Para><Para>He planned to study business in university, but found economics boring.</Para><Para>I always feel that I'm in control of my future. I have the ability to shape whatever I want to happen, through my choices and actions. I think a lot of people would think they want to do something, then they would immediately think of a reason why they can't do it. I don't have that. That doesn't occur to me, for whatever reason.</Para><Para>MR MIGUEL MCKELVEY, co-founder and chief culture officer of WeWork</Para><Para>While doing a course on sculpture, which he thoroughly enjoyed, a professor's remark about his artwork's "architectural" quality prompted him to switch to architecture, which he took at the University of Oregon, where he also played college basketball.</Para><Para>After university, he visited a childhood friend, Mr John Hayden, who was working in Tokyo, hoping to take in the architectural sights in Japan, which he had studied.</Para><Para>There, a hit song by American girl group TLC, whose greatest success was in the 1990s, put paid to his plans and launched his entrepreneurial career.</Para><Para>"There was a popular song at that time called No Scrubs and who even knows what a scrub is - I barely knew (the word myself).</Para><Para>"Other people in Japan wanted to know, 'What's a scrub?'" he says .</Para><Para>He and Mr Hayden launched English, baby! in 2000, using popular culture as a fun way to teach English.</Para><Para>"It was the time of the first dotcom boom. It seemed like anyone could start a company - lots of people were - and so, we started that first company, English, baby!" says Mr McKelvey.</Para><Para>His original two-week tourist budget was stretched by eating family-sized yogurt portions for protein and white bread with toppings such as pepper, butter or cheap curry paste.</Para><Para>Although he was eventually involved in English, baby! for several years, his dream was always "to move to New York and be an architect".</Para><Para>He stayed in Japan for a few months to jump-start the business, an online community for learning English, before returning to the US.</Para><Para>Back home, although he had his own successful business, he found it challenging to find work in architecture as he had no experience in the field. He eventually found a job at a small architecture firm in Brooklyn, New York, where he worked on accounts such as the American Apparel retail stores.</Para><Para>But he was dissatisfied with the physical space he found himself in.</Para><Para>During his job interview, he recalls how people wrote their company name with marker pen on the building, indicating a number or drawing arrows for directions to their offices.</Para><Para>"The building was full of small, creative companies, but they weren't being served by this building," says Mr McKelvey.</Para><Para>Neither the heating nor the air-conditioning was adequate; Internet connections were unreliable and trains rattled noisily nearby.</Para><Para>During this time, he met Mr Neumann, who is now in his late 30s, through a mutual friend, and the pair decided to address this lack of infrastructure. In 2008, they set up their first business, Green Desk, together, which provided ready-to-use, eco-friendly office spaces.</Para><Para>Green Desk, in many ways, could be viewed as a precursor to WeWork.</Para><Para>"When we started Green Desk, it was more focused on providing that empowering infrastructure, giving a small business a way to just walk into a building, be up and running in a few minutes and focus on your work," says Mr McKelvey.</Para><Para>"The exciting thing for us was that once we brought those people together, you would see people forming friendships and starting to do business with one another."</Para><Para>After one social event they had organised for their tenants, he realised that the vibe of the building had changed overnight, with much more conversation flowing and a greater sense of connectedness.</Para><Para>He and Mr Neumann wanted to "figure out how to bring people together and create this energy that can flow between people".</Para><Para>They left Green Desk, which focused more on infrastructure, and founded WeWork in 2010, which was about "uniting" such communities, says Mr McKelvey.</Para><Para>"We had that inspiration to grow very quickly and to open many more locations."</Para><Para>He says WeWork was, in part, lucky in its timing. The financial crisis of the late 2000s prompted questioning about how secure traditional career paths and established companies were, and people started to re-evaluate the kind of careers they wanted.</Para><Para>While WeWork embarks on global expansion, Mr McKelvey remains "humble and authentic", says Ms Anita Shannon, WeWork's director of culture operations.</Para><Para>"He treats everyone the exact same way," she says.</Para><Para>"When Miguel was designing WeWork for the first time, thinking about where to put the water and the printing station was all very intentional," she says, adding that he would remark that the coffee had to be placed at an area where there was more space for human interaction.</Para><Para>Mr McKelvey has his own definition of success.</Para><Para>"When I was a kid, when I would think about how I defined success, it usually was in creating and building something and not relying on someone else to do it for me," he says.</Para><Para>He was independent from a young age, doing laundry and making dinner from about seven.</Para><Para>"I was connected to putting work into something and getting results from it, so I think I have always got joy from that," says Mr McKelvey.</Para><Para>"Adam and I are people who have no limitations. Neither of us ever thinks something can't be done. We're both always optimistic."</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Venessa Lee </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Mr Miguel McKelvey co-founded WeWork in 2010. </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

