<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180324ee3p002kn" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002kn</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002kn" fid="an"/><Num value="1477" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="24"/><S value="59"/><M value="78"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Home</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Medical overcharging and overtreating; It's not a black and white problem, say docs</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Such cases hard to prove as doctors might have been trying to be careful</Para><Para>A patient had hernia in the abdomen, when an organ pushes through an opening in the muscle or tissue.</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Salma Khalik </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="ghea"/><Code value="gcat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002kn</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002kn" fid="an"/><Num value="1477" fid="wc"/><Num value="6888" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="md"/><Time value="234518" fid="upt"/><Time value="234518" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId276477861"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash30898C2FFE0105C4"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORGOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC853742"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="ghea"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Health</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="853742"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:ghea"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Home</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Medical overcharging and overtreating; It's not a black and white problem, say docs</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Such cases hard to prove as doctors might have been trying to be careful</Para><Para>A patient had hernia in the abdomen, when an organ pushes through an opening in the muscle or tissue.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>The doctor decided that to prevent it from happening again, it was best to give her a tummy tuck, removing excess fat in her abdomen.</Para><Para>But why waste that fat? So it was used to give the 37-year-old woman a more rounded bottom.</Para><Para>Because tummy tucks and fat transfers to the buttocks are aesthetic procedures not covered by insurance, which pays only for medical treatments, the surgeon put all the charges under hernia repair.</Para><Para>That, after all, was the original problem. This was one of many questionable bills that insurers say are pushing up claims, and hence premiums, for everyone.</Para><Para>Another patient stubbed her toe and the nail fell out. The doctor found a fungal infection in the toe and warded the patient for a couple of days to make sure it had not entered the blood stream.</Para><Para>The $6,000 bill might seem extreme for a lost toenail, but was the doctor merely being careful, or was he over-servicing the patient for his own profit?</Para><Para>Both the Ministry of Health (MOH) and the Singapore Medical Council (SMC) recently warned doctors that they take a serious view of doctors overcharging and overtreating patients.</Para><Para>BETTER SAFE THAN SORRY</Para><Para>One GP missed the serious eye condition of a patient. He was faulted for not referring the patient to an eye specialist. He was suspended. The take-home message is - if in doubt, refer to a specialist. Missing a diagnosis is not acceptable.</Para><Para>A SPECIALIST IN PRIVATE PRACTICE, on the apparent increase in "over-servicing".</Para><Para>But those whom The Sunday Times spoke to say the problem is not a straightforward one. They say there are many grey areas, and very little black and white, in such cases. It is often hard to define what is overcharging or over-servicing.</Para><Para>OVERCHARGING</Para><Para>There are no fee guidelines, so how do doctors know if their fees constitute overcharging, one asked.</Para><Para>So far, only one doctor has been punished by the SMC for overcharging her patient.</Para><Para>Surgeon Susan Lim's bill of $26 million for five months of care for her royal Bruneian patient resulted in a three-year suspension and a $10,000 fine in 2012.</Para><Para>Most instances of overcharging are not that spectacular and rarely exceed $1 million. There are smaller cases where a doctor might charge two or three times what his peers do, but it could be argued that his skills might be superior.</Para><Para>Private gastroenterologist Desmond Wai said he refers patients who need a gallbladder or appendix removed to a surgeon.</Para><Para>He said: "Obviously, I would not use an expensive surgeon, unless he or she can prove the high charges are justified by supreme clinical outcome."</Para><Para>There are also other valid reasons for higher charges, Dr Wai said, such as for treatments done after office hours. He added that doctors who grossly overcharge would find themselves with fewer patients as "our charges and clinical outcome are very transparent within the medical circle".</Para><Para>But others disagree.</Para><Para>One said the practice is not widespread, but he knows of some doctors who collude with surgeons for kickbacks - which is strictly disallowed under the SMC's Ethical Code and Ethical Guidelines.</Para><Para>Said one doctor: "We all know that there are a few individuals who do this in the private sector and, unfortunately, they have been getting away with it for many years and setting a bad example for the rest of us 'good doctors' who are practising high-quality medicine at fair prices.</Para><Para>"It's right of MOH to sound the warnings. But honestly, it's going to be hard for them to do something."</Para><Para>OVERTREATING</Para><Para>Overtreating or over-servicing patients is another grey area, several doctors said.</Para><Para>One specialist in private practice, who asked not to be named, said: "The SMC has punished several doctors for not correctly diagnosing a patient's medical problem. Most of us watch SMC verdicts very carefully, as SMC is our watchdog.</Para><Para>"One GP missed the serious eye condition of a patient. He was faulted for not referring the patient to an eye specialist.</Para><Para>"He was suspended. The take-home message is - if in doubt, refer to a specialist. Missing a diagnosis is not acceptable."</Para><Para>The subject of a missed diagnosis was raised in Parliament last year, when MP Lim Wee Kiak asked whether doctors should "send all cases for detailed diagnostic tests to avoid misdiagnosing rare medical conditions".</Para><Para>He was referring to a paediatrician who was suspended for not diagnosing an infant with Kawasaki disease. More than 1,000 doctors signed a petition to the authorities supporting the paediatrician.</Para><Para>One private specialist said paediatricians are asking if testing for Kawasaki disease, which is fairly rare, should be done as a first-line test. But they are also asking: Would doing that be considered over-servicing?</Para><Para>Said one: "Damned if we do and damned if we don't."</Para><Para>One private surgeon said he knows of a colleague who would operate on patients twice, charging about $35,000 each time. The first time was for a biopsy and the second to remove the tumour.</Para><Para>He said that a good doctor would have a pathologist on standby to determine if the sample tissue was cancerous so everything could be done at one go.</Para><Para>Senior Minister of State for Health Chee Hong Tat told Parliament earlier this month about patients "who were admitted for gastritis or piles, and then referred to (doctors in) many other specialities ranging from dermatology, ophthalmology, ear, nose and throat, and orthopaedics, for additional scans and tests".</Para><Para>Doctors said such multi-specialist cases need to be looked at on a case-by-case basis.</Para><Para>Dr Wai gave an example of when he had to call in different specialists for one patient. He said: "I had one very sick liver cancer and liver cirrhosis patient that I managed at ICU (intensive care unit).</Para><Para>"He had renal impairment, heart problem, sternum bone infection, and liver cirrhosis and liver cancer, that is, multi-organ failure.</Para><Para>"My team consisted of myself, an infectious disease specialist, a chest surgeon, a nephrologist, a cardiologist, an intensivist and an interventional radiologist."</Para><Para>The patient recovered and was discharged. Dr Wai said: "Outsiders may find it odd that so many doctors take care of one patient. But we all know it's not over-servicing."</Para><Para>However, one patient who saw four private-sector doctors and one in a public hospital for a bad back said the private specialists were recommending various newfangled treatments with estimated fees of more than $60,000.</Para><Para>The specialist in the public hospital told him that at his age, conventional treatment would be better. The cost would be about $25,000.</Para><Para>He said it was not about the cost, as he was fully insured, but what was best for the patient. He felt the only honest doctor in the lot was the one in the public hospital.</Para><Para>PATIENTS' PREFERENCE</Para><Para>Doctors say that sometimes, they accede to a patient's preference.</Para><Para>For example, a patient who can be treated as an outpatient, but who might be required to go for daily tests over several days, might prefer to be warded during that period.</Para><Para>As this is more convenient for the patient, there is no reason for the doctor to refuse.</Para><Para>Dr Chia Shi-Lu, head of the Government Parliamentary Committee for Health, said some cases of over-servicing are not strictly wrong but are a "by-product of the full-rider, no co-payment policy".</Para><Para>The same goes for patients opting for more expensive treatments, though cheaper ones exist. Whether the more expensive treatment is better might be debatable, he said.</Para><Para>Dr Chia, an orthopaedic surgeon at Singapore General Hospital, added: "These are all grey areas and, in public hospitals, we face some of these pressures too when patients insist on staying or asking for more tests, as 'they are already in hospital and insurance is covering'.</Para><Para>"These are not strictly wrong by professional or ethical mores, as patient choice has its place, provided the choice does not lead to more harm."</Para><Para>OTHER FACTORS</Para><Para>A doctor said bureaucracy is also to blame. One example is the way MediShield Life-linked insurance claims have to be filed electronically. These would include all Integrated Shield Plans that provide cover for private care.</Para><Para>Not all doctors in private practice have electronic filing in their clinics. So a patient is unable to claim against insurance if the doctor cannot file the details of the treatment and his bill electronically. But if the patient is warded, his claim can be made through the hospital.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Salma Khalik </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

