<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180324ee3p002li" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002li</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002li" fid="an"/><Num value="2661" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="29"/><S value="60"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Insight</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Fall in foreign manpower; How changes to manpower policy are playing out</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>From more locals in workforce to higher productivity, the benefits are evident; but businesses in some sectors are finding it hard to cope</Para><Para>A decade after starting software development company Tinkerbox Studios, founder Jaryl Sim, 32, had to ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Joanna Seow </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="in"><Code value="i3302021"/><Code value="i3302"/><Code value="i330202"/><Code value="icomp"/><Code value="itech"/></CSet><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002li</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002li" fid="an"/><Num value="2661" fid="wc"/><Num value="12896" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="md"/><Time value="234520" fid="upt"/><Time value="234520" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId276477861"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="tnomci"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashC9D18BB9FA166171"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORGOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCIN"/><Code value="FSP2YESIN"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESPEOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NONS"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC851402"/><Code value="FSPRBC855278"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="in"><Code value="i3302021"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Applications Software</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="851402"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="4"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="i3302"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Computers/Consumer Electronics</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="in:i3302021"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="i330202"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Software</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="in:i3302021"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="3"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="icomp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Computing</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="in:i3302021"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="itech"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Technology</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="in:i3302021"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Insight</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Fall in foreign manpower; How changes to manpower policy are playing out</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>From more locals in workforce to higher productivity, the benefits are evident; but businesses in some sectors are finding it hard to cope</Para><Para>A decade after starting software development company Tinkerbox Studios, founder Jaryl Sim, 32, had to disband a team of 10 software engineers last year due to rising costs.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Costs began to escalate when Tinkerbox could not find enough locals with the requisite skills, and had to bring in expensive foreign hires.</Para><Para>"We had to hire foreigners because there are not enough local software engineers, but we can't bring them in below the minimum EP salary even if they are willing to accept the market rate, which is lower," says Mr Sim, referring to the Employment Pass scheme for foreign professionals.</Para><Para>The minimum EP salary was raised last January from $3,300 to $3,600. It was last raised in 2014, from $3,000. It is higher for those with more years of experience.</Para><Para>Employers like Mr Sim have been feeling the pinch of tighter foreign manpower policies in the hunt for suitable talent.</Para><Para>Labour market figures released recently showed that the number of foreigners working in Singapore, excluding maids, fell by 32,000 last year - the biggest drop in 15 years. This was mostly due to fewer work permit holders in the construction and marine shipyard industries.</Para><Para>But notably, the number of EP holders also dropped by 4,500, the first fall in at least six years.</Para><Para>Meanwhile, more local workers were in jobs. Local employment went up by 21,300 last year, meaning 0.9 per cent more Singaporeans and permanent residents (PRs) were in jobs last year than in 2016.</Para><Para>The decline in foreign worker numbers has come about after moves by the Government from 2010 onwards to tighten manpower and immigration policies, after the economy emerged from a recession. It has also rolled out measures to support companies which invest in technology and in local workers.</Para><Para>And then there are the effects of business cycles, with slower growth in 2015 and 2016 putting a dampener on the labour market.</Para><Para>Insight looks at the pros and cons of how recent efforts to manage the foreign employment situation have played out.</Para><Para>PLUS POINTS</Para><Para>From boosting the numbers of locals in employment, to pushing companies to raise productivity, the benefits of the tighter foreign manpower policy are clear to see.</Para><Para>Measures to slow the inflow of foreigners have covered all levels of workers, ranging from higher levies and stricter quotas for work permit holders, to higher qualifying salaries for mid-level skilled workers on S Passes and higher-skilled workers on EPs.</Para><Para>More recently, there has been a focus on ensuring sufficient jobs for local professionals, managers, executives and technicians (PMETs) as resident workers become more educated. The Fair Consideration Framework began in 2014, under which companies must post job ads on the national Jobs Bank for at least two weeks for Singaporeans to consider before they can to hire a foreigner on an EP.</Para><Para>Over the last two years, the Ministry of Manpower (MOM) has also placed on a watchlist 500 companies found to be favouring foreigners in hiring, and scrutinises their applications for EPs more closely.</Para><Para>MOM tells Insight that the top sectors which firms on its watchlist come from are infocomm technology (ICT), professional services, administrative and support activities and construction.</Para><Para>Companies on the watchlist can get help from organisations such as the Tripartite Alliance for Fair and Progressive Employment Practices (Tafep), Workforce Singapore and the institutes of higher learning to improve their human resource practices and hire fresh graduates and mid-career local PMETs.</Para><Para>So far, more than 2,200 Singaporean PMETs have been hired by these companies over the last two years and 150 companies have exited the watchlist.</Para><Para>Analysts say the measures should also be seen in tandem with policies to help companies adjust. If the tighter foreign manpower policies are the stick approach, schemes to help businesses invest in technology and automation, redesign jobs to attract locals, and upgrade workers' skills are the carrots.</Para><Para>The Adapt and Grow initiative, started in 2016, is a suite of programmes to place local job seekers in jobs and upgrade their skills.</Para><Para>Singapore National Employers Federation (Snef) executive director Koh Juan Kiat says companies can benefit from these as they provide funding and another source for hiring suitable workers.</Para><Para>For example, since 2016, about 870 companies have tapped the P-Max scheme administered by Snef to hire 955 PMETs, he says. P-Max helps small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) upgrade their human resource practices to attract and retain PMETs.</Para><Para>Second Manpower Minister Josephine Teo told employers recently that more than half of over 25,000 job seekers placed last year through Adapt and Grow schemes were PMETs - "people you need for your businesses", she said.</Para><Para>PRODUCTIVITY PUSH</Para><Para>Taken as a package, the policies have helped companies become more productive, say observers.</Para><Para>Singapore University of Social Sciences (SUSS) economist Randolph Tan says employers have been encouraged to rely less on labour and emphasise skills in how they plan their manpower strategies.</Para><Para>"Ultimately, the workforce will benefit from better employment outcomes if businesses do well and are able to perform more efficiently," says Associate Professor Tan, who is a Nominated MP.</Para><Para>The measures seem to have finally borne fruit last year, when labour productivity grew by 4.5 per cent, measured as value-added per actual hour worked. This was more than double the growth rates in the previous four years.</Para><Para>But economists also point out that it is hard to separate the effects of policies from the effects of global business cycles, as Singapore is a small, open economy.</Para><Para>DBS economist Irvin Seah says Singapore's productivity growth is heavily dependent on external factors, since the "value-added" portion, or gross domestic product - which is divided by hours worked - is driven largely by external demand.</Para><Para>The policies have boosted job prospects for local workers - with the growth in local employment rising in the past two years after a sharp drop in 2015.</Para><Para>And workers benefit from being better trained, says National Trades Union Congress (NTUC) assistant secretary-general Patrick Tay.</Para><Para>"The moves have nudged companies to train and develop their existing workforce to enhance their skills and capabilities," he says.</Para><Para>Even as more locals are being employed, are they getting to the companies which need them?</Para><Para>According to MOM, the decline in the number of EP holders last year was mainly in ICT and professional services. Meanwhile, more locals were employed in the financial and insurance services, ICT, professional services and healthcare sectors, so there is some overlap.</Para><Para>ON THE FLIP SIDE</Para><Para>On the other hand, employers struggling to staff their businesses have been asking for some of the measures to be modified, whether it is to hold off on future levy increases or to ease the restrictions for key growth industries.</Para><Para>While some businesses have been able to cope with the slower inflow of foreigners by automating their processes or finding suitable staff from the local talent pool, others have already paid the price.</Para><Para>Mr Kurt Wee, president of the Association of Small and Medium Enterprises (Asme), says many small businesses were forced to downsize in 2015 and 2016.</Para><Para>A Ministry of Trade and Industry report last year noted that the cessation rate of businesses rose considerably in 2015 and 2016.</Para><Para>Mr Wee notes that the tighter foreign manpower policies, such as increased levies, have raised wage costs amid other rising costs such as more maternity and paternity leave.</Para><Para>The difficulties can be industry specific: It is easier to automate processes in industries in the manufacturing sector, than in some service industries and in construction.</Para><Para>Also, bosses in certain industries say there just aren't enough workers.</Para><Para>These employers generally raise two main gripes - that they cannot find locals with the right talent, or that locals do not want to do the jobs they have on offer.</Para><Para>In high-technology industries like infocomm and fintech, Singaporean software engineers with deep skills and knowledge are hard to come by.</Para><Para>Mr Christopher Yeo, who founded artificial intelligence start-up Sentient.io last May, has ended up hiring experienced local engineers and giving them additional training in mathematics and statistics, or recruiting talent through his overseas offices in India and Australia.</Para><Para>Some have also found it harder to hire foreign professionals on EPs, given longer waiting times for approval or passes not being renewed.</Para><Para>Tinkerbox's Mr Sim says he typically had to wait up to two months for applications to be approved, as it could require multiple attempts.</Para><Para>"If the Government feels you're not paying high enough based on the candidate's qualifications and experience, it will reject it and you just have to keep trying again at a higher salary," he says.</Para><Para>Other bosses, especially those in services industries or industries which involve outdoor work such as oil and gas, and marine and offshore, say they cannot find Singaporeans willing to do the work.</Para><Para>Experts note that if businesses are not able to find workers, Singapore's attractiveness as a hub may be affected.</Para><Para>The recent move to extend the Jobs Bank posting requirement to smaller businesses with at least 10 staff, instead of those with more than 25, will raise administrative costs for start-ups especially, says UOB economist Francis Tan.</Para><Para>It may make it difficult for them to be nimble or to bring in a team from overseas with whom they are familiar, he adds.</Para><Para>There is also the worry that as economic growth continues to recover this year, companies constrained by the lack of workers will not be able to capitalise on it.</Para><Para>"Businesses understand the Government isn't going to have a liberal stand on foreign manpower, but we are hoping to see more broad growth for SMEs this year and if there isn't a supportive policy response, then businesses won't be able to execute their growth plans," says Asme's Mr Wee.</Para><Para>Furthermore, falling employment levels, as seen last year, are not ideal for the economy as a whole, since employment growth is one of the two drivers of economic growth - the other is productivity growth.</Para><Para>Last year was the first time since 2003 that the total workforce, not including maids, shrank over the course of the year.</Para><Para>While analysts say a rebound in employment growth this year is likely, it is unclear by how much.</Para><Para>Manpower Minister Lim Swee Say has said that the average net job growth of less than 10,000 a year in the past three years was not high enough.</Para><Para>"We need to bring it up to 25,000 to 40,000 a year to provide enough jobs for a 3.4 million workforce growing at about 1 per cent," he said during the debate on his ministry's budget earlier this month.</Para><Para>WHAT IS THE LONG GAME?</Para><Para>Given the intensity of the global competition for talent, Singapore is not closing the door to foreign professionals, especially those with niche skills which local workers have yet to hone.</Para><Para>Mr Lim has said that MOM will give companies who need such professionals some leeway to bring in foreigners, even if they do not meet all the requirements for an EP.</Para><Para>If the firms satisfy specified conditions, government agencies overseeing their sectors can recommend some flexibility when assessing their applications for EPs.</Para><Para>The ministry is also running a pilot scheme called the Capability Transfer Programme, which subsidises the cost of bringing in overseas experts to train local staff.</Para><Para>And the Lean Enterprise Development Scheme allows companies to hire extra lower-skilled foreign workers for a transitional period, so that local staff can be trained.</Para><Para>A balance needs to be struck.</Para><Para>Opening the door too widely to foreign manpower may lead to social issues and unhappiness among locals, which boiled over in 2013 when the Population White Paper projected Singapore's population could reach 6.9 million by 2030.</Para><Para>The population was then 5.4 million. It was 5.6 million last year.</Para><Para>The Government has now said that the population is likely to be "significantly below" the 2013 projection.</Para><Para>In fact, the working-age citizen population is expected to peak around 2020 and then decline, even with immigrants.</Para><Para>Workforce growth from this year to 2020 will be only about 1 to 2 per cent per year.</Para><Para>Thus, Mr Lim has said the aim is to sustain yearly economic growth of 3 per cent through achieving productivity growth of 2 per cent and employment growth of 1 per cent, though he noted this is not a rigid formula but a framework to guide priorities.</Para><Para>Asme's Mr Wee says that given the projected decline in the working-age citizen population after 2020, "businesses need some clarity on the foreign manpower policy framework and population plan". This is so they can plan their investment strategies, as investments take time to build up, he says.</Para><Para>For now, employers can look at attracting and retaining local staff by using fair, merit-based and inclusive recruitment practices, says a Tafep spokesman. Best practices can be found in the Tripartite Standard on Recruitment Practices on the Tafep website.</Para><Para>Those that have trouble finding the right talent can expand their search to workers with transferable skills but whose experience may be in a different job role or industry.</Para><Para>To help locals and foreigners work well together, use English as a common language, and share Singapore's workplace norms, organisational values and expected behaviours with new employees, the spokesman adds.</Para><Para>"Employers need to understand and accept that different employees will have different needs and priorities... Cookie-cutter policies not only fail to meet the needs of the employees but may also foster resentment."</Para><Para>In the longer run, however, economists have varying views on the sustainability of the tighter foreign manpower policies.</Para><Para>Associate Professor Tan saysthe controls on foreign manpower may have to be tightened even further in some cases, as long as businesses continue to have access to the skills they need.</Para><Para>DBS' Mr Seah, however, sees a shift towards more flexibility in the lower-skilled foreign worker segment.</Para><Para>As the resident workforce becomes better skilled, there will be even fewer people to do manual work in essential roles like drivers, construction workers and cleaners.</Para><Para>A key marker to avoid would be if constraints on foreign manpower make firms reluctant to start new ventures, expand, or change strategy, because they perceive great difficulty in filling positions, says SUSS economist Walter Theseira.</Para><Para>"That would negatively affect Singaporeans," he notes.</Para><Para>He adds that Singapore's foreign manpower policy is part of a larger, long-term strategy to develop the resident workforce. This is why foreign talent who come here should decide whether to spend a few years here, at the end of which they should have trained a local to take over their job, or to sink roots here, and take on the rights and responsibilities of a PR or citizen.</Para><Para>It is a different direction than that of cities like New York or London, which are part of larger countries and will not collapse if immigrants "move in briefly, take what they can, and then leave", he says.</Para><Para>"Singapore will collapse if we don't get people who are committed to Singapore to join us in the long run, and if we don't upgrade Singaporeans to take on the best and most challenging jobs."</Para><Para>Manpower Minister Lim Swee Say has said that the average net job growth of less than 10,000 a year in the past three years was not high enough. "We need to bring it up to 25,000 to 40,000 a year to provide enough jobs for a 3.4 million workforce growing at about 1 per cent," he said during the debate on his ministry's budget earlier this month.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Joanna Seow </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

