<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180324ee3p002jy" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002jy</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002jy" fid="an"/><Num value="1274" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="28"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Top of the News</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Paramedic heroes relive Khoo Teck Puat Hospital shooting</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>As paramedics, they were used to saving lives - but not in the way that transpired one evening in June 2015. When the two colleagues went to see what the commotion was in a room near Khoo Teck Puat Hospital's Accident and Emergency section,...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Zaihan Mohamed Yusof </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180324ee3p002jy</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180324ee3p002jy" fid="an"/><Num value="1274" fid="wc"/><Num value="5898" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180325" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180324" fid="md"/><Time value="234516" fid="upt"/><Time value="234516" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId276477861"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashE8EFD5EB36360F66"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NONS"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC592723"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="592723"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018580-20180324-144303"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Top of the News</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Paramedic heroes relive Khoo Teck Puat Hospital shooting</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>As paramedics, they were used to saving lives - but not in the way that transpired one evening in June 2015. When the two colleagues went to see what the commotion was in a room near Khoo Teck Puat Hospital's Accident and Emergency section, they found themselves in a struggle with a patient who fired three shots from a revolver, two of which hit a policeman who was trying to stop him from escaping. The Sunday Times reveals the drama, as recounted by the two heroes for the first time.</Para><Para>Paramedics Prakash Krishnan and Elfredo Jose Jr Rellita Abasolo heard things "falling down" from a nearby room, then saw a female nurse running out of it, screaming: "Help! Call security!"</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Peering in, they saw a shirtless medical patient wearing leg restraints scuffling with a policeman on the floor.</Para><Para>Muhammad Iskandar Sa'at, a patient who was trying to escape custody during treatment, had somehow managed to grab Staff Sergeant Muhammad Sadli Razali's baton and was raining blows on him.</Para><Para>Mr Prakash initially thought they had been fighting over a taser and jumped between them. Fearing that it might go off accidentally, Mr Prakash forced a pillow over the weapon - which was being held by both attacker and policeman.</Para><Para>His colleague, Mr Abasolo, sat on Iskandar, forcing him into a prone position before a muffled "bang" echoed around the small room.</Para><Para>"We smelled gunpowder. I looked at Prakash and he looked at me; we both laughed nervously," the 30-year-old Filipino told The Sunday Times. "That was the first time we realised it was a real gun."</Para><Para>The two paramedics from Hope Ambulance Service were honoured for their actions in helping to subdue Iskandar on June 20, 2015.</Para><Para>DANGEROUS SITUATION</Para><Para>We smelled gunpowder. I looked at Prakash and he looked at me; we both laughed nervously. That was the first time we realised it was a real gun.</Para><Para>PARAMEDIC ELFREDO JOSE JR RELLITA ABASOLO, referring to his colleague, Mr Prakash Krishnan.</Para><Para>They received letters of appreciation from the police and a plaque from the hospital in recognition of their bravery.</Para><Para>"We were the only ones there. So we kaypoh lah," said 25-year-old Mr Prakash, using the Singlish term roughly translating as "acted as busybodies".</Para><Para>FIERCE STRUGGLE</Para><Para>The security officer got the revolver out of Iskandar's grip one finger at a time.</Para><Para>When the revolver was free, I kicked it away with my boot.</Para><Para>MR PRAKASH KRISHNAN</Para><Para>The two humble paramedics had been working for Hope Ambulance Service for about three years.</Para><Para>When they went to the room at about 7pm, they saw Staff Sgt Sadli holding on to Iskandar's leg.</Para><Para>"(Iskandar) was dragging the policeman while hitting his head with a baton," said Mr Abasolo.</Para><Para>The policeman had pushed the attacker back into the room to prevent him from escaping.</Para><Para>As Mr Prakash, a Malaysian, tried to intervene, Iskandar swung the baton at him, just missing his arm.</Para><Para>The paramedics withdrew and stood behind a wall outside the room. They entered the room again when they saw both men struggling over the "taser" - which was actually Staff Sgt Sadli's revolver.</Para><Para>BEYOND CALL OF DUTY</Para><Para>They chose to spontaneously respond to cries for help. Their actions went beyond the call of duty and I am humbled to have them in our team.</Para><Para>DR CHARLES JOHNSON, Hope Ambulance Service emergency physician.</Para><Para>They grabbed a pillow and blanket from a stretcher to shield themselves in case it went off.</Para><Para>However, the pair were forced to retreat when Mr Abasolo noticed a red laser dot pointing at the blanket Mr Prakash was holding as he entered the room.</Para><Para>A third opportunity to help came when Staff Sgt Sadli managed to pull Iskandar onto the ground.</Para><Para>As the first shot was fired, the paramedics were quickly reminded of the danger they faced. They immediately shouted for help, warning others about the loaded gun.</Para><Para>*</Para><Para>Life jail term, caning</Para><Para>*</Para><Para>Muhammad Iskandar Sa'at fired three shots from a revolver he had snatched from a policeman.</Para><Para>*</Para><Para>Last Monday, Muhammad Iskanpdar Sa'at, 26, was jailed for life and given 18 strokes of the cane for firing three shots from a revolver he had snatched from a policeman.</Para><Para>Police Staff Sergeant Muhammad Sadli Razali's thumb and foot were injured by two of the shots fired.</Para><Para>The incident - an attempt to escape custody - occurred at Khoo Teck Puat Hospital on June 20, 2015, at about 7pm.</Para><Para>Earlier that day, Iskandar had been charged and remanded for vehicle theft. He was later escorted to the hospital by two policemen for medical treatment.</Para><Para>Court documents show that Iskandar had first attacked Staff Sgt Sadli with an intravenous drip pole while in a room meant for patients in police custody. He later hit the officer at least 13 times with the police T-baton before snatching the revolver and firing it.</Para><Para>In the High Court, the prosecution had argued for a deterrent punishment, saying: "The attack took place during visiting hours in a public hospital when there would invariably be significant human traffic. Such an act of wanton violence in a public place necessarily raises public disquiet and necessitates a heavier sentence."</Para><Para>Iskandar's defence lawyers said he had last injected himself with heroin about 27 hours before the incident and was struggling with acute withdrawal.</Para><Para>His attempt to escape was to explain himself to his girlfriend's family and his parents, according to defence lawyer Shashi Nathan.</Para><Para>Zaihan Mohamed Yusof</Para><Para>Staff Sgt Sadli, who was bleeding from the head after being hit with the baton, moaned "I'm hit, I'm hit" when a bullet struck his foot.</Para><Para>In the next 15 seconds, two more shots rang out from under the pillow. Staff Sgt Sadli was shot again, this time, in his thumb. The wounded officer started to turn pale and lose consciousness.</Para><Para>Help came when three hospital security officers appeared and the policeman was taken to safety.</Para><Para>With two security officers helping to pin down Iskandar, the third assisted Mr Prakash in removing the revolver from Iskandar's right hand.</Para><Para>Mr Prakash used both hands to grab Iskandar's wrist while his knee pressed against the gunman's arm.</Para><Para>"The security officer got the revolver out of Iskandar's grip one finger at a time," said Mr Prakash. "When the revolver was free, I kicked it away with my boot."</Para><Para>With the help of two of the security officers, Mr Abasolo managed to handcuff Iskandar, who had to be sedated twice before he finally stopped resisting.</Para><Para>After the drama, Mr Abasolo went to finish some paperwork at the hospital, his hands still trembling.</Para><Para>However Mr Prakash was worried that his employer would reprimand them for putting their lives in danger. Instead, their courage was appreciated. Dr Charles Johnson, Hope Ambulance Service emergency physician, said: "They chose to spontaneously respond to cries for help. Their actions went beyond the call of duty and I am humbled to have them in our team."</Para><Para>After their shift that night, the two paramedics went for ice cream.</Para><Para>Looking back, Mr Abasolo said their instinct to help was strong.</Para><Para>"If we let the guy (Iskandar) go, he could have run amok and shot other people at the hospital. I wouldn't be able to live with myself if that happened."</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Zaihan Mohamed Yusof </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Paramedics Prakash Krishnan and Elfredo Jose Jr Rellita Abasolo in a posed shot with three "bullet holes". They had thought a patient and a policeman were tussling over a taser when they went to the latter's aid. </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

