<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180327ee3s0048t" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180327ee3s0048t</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180327ee3s0048t" fid="an"/><Num value="1096" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180328" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="27"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Community</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">GenerationGrit; Finding his way through a pit of rage</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Mr Dominique Dillon grew up without his father, and the void filled him with anger and sorrow. But the unwavering support of other adults showed him a life with love and hope, and today he devotes himself to paying it forward, he tells The ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Theresa Tan </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180327ee3s0048t</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180327ee3s0048t" fid="an"/><Num value="1096" fid="wc"/><Num value="4551" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180328" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180327" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180327" fid="md"/><Time value="234521" fid="upt"/><Time value="234521" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId277629244"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashE85B5FE9CAF5B7B6"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NONS"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018592-20180327-145232"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001004-20180327-161428"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Community</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">GenerationGrit; Finding his way through a pit of rage</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Mr Dominique Dillon grew up without his father, and the void filled him with anger and sorrow. But the unwavering support of other adults showed him a life with love and hope, and today he devotes himself to paying it forward, he tells The Straits Times in this series about inspiring millennials.</Para><Para>Mr Dominique Dillon, 28, remembers vividly the first time he knew he was different from other children.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>He was with other seven-year-old classmates, and it dawned on him that they all had a father, except him.</Para><Para>His parents were never married.</Para><Para>"I felt left out and ashamed of who I was," the only child said. "I would tell them my dad had died. But some of them still called me a bastard child and poked fun at me."</Para><Para>For as long as he could remember, he had felt rejected and unwanted by his father, a man he met only a few times, but whose presence he missed.</Para><Para>He and his mother, Madam Theresa Anthonysamy, who died about five months ago, struggled. She suffered from bipolar disorder, a mental illness marked by extreme mood swings, and had heart and kidney problems, which made it hard for her to work.</Para><Para>*</Para><Para>GENERATION GRIT: Know of a Singaporean aged 35 or below who has shown grit amid life's adversities? E-mail us at stnewsdesk@sph.com.sg</Para><Para>The pair depended on financial aid from the Government and a Catholic group, as well as maintenance from his father.</Para><Para>His mother had been a nursing aide who quit her job to care for her baby son. She told him she and his father had planned to marry but things did not work out.</Para><Para>He said: "Life was not easy for us, but mum always made sure there was food on the table and I had all the love and discipline I needed."</Para><Para>But even with food on the table and a roof over their heads (his mother owned a three-room flat), he often felt, growing up, that he was trying not to drown in a pit of rage and shame. The bleakest point came when his mother was hospitalised when he was 12 years old. There was no one to care for him and he was sent to live in a home for boys for about half a year.</Para><Para>He said: "I felt the most alone then and the older kids bullied me."</Para><Para>After his mother was discharged from hospital, she visited him at the home every day without fail. Eventually, he went home to live with her.</Para><Para>But by the time he was in secondary school, his rage was threatening to consume him. He would blow up at the smallest slights in school. At home, he fought with his mother over little things. They loved each other dearly, but he said he could not deal with his own pain, much less her mood swings and depression.</Para><Para>"We were like two angry lions fighting," he said. "I felt no one understood my pain. And I was furious because I felt some looked down on me for being in the Normal (Technical) stream."</Para><Para>Once, as the class monitor, he was trying to get the class to be quiet and settle down for the next lesson. When one boy would not sit down, Mr Dillon threw a chair at him.</Para><Para>His teacher saw the whole thing and, realising he needed professional help, referred him to Care Singapore, a charity that helps vulnerable young people.</Para><Para>Looking back, Mr Dillon can recognise the guardian angels who helped to save him - and his mother as well.</Para><Para>There were the youth workers from Care Singapore, who counselled him and showed him how to deal with his inner turmoil.</Para><Para>There was his benefactor, who paid his school fees and gave him an allowance of $300 every month while he was at Nanyang Polytechnic. Mr Dillon got to know the businessman through the Catholic group that was helping his family.</Para><Para>And there were the men he looked up to in church - Father Gerard Louis, a priest, and Mr Prem Augustine, a youth leader - who were unstinting in their patience with him and guidance. In many ways, they were his father figures.</Para><Para>"Through them, I felt loved despite my brokenness and ugliness. It breathed new life into me," Mr Dillon said. "Without all of them, I could have been a school dropout."</Para><Para>With the support of these other adults in his life, he graduated with a diploma in mechatronics engineering. But he knew that his career lay elsewhere.</Para><Para>Others had reached out to him when he was poor, lost and abandoned. He wanted to do the same for young people who were in similar predicaments. He said some people advised him not to go into youth work, as they felt it paid a lot less than an engineer.</Para><Para>"But my mum, who was always my biggest supporter, told me to follow my heart and not to worry about money," he said.</Para><Para>He is now a youth worker at Care Singapore, where he teaches teenagers life skills, such as dealing with peer pressure and conflict.</Para><Para>He said: " I can identify with their needs and pain, and this helps me to better relate to them so I can help make a difference in their lives."</Para><Para>Ms Suria Basri, a counsellor at Care Singapore who worked with Mr Dillon when he was a teenager, is proud of him.</Para><Para>"I have seen his resilience and now he is paying it forward," she said. "Because of his background, he understands what youth are going through and he empathises with them. He has a lot of passion in helping young people."</Para><Para>While life has become more comfortable now that he is earning an income, his one big regret is that he did not do enough for his mother while she was alive.</Para><Para>She died of heart failure in October last year, at the age of 62.</Para><Para>"I miss her a lot and I feel a bit lost," he said. "My mum sacrificed everything for me. She loved me so much and never once gave up on me."</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Theresa Tan </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">Mr Dominique Dillon, 28, with a picture of his mother Theresa Anthonysamy, who died last year. His parents were never married and he had felt rejected and unwanted by his father. Now a youth worker, Mr Dillion said that when he was in secondary school, his rage led him to fight with his mother and blow up over the smallest slights. </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

