<DistDoc action="add" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="STIMES0020180325ee3q0030p" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210954" rl="100">BT, TODAY and Straits</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180325ee3q0030p</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180325ee3q0030p" fid="an"/><Num value="1211" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180326" fid="pd"/><SrcCode value="stimes" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="27"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Petra Nemcova, a supermodel with a heart for children</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>Petra Nemcova has set up a charity to rebuild schools in areas affected by natural disasters and bring education to kids</Para><Para>Czech supermodel, entrepreneur and philanthropist Petra Nemcova, 38, was in Singapore recently to attend a fund-raiser ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">Lydia Vasko </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"/><Code value="apacz"/><Code value="asiaz"/><Code value="seasiaz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcha"/><Code value="glife"/><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="gcom"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">STIMES0020180325ee3q0030p</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="STIMES0020180325ee3q0030p" fid="an"/><Num value="1211" fid="wc"/><Num value="5289" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180326" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="234522" fid="upt"/><Time value="234522" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="0" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="STIMES"/><Code value="fspFileId276728626"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="ASIA"/><Code value="CLNTBLK"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="SEASIAZ"/><Code value="SFSTR"/><Code value="SINGP"/><Code value="TAPN"/><Code value="TBNC"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TGPW"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBAS"/><Code value="TNST"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHashEFFA2D6CBAAC02F1"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATNS"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC110491"/><Code value="FSPRBC585719"/><Code value="FSPRBC621444"/><Code value="FSPRBC847446"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="SPH" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Singapore Press Holdings Limited</PublisherN><AttribCode value="STIMES" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="STIMES" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Straits Times</SrcName><Logo img="stimesLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="singp"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Singapore</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="70"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="621444"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018584-20180325-144929"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="apacz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia Pacific</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="asiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="seasiaz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Southeast Asia</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:singp"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcha"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Charities/Philanthropy</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishNS_en_20180320142642"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="308"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="585719"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018584-20180325-144929"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="glife"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Living/Lifestyle</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="847446"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018584-20180325-144929"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gcha"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:glife"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gcom"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Society/Community</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gcha"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001002-20180325-161629"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Petra Nemcova, a supermodel with a heart for children</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>Petra Nemcova has set up a charity to rebuild schools in areas affected by natural disasters and bring education to kids</Para><Para>Czech supermodel, entrepreneur and philanthropist Petra Nemcova, 38, was in Singapore recently to attend a fund-raiser for the Indonesian arm of her charity, Happy Hearts Fund.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>She started the charity - which rebuilds schools in areas that have been impacted by natural disasters - in 2006 and has built more than 170 schools in 10 countries since, including Thailand, Mexico, Nepal and Indonesia.</Para><Para>Nemcova witnessed the pain and destruction natural disasters can cause first-hand when she was seriously injured in the 2004 tsunami while vacationing in Khao Lak, Thailand, with her fiance, British fashion photographer Simon Atlee.</Para><Para>She survived the deadly waves by clinging to a palm tree for eight hours before she was rescued, suffering internal injuries and a severely broken pelvis. However, Atlee drowned, one of an estimated 230,000 to 280,000 people in 14 countries around the Indian Ocean who lost their lives in the disaster.</Para><Para>After her recovery, Nemcova returned to Thailand to help the relief efforts and learnt how schools are often the last structures to be rebuilt, leaving children without access to education for months or even years.</Para><Para>Based in Miami, Florida, the cheerful, down-to-earth model has already spent two weeks on the road. After just a day in Singapore, she flew to Jakarta, the start of a two-month itinerary which would take her to New Zealand, France, the Czech Republic, New York, Puerto Rico, Thailand and Mexico to promote the Happy Hearts Fund.</Para><Para>1. How do you stay focused and energised through your travels?</Para><Para>Green tea and 85 per cent dark chocolate. Dark chocolate is my guilty pleasure - it makes me happy and gives me energy, and I eat at least a bar a day. I eat gluten-free, am vegan and do not have desserts orsweets, except dark chocolate. It's my only vice.</Para><Para>I also meditate for about 20 minutes every day. It is the first thing I do before my feet touch the floor. It has been my anchor for 19 years and, without it, I don't think I could do all that I do.</Para><Para>2. Where does your philanthropic drive come from?</Para><Para>I grew up under communism in a very poor family, where we were barely putting food on the table.</Para><Para>Dark chocolate is my guilty pleasure – it makes me happy and gives me energy, and I eat at least a bar a day... It's my only vice.</Para><Para>SUPERMODEL PETRA NEMCOVA on her indulgence</Para><Para>You do not have many opportunities under communism. You have no freedom of travel orspeech. My parents could not do what they wanted in their adult lives because they had to follow the system.</Para><Para>I was 11 when communism fell and, from a young age, I understood the value of opportunities and being able to do what you love.</Para><Para>Because of this, I travel and take every opportunity I can. Each one is a gift and blessing, and understanding that is one of the reasons for my drive. It is also why I work to give opportunities to as many children around the world as possible.</Para><Para>Secondly, when I was modelling before the tsunami, I saw how diverse the world is and how many people struggle so unnecessarily.</Para><Para>I would be in the most amazing hotel for a photo shoot and, right next to it, there were people living in shacks. That was a big eye-opener to see the contrast and I felt I could do something about it, even if only in a small way.</Para><Para>3. Why are education and building schools the focus of the Happy Hearts Fund?</Para><Para>Without education, children cannot get out of the cycle of poverty and the manipulation, abuse and health concerns which come with it, especially in the rural areas.</Para><Para>Education is the only opportunity for them to feel empowered and know their rights and the options that are open to them in the world.</Para><Para>With an education and the better job opportunities that follow, children can empower themselves and their whole family.</Para><Para>4. What is the biggest challenge you face in your charity work?</Para><Para>More than 5,000 schools were destroyed by earthquakes in Nepal.</Para><Para>In many places, 90 per cent of the community was completely destroyed in what are already extremely poor, rural areas where the people's only way to survive is working the land.</Para><Para>You have these schools which need support and you want to help many children, but you cannot because you have limited funding.</Para><Para>You have to make very hard decisions about which children are going to get the opportunities and which will not and it is only a matter of funds. That is the biggest challenge.</Para><Para>5. Of the titles used to describe you - model, philanthropist and entrepreneur - which means the most to you?</Para><Para>I do not associate myself with one and I do not describe myself as either or. I am a human being, a citizen of the universe who feels at home in many countries and has the responsibility to make the world better. I have received many gifts in life and it is my responsibility to share these gifts.</Para><Para>My fashion work is helping my philanthropy and the things I have learnt from philanthropy, I can apply to business. That is the beauty of it.</Para><Para>6. You have said it is important for you to live life fully and meaningfully. What does that mean for you?</Para><Para>Practically speaking, it means appreciating every day and moment because they are a gift. Most people can never connect with this idea because we get used to thinking we are invincible, but we are not.</Para><Para>Nature can swing her arm, something can happen and your whole life can be changed. Everything you have or the people you love can be gone.</Para><Para>There is really a preciousness of every moment and every day. That is what I mean by living fully, the appreciation of the moment.</Para><Para>To live meaningfully is to lift the people around us. Once people start helping others, even in a small way such as helping the elderly with their shopping, that personal connection brings the biggest happiness in life.</Para><Para>7. What are you most proud of in your life?</Para><Para>The only way I could use the word "proud" is to say I am proud of the Happy Hearts teams and the work they do, and of our volunteers who give selflessly.</Para><Para>I am in awe and grateful for them, but I would never use the word "proud" for myself. It is not a word I connect with.</Para><Para>To me, the word "proud" means I am satisfied with what I have done and I am not. There are still so many children who need support and there is so much more to do.</Para><Para>8. How would you like to be remembered?</Para><Para>I would like to be remembered as someone who has lived life fully and meaningfully.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">Lydia Vasko </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field">A survivor of the 2004 tsunami, Czech supermodel and philanthropist Petra Nemcova says it is a challenge to help many children because funding is limited. </Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">(c) 2018 Singapore Press Holdings Limited </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

