<DistDoc action="rep" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="WSJO000020180321ee3l0038p" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210958" rl="100">WSJ</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">EA31E8BE80704A80080BC93A321E1105 SB10260750186020754861004584111402772693252</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="WSJO000020180321ee3l0038p" fid="an"/><Num value="1818" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180321" fid="pd"/><Time value="145600" fid="et"/><SrcCode value="wsjo" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Wall Street Journal Online</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="26"/><S value="60"/><M value="74"/><L value="140"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm">Your Health</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">IVF Testing Spurs a Debate Over 'Mosaic' Embryos; Some women hoping to get pregnant—and the doctors treating them—agonize over using embryos with some abnormal cells</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>It was her last chance.</Para><Para>MaryJo Dunn had been trying to get pregnant through in-vitro fertilization for 20 months.</Para><Para>At age 45, she expected it to be challenging. But giving up wasn't easy. She and her husband had lost their only child, a ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By Sumathi Reddy </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc. All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="namz"/><Code value="usa"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="ghea"/><Code value="ncolu"/><Code value="ncat"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">EA31E8BE80704A80080BC93A321E1105 SB10260750186020754861004584111402772693252</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="WSJO000020180321ee3l0038p" fid="an"/><Num value="1818" fid="wc"/><Num value="8534" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180321" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180321" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="md"/><Time value="145600" fid="et"/><Time value="145702" fid="upt"/><Time value="063242" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="4" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="WSJO"/><Code value="fspFileId275395876"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="CTGSMFS"/><Code value="CTGWSJ"/><Code value="DEEPWSJP"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="IBNK"/><Code value="IFINAL"/><Code value="IINV"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="SFWSJ"/><Code value="TBAC"/><Code value="TBED"/><Code value="TBIZ"/><Code value="TBRK"/><Code value="TDJP"/><Code value="TDJWMNP"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TFIN"/><Code value="TIAS"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TIMG"/><Code value="TINT"/><Code value="TIOP"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRD"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="fspWebpage"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash1ACD3DD6332B5036"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCO"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC799842"/><Code value="FSPRBC803821"/><Code value="FSPRBC808880"/><Code value="FSPRBC830855"/><Code value="FSPRBC831151"/><Code value="FSPRBC849276"/><Code value="FSPRBC849559"/><Code value="FSPRBC852186"/><Code value="FSPRBC857584"/><Code value="FSPRBC860298"/><Code value="FSPRBC860312"/><Code value="FSPRBC861461"/><Code value="FSPRBC861689"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="DJENT" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc.</PublisherN><AttribCode value="WSJO2" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="WSJO" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Wall Street Journal Online</SrcName><Logo img="wsjoLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="re"><Code value="namz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">North America</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="861461"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:usa"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="usa"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">United States</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="861689"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="860298"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:ghea"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ghea"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Health</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="860312"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/><CodeA name="rule" value="799842"/><CodeA name="rule" value="803821"/><CodeA name="rule" value="830855"/><CodeA name="rule" value="831151"/><CodeA name="rule" value="849276"/><CodeA name="rule" value="849559"/><CodeA name="rule" value="857584"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncolu"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Columns</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="808880"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018570-20180321-194323"/><CodeA name="rule" value="852186"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="ncat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Content Types</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:ncolu"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00000998-20180321-161406"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipc">N/GEN N/HLT R/NME R/US </DescField><DescField fid="ipd">COLUMN YES WSJ.com WSJ.com Site Search WSJAsia WSJEurope WSJ Japanese Online WSJ-PRO-WSJ.com SB102607501860207548610045841114027726932521 SYND CODES_REVIEWED Free All FREE Your Health </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field">Your Health</ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">IVF Testing Spurs a Debate Over 'Mosaic' Embryos; Some women hoping to get pregnant—and the doctors treating them—agonize over using embryos with some abnormal cells</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>It was her last chance.</Para><Para>MaryJo Dunn had been trying to get pregnant through in-vitro fertilization for 20 months.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>At age 45, she expected it to be challenging. But giving up wasn't easy. She and her husband had lost their only child, a 17-month-old son, two years earlier to a rare type of cancer.</Para><Para>The Dunns were running out of time and money. They had already spent more than $70,000 on fertility treatments and taken out a loan. But the doctor recommended against implanting Ms. Dunn's two remaining embryos, she recalls, because of the results of genetic tests on them. However, a counselor at the testing lab explained that the embryos weren't technically abnormal. One was undetermined because the DNA in the sample was of poor quality. The other was a type known as "mosaic," an embryo with both normal and abnormal cells.</Para><Para>"At that point I didn't know that there was even a possibility of transferring mosaic embryos or that they could result in a healthy baby," Ms. Dunn says. After discussion with her doctor, she decided to go ahead and in December gave birth to two healthy baby girls, Riley and Kelsey. Her daughters are fraternal twins, one from the mosaic embryo.</Para><Para>Mosaic embryos and the test that detects them—preimplantation genetic screening—are complicating choices for women hoping to have children and stirring contention among fertility doctors. Mosaic embryos weren't easily detectable until about two years ago, when the technology for the test improved. A number of studies conclude that mosaic embryos represent about 20% of all embryos created through in-vitro fertilization.</Para><Para>When a woman undergoes IVF, her eggs are retrieved and combined with sperm to grow an embryo in a lab. Before an embryo is put into a women, she can opt for the genetic test that determines if it is normal, abnormal or mosaic based on the number of chromosomes in a small sample of cells. The main risk mosaic embryos pose is miscarriage, experts say. There isn't evidence that such embryos pose a higher risk of birth defects, they add, though larger studies are needed in order to rule that out definitively.</Para><Para>A committee of the American Society for Reproductive Medicine published <ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.fertstert.org/article/S0015-0282(18)30002-5/fulltext">an opinion on embryo screening </ELink> this week in the journal Fertility and Sterility. On the question of mosaic embryos, the committee didn't have enough information to form an opinion on what percentage of normal cells is needed to be recommended for use, says Alan Penzias, an associate professor at Harvard Medical School and chairman of the practice committee.</Para><Para>However, the fact that the latest generation of tests are reporting higher rates of mosaicism in embryos raises questions about the validity of the diagnosis, Dr. Penzias says. "If the less refined technology missed it, but pregnancies were still happening, it seems likely that the mosaics were probably being called normal before."</Para><Para>How labs interpret the results is part of the debate. Some independent labs that conduct the tests say many clinics don't tell patients if they have a mosaic embryo, leaving the lab with only two choices for classifying them: either normal or abnormal.</Para><Para>Santiago Munne, the former chief scientific officer of CooperGenomics, a New Jersey-based genetic-testing lab that is one of the largest in the country, estimated that about half of fertility clinics don't want to know if an embryo tests as mosaic. "There is quite a bit of resistance from doctors," says Dr. Munne, who recently left CooperGenomics to start another company. "They want the results to say 'normal' or 'abnormal.' The onus is then placed on the testing lab to really make a false choice because they're not normal and they're not abnormal. They are in-between and they have some potential."</Para><Para>Sarah Yarnall, global product director for PGS at CooperGenomics, says fertility clinics are wary but that things are changing as they learn more about mosaicism. "More providers are wanting this information and understand the benefit of having it though it's not 100% fully embraced by any means yet," she says.</Para><Para>Studies have found that a mosaic embryo develops into a healthy baby about a third of the time. A study published in January in Fertility and Sterility showed that 78 mosaic embryos resulted in the births of 24 healthy babies. A comparison group of 251 normal embryos resulted in 117 such births.</Para><Para>In <ELink type="webpage" ref="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29307401">an editorial accompanying the study</ELink>, Glenn Schattman, associate professor of reproductive medicine at Weill Cornell Medical College in New York, notes that what was surprising is that even embryos with up to 50% of abnormal cells implanted at the same rate as those that tested as normal. And though embryos with more than half abnormal cells had lower implantation and birth rates, the pregnancies still resulted in healthy births, suggesting the abnormal cells were either eliminated or repaired.</Para><Para>The results, Dr. Schattman says, raise the bigger question of whether the testing should be done at all. "You might biopsy an area that's all abnormal cells and that's the only spot with abnormal cells," he says. "The area might be chromosomally abnormal but it doesn't represent the rest of the embryo."</Para><Para>"I think there are a lot of patients undergoing PGS that are missing opportunities to have their genetic children because of it," he adds.</Para><Para>Some clinics discourage patients from having PGS tests of their embryos. "I think most clinics like ours really struggle with it," says Richard Paulson, a professor and vice chair of the obstetrics and gynecology department at the University of Southern California. His clinic seldom recommends PGS testing of embryos. "With the mosaic embryos you have to have this long discussion with the patient. We don't know what it means and they don't know what it means," he says.</Para><Para>Other doctors argue against implanting mosaic embryos. CCRM, a Colorado-based fertility clinic, has a policy against doing IVF with mosaic embryos, says Mandy Katz-Jaffe, scientific and genetics director. Dr. Katz-Jaffe says clinic researchers analyzed 50 mosaic embryos donated by patients for research and found abnormal cells both outside and inside the embryo, which she sees as an indication that they could have resulted in babies with genetic defects.</Para><Para>Richard Scott, clinical and scientific director of RMA of New Jersey, says the question of implanting a mosaic embryo rarely comes up because usually there are normal ones to use. Most couples don't want to take the risk of miscarriage that comes with implantation of a mosaic embryo, he says. "They've had very long and difficult reproductive histories."</Para><Para>A spokeswoman for Invitae, a San Francisco-based genetic-testing company, says it classifies any embryo with evidence of an abnormality as abnormal, not mosaic. "Most of our clients do not request information on mosaicism," she wrote in an email.</Para><Para>Igenomix, a genetic-testing company based in Valencia, Spain, tests embryos for about 200 U.S. clinics. Roughly 80% of those clinics classify embryos as either normal or abnormal and don't want to know if one tests mosaic, says Carlos Simón, Igenomix's chief scientific officer.</Para><Para>In a survey of 264 women who had undergone IVF in the past year, more than half said they weren't told that PGS could reveal mosaic embryos, according to <ELink type="webpage" ref="https://www.fertilityiq.com/">a recent survey</ELink> by FertilityIQ, a San Francisco-based website with patient reviews of fertility doctors. More than 80% said they would want to know if an embryo were mosaic.</Para><Para>"Before patients pony up the cost of doing PGS, they should be told that ambiguity is going to be reflected in this test," says Jake Anderson, who started the website with his wife Deborah in 2015. "A lot of clinics are not breaking out in a properly refined way information that we know is medically pertinent. I see that as a major problem."</Para><Para>Ms. Dunn, the Connecticut mother, attributes her decision to move forward with the mosaic embryo to Dina Nusblat, a genetic counselor at CooperGenomics. Ms. Nusblat told her that some women had transferred mosaic embryos and had healthy babies.</Para><Para>The Dunns went back to their doctor, Lawrence Engmann, a reproductive endocrinologist at the Center for Advanced Reproductive Services in Farmington, and pressed him on using the embryos. Dr. Engmann says he recommended against the mosaic embryo because the clinic's policy at the time was not to use them.</Para><Para>After signing various legal waivers, he agreed to implant the mosaic embryo and the "undetermined" one in Ms. Dunn. The twins were born six weeks early, on Dec. 15. They went home on Christmas Day. "The girls have given us so much joy and reason to want to keep going," Ms. Dunn says. She realizes that her story is unusual. "It's a tricky thing," she says. "But I just want people to know that there's this possibility with these mosaic embryos."</Para><Para>Do you have a story about infertility treatment? Write to Sumathi Reddy at <ELink type="webpage" ref="mailto:sumathi.reddy@wsj.com">sumathi.reddy@wsj.com</ELink> or follow her on Twitter at <ELink type="webpage" ref="https://twitter.com/rddysum">@rddysu</ELink></Para><Para>Do you have a story about infertility treatment? Write to health columnist Sumathi Reddy at sumathi.reddy@wsj.com or on Twitter at @rddysum</Para><Para>Testing Embryos</Para><Para>When women undergo in-vitro fertilization, doctors combine their eggs with a sperm to form an embryo in the lab. Over the next five days, the embryo grows from one cell to about 100. Preimplantation genetic screening, or PGS, entails extracting five to seven cells from the outer part of the embryo—the part that will eventually form the placenta—on day five.</Para><Para>The cells are sent to a lab for genetic testing. The test, which usually costs between $4,000 and $5,000, isn't required to undergo IVF and less than half of women have it done. It usually isn't covered by insurance. PGS is done to determine which embryos have the best chance of implanting and producing a healthy baby.</Para><Para>Until about two years ago, the test only distinguished between normal and abnormal embryos. If an embryo's cells have the correct number of chromosomes—46—it is labeled euploid, or normal. Such embryos have a 50% to 60% chance of resulting in a baby. If an embryo has cells with a missing or extra chromosome it is considered aneuploid, or abnormal, and not recommended for use. With the use of next-generation sequencing technology came a finer degree of resolution and PGS became able to identify mosaic embryos. These are embryos with a mix of normal and abnormal cells. Some experts say as many as 20% of embryos created for IVF are mosaic.</Para><Para>—Sumathi Reddy </Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By Sumathi Reddy </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc. All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="https://www.wsj.com/articles/ivf-testing-spurs-a-debate-over-mosaic-embryos-1521644178" type="webpage"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

