<DistDoc action="rep" dist="dist_id" distdocver="05.1" an="WSJO000020180322ee3m005v5" doctype="article"><SelectData><FolderName id="302210958" rl="100">WSJ</FolderName></SelectData><ReplyItem lang="en"><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><IPDocId fid="id">18A4F534068CB8FF2902B3D3C4892D3A SB11115384206897403412704584097293833686808</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="WSJO000020180322ee3m005v5" fid="an"/><Num value="1372" fid="wc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><Time value="184400" fid="et"/><SrcCode value="wsjo" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Wall Street Journal Online</SrcName><TruncRules><XS value="30"/><S value="54"/><M value="75"/><L value="137"/></TruncRules><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Why Bogotá is Now on Ambitious Travelers' Agendas; The Colombian capital is suddenly in the travel spotlight, thanks to new luxury hotels, inventive restaurants and a street scene so lively it makes the country's darker days seem like ancient history</Para></Headline></Title><Snippet><Para>EVER SINCE COLOMBIA began shrugging off its don't-think-of-visiting status, Cartagena and Medellín have emerged as glamorous tourist destinations. But until recently, Bogotá, the country's capital and largest metropolis, held little ...</Para></Snippet><Byline fid="by">By Finn-Olaf Jones </Byline><Credit fid="cr"></Credit><Copyright fid="cy">Copyright 2018 Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc. All Rights Reserved. </Copyright><CodeSets><CSet fid="co"><Code value="rvlfcl"/></CSet><CSet fid="re"><Code value="bogota"/><Code value="col"/><Code value="lamz"/><Code value="samz"/><Code value="devgcoz"/><Code value="dvpcoz"/></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"/><Code value="glife"/><Code value="gtour"/></CSet></CodeSets></ReplyItem><MetadataPT><DocData><DocType value="article" fid="fmt"/><IPDocId fid="id">18A4F534068CB8FF2902B3D3C4892D3A SB11115384206897403412704584097293833686808</IPDocId><AccessionNo value="WSJO000020180322ee3m005v5" fid="an"/><Num value="1372" fid="wc"/><Num value="6580" fid="cc"/><Date value="20180322" fid="pd"/><Date value="20180322" fid="upd"/><Date value="20180325" fid="md"/><Time value="184400" fid="et"/><Time value="184425" fid="upt"/><Time value="033023" fid="mt"/><BaseLang value="en" fid="la"/><Editor value="" fid="rve"/><RevisionNo value="9" fid="rvn"/></DocData><PubData><Restrictor fid="rst"><Code value="FSPNORMAWS0300"/><Code value="WSJO"/><Code value="fspFileId276517519"/><Code value="FUT"/><Code value="CLNTALL"/><Code value="CTGSMFS"/><Code value="CTGWSJ"/><Code value="DEEPWSJP"/><Code value="EN"/><Code value="IBNK"/><Code value="IFINAL"/><Code value="IINV"/><Code value="NAMZ"/><Code value="SFWSJ"/><Code value="TBAC"/><Code value="TBED"/><Code value="TBIZ"/><Code value="TBRK"/><Code value="TDJP"/><Code value="TDJWMNP"/><Code value="TFCDLIC"/><Code value="TFIN"/><Code value="TIAS"/><Code value="TIBMNB"/><Code value="TIMG"/><Code value="TINT"/><Code value="TIOP"/><Code value="TMNB"/><Code value="TMNBUS"/><Code value="TNPS"/><Code value="TNWP"/><Code value="TNWPN"/><Code value="TOPUSA"/><Code value="TSCH"/><Code value="TTRD"/><Code value="TTRK"/><Code value="TUSN"/><Code value="TWMSA"/><Code value="TYAS"/><Code value="TYLA"/><Code value="USA"/><Code value="fspWebpage"/><Code value="MPCV1M9M1B1"/><Code value="MPCEnvPROD"/><Code value="MPCDocHash1081BF1FFC12C8DE"/><Code value="FSPTHINGFINDER"/><Code value="FSP2YESCO"/><Code value="FSP2YESCOORG"/><Code value="FSPRBC"/><Code value="FSPRBCNS"/><Code value="FSP2YESNS"/><Code value="FSPCATEGORIZER"/><Code value="FSPCATRE"/><Code value="FSPRBCRE"/><Code value="FSP2YESRE"/><Code value="FSP2NOCOOC"/><Code value="FSP2NOIN"/><Code value="FSP2NOPEOC"/><Code value="FSPRBC621529"/><Code value="FSPRBC697648"/><Code value="FSPRBC720986"/><Code value="FSPRBC860298"/><Code value="FSPRBC860336"/><Code value="FSPRBC860450"/><Code value="FSPRBC861113"/><Code value="FSPRBC861362"/><Code value="FSPRBC861557"/><Code value="MPCCL"/><Code value="MPCJP"/><Code value="MPCKW"/><Code value="MPCKP"/><Code value="MPCESRE"/><Code value="MPCESIN"/><Code value="MPCESNS"/><Code value="FSP2AC"/></Restrictor><IPId value="DJENT" fid="ip"/><PublisherN fid="pub">Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc.</PublisherN><AttribCode value="WSJO2" fid="atr"/><SrcCode value="WSJO" fid="sc"/><SrcName fid="sn">The Wall Street Journal Online</SrcName><Logo img="wsjoLogo.gif" link="" src="http://logos.factiva.com"/></PubData><CodeSets><CSet fid="co"><Code value="rvlfcl"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia</CodeD><CodeI org="thingfinder" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="ptf--aboutCo-00004107-20180322-231424.dictionary"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="re"><Code value="bogota"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Bogota</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="220"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="720986"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="col"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Colombia</CodeD><CodeI org="categoriser" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="es-EnglishRE_en_20180319142019"/><CodeA name="es_score" value="196"/></CodeI><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="861113"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="621529"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:bogota"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="lamz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Latin America</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="861362"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:bogota"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:col"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="samz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">South America</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="861557"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:bogota"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:col"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="devgcoz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Emerging Market Countries</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:bogota"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:col"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="dvpcoz"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Developing Economies</CodeD><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:bogota"/><CodeA name="root" value="re:col"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code></CSet><CSet fid="ns"><Code value="gcat"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Political/General News</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="860298"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:glife"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gtour"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="0"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="glife"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Living/Lifestyle</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="860336"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/></CodeI><CodeI org="expansion" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="root" value="ns:gtour"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="1"/></CodeI></Code><Code value="gtour"><CodeD index="no" lang="en">Travel</CodeD><CodeI org="rbc" action="add"><CodeA name="rule" value="860450"/><CodeA name="db" value="prbc---00018581-20180324-194406"/><CodeA name="rule" value="697648"/></CodeI><CodeI org="validation" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="status" value="active"/></CodeI><CodeI org="hierarchy" action="add"><CodeA name="db" value="pedv---00001001-20180324-161425"/><CodeA name="nodelevel" value="2"/></CodeI></Code></CSet></CodeSets><DescTPC fid="de"><DescField fid="ipc">N/GEN N/LIF N/TVL R/CL R/LTM R/SM </DescField><DescField fid="ipd">WSJ.com WSJ.com Site Search WSJAsia WSJEurope WSJ Japanese Online WSJ-PRO-WSJ.com ART SCENE BOGOTA BEST CITIES IN COLOMBIA BEST OF BOGOTA BOGOTA SAFETY BOGOTA TRAVEL BOGOTA TRAVEL GUIDE COOLEST NEIGHBORHOODS IN BOGOTA THINGS TO DO IN BOGOTA WHAT TO SEE AND DO IN BOGOTA WHERE TO GO IN BOGOTA WHERE TO STAY IN BOGOTA SB111153842068974034127045840972938336868081 SYND CODES_REVIEWED Off Duty Travel </DescField><DescField fid="ipcns">OLEM OTRA </DescField></DescTPC></MetadataPT><ArchiveDoc xml:space="preserve"><Article markup="pp0" lang="en" index="field"><HandL fid="hlp"><Title fid="hl"><SectionName fid="se" index="field">Life</SectionName><ColumnName fid="clm" index="field"></ColumnName><Headline fid="hd"><Para lang="en">Why Bogotá is Now on Ambitious Travelers' Agendas; The Colombian capital is suddenly in the travel spotlight, thanks to new luxury hotels, inventive restaurants and a street scene so lively it makes the country's darker days seem like ancient history</Para></Headline></Title><LeadPara fid="lp"><Para>EVER SINCE COLOMBIA began shrugging off its don't-think-of-visiting status, Cartagena and Medellín have emerged as glamorous tourist destinations. But until recently, Bogotá, the country's capital and largest metropolis, held little interest for the outside world.</Para></LeadPara></HandL><TailParas fid="td"><Para>Geographically, the city has always been remote. The gold-mad Spanish built Bogotá deep in the country's interior, next to the indigenous Muisca tribal mines on a mountainous shelf 8,600 feet above sea level. From this lofty position, Bogotá rode out the country's darkest years, including the era of the cocaine conquistadors—the late 1970s through the 1990s—and the civil conflict with the FARC rebel group that dates to the 1960s and only officially ended in 2016. In just the last few years, Bogotá's been going stronger, reflecting the country's erupting optimism with new luxury hotels (including two Four Seasons properties), highly original restaurants and a kinetic cultural scene to go along with its second youth after decades of violence. And though Bogotá still has its dicey side—locals will tell you to keep your cellphone in your pocket to avoid theft—the city is far safer than before, with the homicide rate at its lowest in 40 years (and lower than some U.S. cities).</Para><Para>Like so many urban destinations on the rise but clogged by traffic, Bogotá has bred a vibrant bike scene—cars are even banned on the city's major thoroughfares on Sundays to give two wheelers more glide room. One afternoon, I took a bike tour led by a local artist, Mateo Mora, who led me from the cobblestoned Plaza del Chorro de Quevedo—site of the original Muisca settlement the Spanish built after their 1537 arrival—and north toward the wealthier suburbs. "Fifteen years ago, we wouldn't have gone here. There would have been too much crime," said Mr. Mora as we biked down the ancient street Carrera Séptima, which bisects the oldest part of town. Art lined our entire route. "In 1991, the Ministry of Culture established an arts program to subsidize street art here in the city," he explained, pointing out temporary van-sized wooden murals of fantastical jungles, seas and creatures created by his own art collective, MAL, along the leafy streets of the Teusaquillo neighborhood. Elsewhere, we kept stumbling across the sociopolitical works of DJ Lu, perhaps Bogotá's best-known graffiti artist; his signature combines a pineapple with a grenade.</Para><Para>The city's biggest bang for your buck—literally—is playing tejo, a uniquely Colombian sport where players lob pear-shaped metal pucks at baked triangles of gunpowder. At Los Bucaros, a tejo venue in the business district, you can play for free on a dozen indoor courts, as long as you keep buying bottles of chilled Joker beer ($1 apiece). The scene is part bowling alley, part beer hall with locals making ballet-like swings to send the pucks flying across the hall to hit the exploding tiles. As much as I enjoyed trying, I never mastered the technique.</Para><Para>A short stroll brought me to the cobblestoned heart of the city in the La Candelaria district, a maze of alleyways lined with wooden porches, trattorias and tiny pottery and fabric shops. In the sun, the district struck me as a surreal stone forest of shadows until I abruptly stumbled into stadium-sized Plaza de Bolivar, ringed by grand colonial buildings including the 19th-century Primatial Cathedral and the austerely elegant National Capitol.</Para><Para>I wandered four blocks north to the Museo del Oro, and entered with the same bored dread I saw on the faces of the hundreds of school kids packed in there. Moments later I was hypnotized. The exhibits, superbly designed, showcase a five millennia-tradition of goldsmithing in the region. One darkened room was dominated by a brilliantly illuminated helmet that could have come from a Flash Gordon comic—it dates back two millennia.</Para><Para>Once the sun set and La Candeleria became a ghost town I moved next door to Bogotá's newly hip La Merced neighborhood whose neo-Tudor buildings reminded me of a high-altitude London, right down to the cool modernist refurbishments. The Cine Tonalá, which has three art-house cinemas, a dance hall, bar and restaurant wedged into three floors, was the center of the action. Colombian black-and-white experimental shorts were screening in the upstairs movie theater while on the terrace local university students were downing beer and Colombia/Mexican fusion cuisine between smokes and surprisingly average coffee—a strange curse in Juan Valdez country. "The best coffee gets exported because foreigners pay the highest prices," a waiter explained. "Locals get the mediocre stuff."</Para><Para>But I did find exceptionally good coffee served out of Cognac glasses at Leo Cocina y Cava, a restaurant opened by Leonor Espinosa, star of the new scrum of chefs applying international techniques to Colombia's diverse and often unusual array of produce. "Colombian cuisine is based not on regions but ecosystems," said Ms. Espinosa, as a waiter served me one of her more exotic dishes: gelatinous sea snail topped by macadamia nuts and Andean spices. "We play incessantly with these strange ingredients we source from around the country until they work together." Those diners who don't thrill at the thought of gelatinous sea snail—personally, I found it deliciously ethereal—might prefer to experiment instead with one of the restaurant's many types of arrechón, bottles of homemade alcoholic concoctions. Ms. Espinosa told me that the recipes were brought over by slaves from Africa and are still produced by their descendants. The one I sampled tasted like almondy Bristol Cream.</Para><Para>Several other buzzy eateries dot the streets of Bogotá's uber-elegant Zona T neighborhood, tucked in between high-end boutiques and filling shiny new buildings. In the heart of Zona T, you'll find Andrés DC, a kitsch-plastered offshoot of a restaurant whose original location is just outside town. There, on my last night in Bogotá, I joined a friend of a friend, Sebastián Velásquez, a local media lawyer, for dinner of ajiaco con pollo, an amped-up chicken soup made with plantains, corn on the cob and lots of highland spices.</Para><Para>As the night progressed, the atmosphere turned rowdy. First, a marching band passed through. Later, one group of local ladies and then another climbed on to the tables to samba. "It's the party after the storm," said Sebastian.</Para><Para>THE LOWDOWN // Going Down to Bogotá, Colombia</Para><Para>Getting There: Several airlines offer direct flights to Bogotá from New York, Miami, Los Angeles, Atlanta and Fort Lauderdale, Fla. Keep in mind that Bogotá sits at 8,660 feet, which is 500 feet higher than Vail Ski Resort—so drink lots of water and be prepared to feel the altitude right off the plane.</Para><Para>Staying There: Four Seasons Hotel Casa Medina—one of two Bogotá properties opened by the hotel group in the last few years—occupies a 1940s historic landmark that was refitted with colonial panache. It features the high service standards one expects from the Four Seasons at a price one doesn't. From about $220 a night, <ELink type="webpage" ref="https://www.fourseasons.com/bogotacm/">fourseasons.com/bogotacm</ELink>. NH Collection Bogotá Andino Royal is a boutique hotel with a sleek Scando-modernistic vibe and a rooftop deck that overlooks the best shopping and nightlife spots in Zona T. From about $127 a night, <ELink type="webpage" ref="https://www.nh-hotels.com/">nh-hotels.com</ELink></Para><Para>Eating There: Leonor Espinosa's Leo Cocina y Cava serves nouveau Colombian cuisine in an airy contemporary setting. 6-75 Calle 27B, restauranteleo.com. For more traditional fare, try Misea, another restaurant from Ms. Espinosa, with two locations in town, featuring cuisine from Colombia's Atlantic coast such as shrimp with mashed cassava or cheese and yam soup. 27-50 Transversal, restaurantemisia.com. At the Andrés DC outpost in Zona T, Colombian comfort food and tall adult beverages are served in a hyperactive carnival atmosphere. 12-21 Calle 82, <ELink type="webpage" ref="http://www.andrescarnederes.com/">andrescarnederes.com</ELink>.</Para></TailParas><Byline fid="by" index="field">By Finn-Olaf Jones </Byline><Credit fid="cr" index="field"></Credit><Contact fid="ct" index="field"></Contact><Notes fid="rf" index="field"></Notes><Art fid="art" index="field"></Art><Copyright fid="cy" index="field">Copyright 2018 Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc. All Rights Reserved. </Copyright></Article></ArchiveDoc><AdocTOC adoctype="article"><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/ArchiveDoc::Article" type="arttext"></Item><Item size="0" ref="distdoc:archive/InvertText" type="invtext"></Item><Item subtype="primary" size="0" ref="https://www.wsj.com/articles/why-bogota-is-back-on-ambitious-travelers-agendas-1521744253" type="webpage"></Item></AdocTOC></DistDoc>

